<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fundamentals of the Protestant religion asserted by reason as well as Scriptvre written in French by the famous Monsieur de Gombaud ; made English by Sidnet Lodge ; to which is added his Letters to Monsieur de Militiere and other personages of the French-court upon the same subject.</title>
            <author>Gombauld, Jean Ogier de, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 249 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14808</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11845724</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11845724</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 532:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fundamentals of the Protestant religion asserted by reason as well as Scriptvre written in French by the famous Monsieur de Gombaud ; made English by Sidnet Lodge ; to which is added his Letters to Monsieur de Militiere and other personages of the French-court upon the same subject.</title>
                  <author>Gombauld, Jean Ogier de, d. 1666.</author>
                  <author>Lodge, Sidney, b. 1648 or 9.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 167 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W.C. M.G. and W.H. and sold by W. Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FUNDAMENTALS OF THE PROTESTANT RELIGION Aſſerted By REASON As well as <hi>SCRIPT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in <hi>French</hi> by the Famous <hi>MONSIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R de GOMBA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>D,</hi> Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> by <hi>SIDNEY LODGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, his Letters to <hi>MONSIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R de MILITIERE,</hi> And other Perſonages of the <hi>French-</hi>Court, upon the ſame Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. C. M. G.</hi> and <hi>W. H.</hi> and ſold by <hi>W. Davis</hi> in <hi>Amen-Corner.</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>BRIDGET</hi> COUNTESS OF PLYMOUTH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>DEdications are uſually made to Perſons of your Ladiſhip's high Character, as marks of Gratitude, or Reſpect due to 'em: This of mine is of that nature, there being no one to whom I owe more Acknowledgments, or a greater Honour than to your Ladiſhip. <hi>Romances</hi> and <hi>Playes</hi> are generally ſuch Books, whoſe Fronts are honour'd with Names of your Ladiſhip's Sex; but I have made choice of this Serious and Weighty Subject, as believing it moſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to your Inclinations. The Matter of it is <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Solid,</hi> but withal <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful,</hi> it being writ in an Eloquent, and yet unaffected <hi>Style;</hi> I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb facs="tcp:49837:3"/>
to make it not leſs ſo in our own <hi>Tongue.</hi> If your Honour finds any Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in the reading of it, I ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Pains I have taken in it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently requited; and nothing will more encourage me to Attempts of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than your Ladiſhip's Approbation of this. Becauſe ſuch Applications as theſe, if tedious, are preſumptive, I'll only beg leave humbly to aſſure Your Ladiſhip, that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honour's<lb/>
moſt Obliged, and<lb/>
moſt Humble Servant,<lb/>
                  <hi>SIDNEY LODGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Preface tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> gives you a ſhort account of the LIFE of the celebrated Author: I intend by this only to let you know, that the enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is ſo Rational Pithy, and full of Senſe, that it will ſufficiently recommend it ſelf, and withall, to beg you to read it with a due Attention and Candour. For my own part, I dare confidently ſay, I have been very faithful to the Original (having taken no more liberty than what a Tranſlator may juſtly claim) and yet I hope I may, without being thought Arrogant, affirm, that I have given it ſo much the proper Idiom of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that you'll find it eaſie, ſmooth, and Natural, and as pleaſing as 'tis uſeful; for ſuch a Mixture being moſt grateful, ought to be aimed at by thoſe who write. The Follies, the Superſtition, the Idolatry, the Tyrannical Uſurpation of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are here repreſented, in ſuch lively, and yet deform'd Colours, that no man who pretends to be reaſonable, but will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to avoid 'em. Can any one imagine himſelf ſafe under that Religion, where the
<pb facs="tcp:49837:4"/>
Name of God is onely made uſe of as a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, and inſtead of that <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſet up, and really <hi>worſhipped.</hi> Religion is both reveal'd and Natural, to inſtruct us fully: In the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, God has been graciouſly pleas'd to give us his Word, but the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manely forbid the reading it: To attain to a perfect knowledge of the latter, he has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du'd us with Reaſon, but that is enſlav'd by their poſitive Determinations: nay, they rob us of our Senſes too, by their eſtabliſh'd Principle of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> ſo that indeed the Peoples Religion does wholly conſiſt in a blind obedience to a <hi>Pretended-Infallible-Prieſt.</hi> How happy then are we! who are under a Government where the reading of the Scriptures, (the Rule of Faith) is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allowed, but commanded by the Church: A Church free from the Extremities, on one hand, of Idolatry, and on the other, of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm; ſo that here we have the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of improving both our Religion and our Reaſon, not being forbid the free Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the one, or oblig'd to do violence to the other; of being both good Chriſtians and Philoſophers, for the one may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the other, which is clearly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by this ſhort Treatiſe, which I hope will meet with a kind Entertainment in the World.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE FROM THE <hi>FRENCH.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THOSE who are acquainted with <hi>Monſieur de Gombaud,</hi> know, that he ſet a greater value on his Diſcourſes concerning Religion, than on any of his other Works. He was invited to write of that Subject, upon a pure charitable deſign of making the Truth known to ſuch who were yet under the darkneſs of Error, and to confirm thoſe in the true Faith, who were either born in, or had embraced it. He frequently complain'd of two things, the one was, that thoſe who writ concerning Religion, were too Volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, urging Proof upon Proof, and Authority upon Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, without being careful to obſerve a due Order, and clearneſs in their Diſcourſes: The other was, that many perſwaded themſelves, the <hi>true Doctrine</hi> was not conſiſtent with an <hi>Elegant Style.</hi> To ſhew how they were deceived in this particular, he compos'd his <hi>Conſiderations on the Chriſtian Religion</hi> when he was yet young, and in the Vigour of his Age; and in this has really demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that an Author may be both ſtrong and perſpicuous, ſhort and full, ſolid and elegant. Having communicated this Piece to many of his Friends, and even to ſome of the <hi>Roman Communion;</hi> it was ſo well eſteem'd by all of 'em, that he was encouraged after that to make a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> on
<pb facs="tcp:49837:5"/>
the Euchariſt, and then another, which he preſented to one of his Friends, under the Name of <hi>Ariſtander.</hi> Moſt of his Letters were writ in a much fuller Age. Through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Works, the ſtrength and admirable ingenuity of his Mind, his extraordinary faculty of thinking of, and expreſſing things, will be diſcover'd. I will ſay nothing of the Reaſons that oblig'd him to keep theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Writings private; I am ſure he paſſionately deſir'd to have publiſh'd 'em, believing they would be of great uſe, and it may be there has not yet been any Secular Man known in the World, who was more zealous for the Glory of God, or had a greater, or a more ſincere Love for his Neighbour than he had. But when the heat and earneſtneſs with which he writes, ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, and withal, it ſhall be conſider'd that all he had to ſubſiſt on, did abſolutely depend on Court, it will not be thought ſtrange that he did not make 'em Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick in his Life-time. That the World might not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of 'em after his Death, which it might, if they had fallen into the hands of any who were not of his Religion, he put 'em in his latter days into thoſe of a good Friend, whoſe Fidelity and Kindneſs he had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd, whom he oblig'd to promiſe him to keep 'em ſafe, till a convenient Opportunity offer'd it ſelf to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh 'em. This Friend always deſign'd to perform theſe Deſires, and his own Promiſe; but beſides the difficulty of Printing things of this Nature in the Kingdom, he met with many other Impediments. At length, after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Attempts and Delays, he reſolved to make the dear Children of his Friend change their Climate, in hopes that when they return'd home, tho' in a ſtrange Garb, they would be own'd as truly <hi>French.</hi> I leave the Reader to judge of their Merits, and of thoſe of their Father. His Works have long ſince made him ſo well known in <hi>France,</hi> and in other Nations too, where they underſtood, and lov'd the Tongue, that 'twill be needleſs to ſay any thing of 'em to thoſe who have but ſeen his <hi>Eudymion,</hi> his <hi>Letters in Proſe,</hi> his <hi>Paſtoral of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marante,</hi> his <hi>Tragedy of the Danaides,</hi> his <hi>Collection of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaneous
<pb facs="tcp:49837:5"/>
Poems,</hi> in which are his incomparable <hi>Sonnets,</hi> eſpecially thoſe called the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and his <hi>Epigrams,</hi> of which there are Three Books. And this is to give notice to ſuch who may not poſſibly have met with 'em, that there are ſuch Books, that they may have the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of having the ſame knowledge and opinion of 'em that others had.</p>
            <p>Beſides he left a <hi>Tragicomidy of Cydippe,</hi> and looſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers enough to have made a new <hi>Collection of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems,</hi> eſpecially <hi>Sonnets and Epigrams;</hi> but having fallen into the hands of ſuch who did not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe things, have not yet ſeen the Light. I could very much enlarge my ſelf upon what concerns the Perſon and Life of this famous Man, but by both the one and the other he had procur'd ſo large a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in the World, that I ſhould inform thoſe who are living of little of him, but for the ſake of Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I will add—That <hi>John-Oger de Gombaud</hi> was a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of <hi>Xaintonge,</hi> and younger Brother by a fourth Marriage; which he would frequently ſay in Raillery, as an excuſe that he was not Rich. He was tall, well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made, of a good Meen, and look'd like a Man of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. His Piety was undiſſembled, his Honeſty thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experienc'd, his Manners grave, and well-regulated. He had a Heart as Noble as his Aſpect promis'd it, a Mind upright, and naturally vertuous, of an exalted Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, leſs fertile than judicious, of a violent hot Humour, preſently provok'd to Anger, and yet had a ſerious and compos'd Look. After having finiſh'd all his Studies under the moſt celebrated Maſters of his time at <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux,</hi> he came to <hi>Paris,</hi> at the latter end of the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, where he ſuddenly made himſelf known, and valued too.</p>
            <p>This mighty Monarch being unhappily Aſſaſſmated, was bewailed by all the <hi>French,</hi> as the Father of his Country; and the Poets did adorn his Tomb with mournful Flowers they had gather'd from <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Gombaud,</hi> tho' young, was not the laſt, or leaſt Conſiderable amongſt 'em. In the Minority of <hi>Louis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49837:6"/>
the Juſt, and in the Regency of the Queen, <hi>Mary de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias,</hi> his Mother, he was one that was highly eſteem'd by this Great Princeſs, there being no one of his Quality who had ſo free an acceſs to her, or was received with greater kindneſs. She being of a generous and free tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and which ſhe loved to ſhow to deſerving Men, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd conſiderable Penſions to ſeveral Perſons of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Ingenuity: That of Monſieur <hi>de Gombaud</hi> was Twelve hundred Crowns; which made him always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in very good Equipage at Court, whether at <hi>Paris,</hi> or in Progreſſes, which were in thoſe times frequent. And being one who hated all ſuperfluous Expences, tho' no one more gentile in making ſuch which were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, had rais'd a pretty good Stock from what he ſpar'd out of his large Allowance, which was very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to him when that came to be leſſen'd; when both Civil and Forreign Wars had almoſt dryed up that Fountain from whence he had had ſuch Plenty.</p>
            <p>He was at firſt reduc'd from Twelve hundred Crowns to Eight, and then from Eight hundred to Four, which were continued to him to his Death; yet without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paid, ſince the War of <hi>Paris,</hi> but from the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of ſome Great and Generous Perſons, by whom he had the honour to be known and favour'd, amongſt which the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Montauſier</hi> were the principal. For ſome years alſo he had a Penſion under the Great Seal from Monſieur <hi>de Seguier,</hi> Chancellor of <hi>France.</hi> He was always very healthful, to which his Frugality and Regular manner of Life did much contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. But walking one day in his Chamber, which was uſual with him, and his foot ſlipping, he fell down and hurt ſo very much one of his Hips, that he was after this unhappy Accident, to the end of his Life, almoſt always confin'd to his Bed. He liv'd even an whole Age, if the time of his Birth, writ with his own Hand in one of his Books, were true, as he had aſſur'd a Friend of his it was, who never ſpake of it 'till after Monſieur <hi>de Gombaud</hi>'s Death. He had been honour'd with the Friendſhip of the moſt conſiderable Perſons of both Sexes of three
<pb facs="tcp:49837:6"/>
Courts, which he had ſeen; <hi>viz.</hi> That of <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, of <hi>Louis</hi> the Thirteenth, and <hi>Louis</hi> the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth. And in the Regency of two great Queens, <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> and <hi>Anne of Auſtria,</hi> no One was more conſtantly at Court, but eſpecially in the time of the former. But he did yet with greater diligence and pleaſure frequent that infinitely agreeable Company of Quality and Worth, who met at the Houſe of <hi>Rambouillet,</hi> which was a leſſer Court made up of choice Perſons, fewer in number, but, if I durſt ſay it, more refin'd than that of the <hi>Louvre,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not One was admitted to approach this Temple of Honour, where Vertue was rever'd under the Name of the Incomparable <hi>Artenice,</hi> who was not worthy of her Approbation and Eſteem.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Monſieur <hi>de Gombaud</hi> was both loved and admir'd by all thoſe, who, as he, had offer'd Sacrifices to the Muſes, and the Graces; and I doubt not but ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ages will be juſter to him than that in which he lived; and that his Excellent Works will procure him an Immortal Name, which is the Reward of all Learned Men, when they can reach that height to which this Gentleman had arrived.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:49837:7"/>
            <head>The Principal Matters contain'd in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. COnſiderations upon the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</item>
               <item>2. A Treatiſe concerning the Euchariſt.</item>
               <item>3. A Diſcourſe, in which the Author gives his Reaſons why he prefers the Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion before the <hi>Roman Catholick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. A Letter to a Lord at Court, who endeavour'd to perſwade him to turn <hi>Catholick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. A Letter to an Officer of the Crown, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten diſcours'd to him of Religion.</item>
               <item>6. A Letter to Monſieur de la <hi>Militiere,</hi> who deſir'd his Opinion in writing, on the Books if Controverſie he had made.</item>
               <item>7 A Letter to a Lady, who preſs'd him to go hear the Sermons of ſome of the Famous Preachers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49837:7"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS UPON THE <hi>CHRISTIAN RELIGION.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>WHEN I firſt began to have the Uſe of my Senſes and my Reaſon, I could not but frequently medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the Beauty of this <hi>Great World,</hi> the admirable Diſpoſition of it's parts, thoſe mutual Offices they each render to other, as well as thoſe juſt Laws by which they are eternally conſerv'd. On theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Effects, I often employ'd my Conſideration; and yet the conſtant Cuſtom of doing ſo, did not at all leſſen my Wonder of 'em: I could not then but acknowledge, that the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> was as a viſible Word, that beſpake, and manifeſtly prov'd a <hi>God;</hi> and in compariſon of which, our Eloquence was ſilent, at leaſt, ſo imperfect and contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it ſelf, that what it endeavour'd to bring to Light, it made more obſcure. I obſerv'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49837:8"/>
that every thing tended to it's natural End, punctually did it's Duty, unleſs <hi>Man;</hi> for he, from the very beginning, took part with the <hi>Devils</hi> themſelves, the Enemies of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and thus ingratefully ſinn'd againſt him from whom he had received ſuch infinite Favours, who had made him in as great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as could be, though not a God, yet after his own Image. But, as the firſt Product of his Mind was Vanity and Pride, ſo that of his Body was <hi>Cain,</hi> the Murderer of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and as all his Children inherit his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and Raſhneſs, ſo conſequently, his Puniſhment and Condemnation. In the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Obſervation I have made of'em, I have found ſome of the Nature of Devils, others of Beaſts, many of both together, being guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Rapine and Extortion, their Hands ſtain'd with Blood; and in a Word, the whole Courſe of their Lives paſs'd either in private Conſpiracies, or open Rebellion and Thefts.</p>
               <p>'Twas then a ſecret Horror ſeiz'd me, and a Sadneſs, even as the Shadow of Death, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd the ſereneſt days of my Life. 'Twas little Satisfaction to me, that God had made me <hi>Man,</hi> or that I was of the number of thoſe who bore the Name of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſince I ſaw what Diſorders happen'd amongſt 'em, and that Malice and Ignorance were as predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant here, as with <hi>Barbarians</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> Nothing was ſo averſe to me, as thoſe whom
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49837:8"/>
I look'd on as my Fellow-members; and yet I found 'twas neceſſary, either to comply with 'em, and ſo make my ſelf an accomplice with 'em in their Exorbitances, or elſe, to render my ſelf perpetually deteſtable to 'em: yet, I conſider'd, that like Accidents did equally ſurprize both Old and Young, and I could not perſwade my ſelf, that any reaſonable Souls could find any real Satisfaction or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment under ſuch great Uncertainties that muſt needs follow.</p>
               <p>My Reaſon it ſelf, and all its thoughtful Reſults, did but yet ſerve to torment me more, till I had carefully conſulted the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles, the beſt of Books, and was aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, that God in his Providence did reſerve and mark out to himſelf ſome, for whom, even the Angels have reſpect; and who ſhall not be deſtroyed in the day of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. That this World is but a place of tryal to diſtinguiſh the Good from the Bad, a way that leads from Darkneſs to Light, from Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery to eternal Happineſs. Theſe words I had heard with more Fear and Wavering than Aſſurance, (perceiving how very few either could or would underſtand 'em) had I not from themſelves learn't, that even Shepherds and Fiſhermen have more Knowledge in 'em than the greateſt Caſuits, or learned'ſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers; and, that juſtly to comprehend their Meaning, we ſtand not in ſo much need of Logick or Rhetorick, as true Faith and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49837:9"/>
That they teach a Knowledge, which puffeth not up, but does humble and abaſe men; and yet not ſo far, but (though mean and low in the World) have Courage enough to declare the Truth before the proudeſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and daily to run the hazard of their Lives, that by their Endeavours they may ſave others from Death.</p>
               <p>Theſe divine Revelations, attended with a Spirit of Comfort, calmed my diſturbed mind: I found my ſelf ſo ſuddenly transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from what I was, that that Sadneſs which had poſſeſſed me, though not quite gone, yet had changed its Nature; for, now 'twas occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned only by my Sins and Infirmities. If I have any remaining Fears, they do but ſtrengthen me, and provoke me to ſtrive with more Violence and Ardency to attain that end which Hope and Faith propoſe.</p>
               <p>I was fill'd with a juſt ſenſe of Joy, ariſing, not from a tranſitory unſatisfying Pleaſure, but from a permanent ſatisfying Good; which, though communicative, encreaſes; and of which, though one may liberally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, will not at all be diminiſh'd. 'Tis this which invites me to freely offer what I have received; to joyn my Voice with thoſe of the faithful, (whom God in his Providence has mixed with others) that the Truth may be loudly declared, ſo that thoſe will be inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable who have heard it, and would not believe, or thoſe who betraying themſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49837:9"/>
to their private worldly Intereſt, feared to liſten to it, leſt they ſhould be obliged to follow it's Dictates.</p>
               <p>The Time may come, when they will, perhaps, accuſe us of having been too remiſs of not having ſufficiently informed 'em, and then will they be ready to impute their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Ignorance and Obſtinacy to our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect or Weakneſs. And yet, when we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to inſtruct 'em, ſome pity us, others laugh at, or deſpiſe us; and indeed, the moſt favourable Opinion they can have of us, is, that we are poor, ſimple, extravagant Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Others are in Paſſion, and angry with us, ready to tear us in pieces, affront and injure us, look on us as Hereticks and Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, though our Crime is of that Nature, that we deſire nothing more than to expoſe it even to the Cenſure of our very Judges.</p>
               <p>But, to whom ſhall we diſcourſe, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be underſtood by Idolaters? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets have pronounc'd ſuch a Curſe againſt 'em, that makes 'em void of Knowledge; makes 'em like even what they worſhip and adore. We cannot be underſtood by men of weak, or no Judgments; they comprehend nothing, and do but rather raiſe Doubts in themſelves, than find Satisfaction. If they are of wicked debauch'd Lives, they are diſturb'd to hear the Voice that condemns 'em. But, they are the moſt dangerous who have the moſt Learning; theſe uſe Tricks and Evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49837:10"/>
and wreſt the cleareſt Senſe and Words to their own meaning; the eaſieſt, and moſt natural Propoſitions, when they pleaſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come difficult and ambiguous; they equally prove, and deny every thing; and at length, as a juſt Puniſhment upon 'em, they ſo far neglect the Knowledge of the Truth, as to be unhappy enough not to know themſelves; they have employ'd their Time and Studies ſo much in ſuperfluous things, that they have utterly loſt all manner of Care of ſuch that are neceſſary; they have made their humane Learning ſo much a Judge of the Divine, that it has render'd 'em infinitely worſe than if they had been altogether ignorant. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, ſince 'tis hard to perſwade any one to what is diſagreeable to him, I cannot but fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy I hear the Wiſe men of the Age and our Courtiers, ſaying, <hi>Prethee talk to us of what is pleaſing and grateful to us, and don't you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be wiſer than the Church.</hi> They ought not, they believe, be better than their Fathers were, or follow other Cuſtoms than thoſe of their own Country or Towns: The Eſtates they have will not allow 'em to make any Profeſſion which may be in the leaſt in juri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to 'em, and at whatever Rate it is, God and Religion muſt ſuit with their Intereſt and Convenience. How! to live contrary to the Opinion of the World, to have different Sentiments from the great Doctors of the Chair, to go againſt the belief of the People,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49837:10"/>
the Magiſtrate and Prince; Is not this to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one's ſelf to be thwarted by every one? To talk thus of Reformation, is to be look'd on as a Diſturber of the Peace, or a Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and Liberty is grown to that paſs, that 'tis incurable. Religion is almoſt turn'd into Superſtition; and on all ſides, the Corruption of the Age is ſo great, that there is not only need of a Deluge to cleanſe the Earth, but a Univerſal Fire to conſume it.</p>
               <p>To what end then is all this Diſcourſe? What Light or new Invention ſhall we add to thoſe ſo many excellent ancient Leſſons we have already receiv'd, which, becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways neceſſary, are always new? If we have not ſuch Articles of Faith, ſuch Catechiſms as are ſufficient for our Inſtructions, to make us the beſt Chriſtians, yet there is nothing wanting in the Old and New Teſtament, to inform us of our Duties. Nevertheleſs, ſince he who ſupplies us with Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and has planted his Word in our Hearts, would have us publiſh it with our Mouths, that being converted, we may la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to convert our Brethren; We ought not to be ſilent where there is ſo great a Neceſſity of ſpeaking, of writing at leaſt, what the World may not be diſpleaſed to read.</p>
               <p>But, let us take Care, that we do not imitate thoſe ambitious Writers, who only aim at procuring Glory, and Reputation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49837:11"/>
by their voluminous Works, with which they burthen the Minds of men, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that a Multitude of Words does argue nothing more than their difficulty of Conception, or expreſſing themſelves.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore by ſpeaking, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (notwithſtanding all manner of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition) to ſave ſome by Fear, pulling them out of the Fire, and try if it will not pleaſe God to open the Heart, amongſt Men, of a <hi>Naaman,</hi> and amongſt Women, of a <hi>Lydie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>'TIS obſervable, that the moſt celebrated Holy men, the firſt Writers of Sacred Hiſtory, who have inſtructed us in the Laws of living well, and taught us the Methods of Salvation, have not given themſelves the trouble to find out Arguments to prove, or expreſly to demonſtrate the Being of a Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, believing that 'twas impoſſible for men to be reaſonable, and doubt of ſo manifeſt a Truth. We cannot but confeſs indeed, that every thing, in its proper Language, does aſſert this ſo clearly, that the whole World ſeems to be but one large Object, by which God is pleas'd to make himſelf ſeen, being in his Nature <hi>Inviſible.</hi> Beſides thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49837:11"/>
which are naturally implanted in us, whereby we diſcern betwixt Good and Evil; thoſe Terrours of Conſcience, thoſe Rational Diſcourſes which exalt us even above our ſelves, that tendency to a ſovereign Good, the deſire of Perfection and Immortality, do yet imprint a fuller ſence of him in our Minds, than we can have of him by our Eyes. If therefore we argue from within our ſelves, or from without, we find him every where, and this Notion is ſo univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that it can proceed from nothing but Nature it ſelf, ſo that thoſe who disbelieve this, ſeem to have deveſted themſelves of it. To deny a <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Providence,</hi> the Wiſe and Judicious ſay, <hi>is to be deaf to ones own Voice, and a Stranger to ones ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet there are thoſe who enjoy the ſoft and pleaſurable Benefits of Life, and good Senſe, and yet acknowledge not its Author, or at leaſt, do but ſpeciouſly pretend it, that they may avoid the being thought Atheiſts: Theſe men accommodate themſelves to all ſorts of Religions, having none at all, or do embrace or quit 'em, as they may be uſeful or diſadvantageous to their Pleaſures and Intereſt. They will oblige themſelves to no Laws, but ſuch which gratifie 'em; the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to them are the cruelleſt; and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name of Divinity does either offend 'em, or makes no impreſſion at all on 'em. They deſtroy, as much as 'tis poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49837:12"/>
the Author of their Being, and pleaſe themſelves in disbelieving, what if they believed, they would be bound to reverence and fear. Their licentious Humours give 'em not leave to inform themſelves of what they ought; and doubtleſs they either read not at all, or if they do, don't meditate on it; but if they do, they are ſo naturally inciin'd to Evil, that they turn all to an ill ſence. However, theſe would be thought the ſubtle, ingenious men of the Age, imagining they know much more than others, having learn'd from ſome lewd cunning Fellow two or three falſe Arguments to prove their horrid Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which paſs with ſuch as themſelves, the Profane, or with the Ignorant; beyond theſe they proceed not, or if they do, 'tis like unlearn'd men, ſtill putting Queſtions, and never making Anſwer to any. 'Tis with ſorrow I ſpeak it, that moſt Princes and Noble-men are ſo far from ridding their Courts of theſe Monſters, that they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd as better Company than others; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd as particular Friends and Confidents; ſo that thus inſenſibly they themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty with them of offending the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty. Without theſe, their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation at Table, and in Company, will be thought dull and inſipid. Here are they loaded with Honour, and filled with the choiceſt Delicacies, and then, when they ought to make the higheſt acknowledgments,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49837:12"/>
they pronounce the greateſt Blaſphemies. What they ſay is receiv'd with Applauſe, and the more are they valued, the more impudently they attack God Almighty. Men, the moſt ingrateful, and leaſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of all ſorts, making acknowledgments only to themſelves, believing all they have to proceed from their own Induſtry or good Fortune. True Children of the Devil, who is the falſe Accuſer, ſtriving to ſignalize themſelves by the ſame Methods their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do's, by oppoſing, or openly fighting againſt the Truth.</p>
               <p>Since theſe acknowledge no greater Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom than their own, they may believe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, 'tis by their Virtue, by their Care, the Earth is ſupported by its own weight, that it is incompaſſed by the vaſt Waters of the Sea, without being overflown; That by their Providence and Induſtry ſo many dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Streams paſs through its Veins, ſome riſing into Fountains, refreſhing all ſorts of Creatures, and then making uſeful Rivers, fill'd with Fiſh, and ſerviceable to entertain a Commerce between men; And doubtleſs, by their Order, the Sun riſes at an appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time, to light them, when ſatisfy'd with ſleep, and each Seaſon returns to gratifie them with all manner of Delight. If they can't in all theſe but confeſs their inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, why will they not alſo own that there are Powers greater than theirs employ'd in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49837:13"/>
theſe wonderful Services, and by degrees they'l find one Superiour to others, which are finite, and to have a beginning, and therefore neceſſarily depend on one that has none, which is infinite? Otherwiſe we ſhould paſs from the leſs to the greater without end, from cauſe to cauſe, without finding the firſt or laſt, which alone merits the name of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. To what are we come, that we muſt even now with Induſtry endeavour to prove the Truth of the being of a God! Is not this indeed to affront men as reaſonable as our ſelves, to ſhew 'em what each particular Sence does conſtantly prove to 'em? Is not this to teach thoſe to ſee who have their Eyes open, and tell others they have the uſe of Reaſon, who profeſs themſelves men? Shall we add to theſe Conſiderations, the frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repealed Arguments of thoſe who have undertaken ſo high, but juſt and reaſonable a Defence? In effect, if there was no God, How could the World be? Could it be the Workmanſhip and the Workman of it ſelf? Could it be before it was? How can theſe agree, and yet but the ſame World? If it be eternal, and is independent on any firſt Cauſe, that Order which we obſerve, and muſt be an effect of admirable Wiſdom, with all thoſe Powers which are differently communicated to each part, would, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, prove what ſome have fancied, That it is <hi>God himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49837:13"/>
For, it is not in the leaſt probable, that it's Beauty, it's Order, and Duration, can be the effects of blind and confus'd Chance; Can we imagine, that from thence could proceed ſuch long and regular Succeſſions of Time and Motion? Can we attribute to that, ſo much Care, and Wiſdom, as to be able to make ſo different Cauſes tend to the ſame Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? This certainly, under another Name would be God himſelf, and his Blaſphemers would meet in every place, what their guilty Souls are afraid of finding any where: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, What is this Fortune, but a vain and inſignificant Title, an imaginary Idol, that exiſts but in our Fancies, to which we erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly attribute ſuch Effects, of whoſe Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes we are ignorant.</p>
               <p>She appears to us leſs or greater, according to our Proportion of Knowledge; and, if we could but free the World from Ignorance, the Notion of Fortune would be laid aſide. 'Tis then the Deity of the ignorant, which no wiſe man adores; and I cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how thoſe who plead for her can believe, themſelves reaſonable, ſince, according to the Opinion they have of all things, they muſt confeſs they were made by Chance, and conſequently, that they move, act, and ſpeak ſo. There are amongſt theſe, ſome who pretend to believe a God, but, at the ſame time, make him careleſs and idle, ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and wholly unconcern'd in the Affairs of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49837:14"/>
the Univerſe, at leaſt, in all ſublunary things, imagining perhaps, ſays one, that this would be too great Trouble to him; <hi>As if their Impieties could give him any Comfort or Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</hi> Is not this to deny, whilſt they own him, and boldly to confine the Actions of an infinite Power? Is not this to make to themſelves a God, who cannot barely act as a Man, to allow him Underſtanding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Counſel, a Will without Freedom, Goodneſs without Communication; in a Word, a Being without a Being, and leſs than that of the <hi>Elements,</hi> which comes neareſt to no Being at all.</p>
               <p>But, not to inſiſt farther on the univerſal chain of Cauſes with their Effects, which plainly demonſtrate, that things of the ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt nature, are aſſiſted by thoſe of the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and that theſe neceſſarily depend on the ſame Wiſdom and Power by which they are made and conſerv'd. Who is he that in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger chaſtiſes both Kings and People; that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves the Scepter from one, and gives it to another; that overturns Empires, and in an inſtant, changes the Face of Eſtates; and to ſhew that this is done by his Power, has long ſince foretold it by the Mouth of his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Prophets? Who was it that puniſh'd the Sins of men by a miraculous Flood, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all the World; and by whoſe Advice was one only Family ſaved from it? Who was it that promis'd ſuch a Deluge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49837:14"/>
ſhould never return, and who has ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully kept his Promiſe? What Spirit fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw the coming of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> three or four thouſand years, of whom the Prophets have ſo particularly ſpoke, as if they, as well as the Apoſtles, had ſeen him: From whom, but God himſelf, or ſome Angel ſent from him, were thoſe Predictions of the Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> and of that Lamp which ſhould be kept in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, of the diſperſing and rejecting of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Converſion of the <hi>Gentiles?</hi> If it be told me that there are Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Aſtrologers, and Wiſe men, who fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell things to come, I muſt ask by what hand they are writ in the Heavens, in ſuch Characters that men can read 'em, and who has plac'd the Signs in the Stars, or rather, their Vertues and Cauſes, which the ſame men cannot comprehend? It muſt needs be, that thoſe who are not touch'd with theſe Conſiderations, are blinded with Paſſion that prevents their Reaſon, who, from Cuſtom become obſtinate, and from Ignorance, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid. We find that there are many very wiſe, and knowing in all worldly things; nay, are ignorant and inſenſible of nothing but Divine ones: But, if I am not deceived; moſt bear in their Breaſt both their Accuſer and Judge, and will, earlier or later, be forc'd to ſay as others have done, <hi>We are ſo weary of the ways of Iniquity, that we can endure 'em no longer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49837:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THUS whatever preſents it ſelf to our ſight do's ſpeak of a God, and prove that he is; but what he is, neither all thoſe Objects, nor all our Reaſon can diſcover to us. Yet ſo much as we know of him, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make us believe, and worſhip what we don't perfectly know. Let it be then that the continu'd courſe of Cauſes and Effects is not infinite, that all things either reach or tend viſibly to their End; that from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienteſt of Books, in reſpect of which all others are but new, and imperfect, we know the Origine and Riſe of all Nations; That the Powers of the Heavens are become weak, that the Age and Strength of Men are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, in compariſon of that account we receive of 'em in Sacred and Profane Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it does evidently appear that God created the World; and for an additional Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his greateſt Work, made Man after his own Image, that is, wholly conformable to his Will, not in Eſſence but Imitation, and as Perfect and as Happy as the Nobleſt Creature could be. He was plac'd in an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Station, between Beaſts and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, was the Bond of the Univerſe, the End of all created things, over which he had eternally commanded, had he been only but obedient to his Creator. But not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49837:15"/>
with thoſe abundant Favours he had received, raſhly aſpires to a degree above his Sovereign, endeavours to riſe higher than the Top it ſelf, and aiming at ſomething in nothing, was near returning to that firſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from whence he came. How ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bold! What high Preſumption is it to covet being equal with God! What baſe Incredulity to accuſe him of falſhood or Envy! What horrid Ingratitude and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, to ſet the Devil in Gods place! How extremely ſpiteful and uncharitable was he to his Children, to ſell 'em before they were born, and enſlave 'em before they knew what Liberty was! He ſcarce imagin'd that he ſhould be believ'd the worſt Father of the World, that the Curſe he had drawn on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would extend it ſelf from one end of the Earth to the other, from the beginning to the end of all Ages, and would be the moſt certain Inheritance he could leave to his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. He foreſaw not, that inſtead of that commerce and fellowſhip he held with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, inſtead of that Acceſs he had to, and Communication with God himſelf, his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Succeſſors would converſe only with Devils, and muſt eternally ſubmit to their Power and Tyranny; and that to live amongſt men, would be to herd with Lyons, Tygers, Vipers, and Dragons. He foreſaw not, that inſtead of an Eternal Spring which he began to enjoy, and might have preſerv'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49837:16"/>
for 'em, they would ſuffer the Extremities of cold Winter, or be ſtifled by the exceſſive Heats of Summer, that inſtead of thoſe fair delightful Trees he ſaw in the Terreſtrial Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, and of that delicious Fruit, and thoſe curious Flowers he had the liberty to gather there, they would ſeldom ſee but Racks and Gibbets, the devouring Grave, and dead mens Bones. He foreſaw not, that beſides the Hardſhips and Swet of Labour, the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of fatal Neceſſity, ſharp Pains, or lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Diſeaſes, and the continual Horrors of approaching Death; there would be Judgments and Plagues that would ruine whole Towns, and deſtroy Provinces, that there would be ſometimes ſo great a Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and the dead ſo frightful, that there would be ſcarce any left, either to lament or bury 'em; that Nature would become ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of her ſelf, that Men would devour Men, and Children tore in Bits would again return to their Mothers Bellies. He foreſaw not that the greateſt part of his Poſterity would become ſo odious to each other, that they would pleaſe themſelves with perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the juſteſt and moſt innocent of their Brethren, rather than imitate them; that they would not content themſelves to ſtone ſome, and maſſacre others, but would wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily invent ſome new Puniſhment, by which they might force them to deny the Truth, to worſhip Wood or Stone, or elſe to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49837:16"/>
the cruelleſt Torments the Furies of Hell it ſelf could inſpire 'em with. No, he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw not all theſe things; and the Devil, who flatter'd him with Hopes that his Eyes ſhould be more open'd, endeavour'd to blind him more, that he might throw him into a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Abyſſe, from whence, 'twas not to be imagined, that ever either any Humane, Angelick, or Divine Power, could juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve him.</p>
               <p>How is he diſguiſed by this Fall! what Proportion is there between what he is and what he was! He is aſham'd of himſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only ſo much Sight left him as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his Nakedneſs, and ſo much Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as to perceive his Error. From the Image of God, after which he was made, he is transform'd in an Inſtant into that of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and he has no more of the firſt Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence remaining, than the Trouble of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt it. What comfort can he find af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Loſs? He cannot hope for any from his Reaſon, that having help'd to deſtroy him. He who could not preſerve himſelf upright when ſtanding, how, when fallen, ſhall he recover himſelf? What can he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe himſelf, either from Angels or God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſince he has broken that Law by which he was obliged to Obedience or Puniſhment? The Puniſhment which bears the ſame Date with Guilt, does, without Intermiſſion tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him, and has left him only ſo much
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49837:17"/>
Life as to make him ſenſible of the Terrors of Death. But, what is yet worſe, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is aggravated according to the Greatneſs of the offended Perſon; and as he has ſinn'd againſt an infinite Being, ſo he muſt dye, or ſuffer infinitely! What Confuſion of Thoughts, What Remorſe, What Terrors torment his Mind! Since he was not only told his Duty, but threatned with Diſgrace if he did it not, and to invite him to be the more careful, one would have believed the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of his Death ſhould have kept him from ſinning. To what deſpair does he find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reduc'd, and what can he do or imagine in this ſad miſerable Condition! Unleſs God has made what he cannot repent him of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made; and that he builds not to pull down, and his Glory will not ſuffer his Workmanſhip to periſh. That 'tis not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable the moſt excellent of Creatures was deſtin'd to everlaſting Miſery, that being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, and the Fault not altogether his own, he ſhould be obliged to make Satisfaction, as the Devils themſelves, who are always doing it, but never accompliſh it.</p>
               <p>Howſoever it is, he ſaw no Expedient for his Deliverance, and could not imagine how he might find Mercy from God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violating his Juſtice. 'Twas this that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he nor all his Poſterity could conceive.</p>
               <p>Some have been ſo amaz'd at it, that they have turn'd Atheiſts, others made to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49837:17"/>
Gods after their own faſhion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Idolaters. This unhappy temper, but ſo natural and ſo ſtrong, has even univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally prevail'd, and ſo corrupted the very Senſe and Underſtanding of Men, that they would have the Objects of Adoration Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and viſible, as themſelves, not being able to frame to themſelves any thing high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, attributing to them humane Paſſions, and appointed 'em Services according to their own vain Imaginations. They have not only been leſs than men by worſhipping them, but than Beaſts themſelves, having worſhipped thoſe too. They adored the moſt abject and vileſt Creatures, who were ſo far from bearing any marks of Divinity, that they had not common ſignes of Life; and, leſt their Idolatry ſhould not be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently execrable, they worſhipped even the Infernal Powers, the greateſt Enemies of the Creator. Many, believing that there was a future, and better ſtate of Life for Man than that of this World, inſtead of ſearching the Divine Oracles, to inſtruct 'em in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of their great End, have apply'd themſelves to doubtful and Diabolical ones. Inſtead of the only and true Remedy by which they might be cleanſed from all Sin and Corruption, they have taken indirect Meaſures, and from hence wearied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Ceremonies, Abſtinencies, Purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Faſtings, Offerings, which have been
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49837:18"/>
only effectual to add freſh Troubles to their Life. For what Sacrifices, what Beaſts, what Hecatombs can expiate the Crime only of one Man? Or rather, what Man is able, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conceiv'd in Sin, to make ſatisfaction, not for others; but for himſelf? And what Sacrifices can he offer but Ingratitude, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Hatred, Malice, Vain thoughts, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Words? What is his Virtue but Vice palliated, his Prudence but Subtilty and Fraud, his Valour but raſhneſs, and his Wiſdom but Hypocriſie? If he does pray, 'tis only from Cuſtom or for Faſhion-ſake, and if at ſometimes he is more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Zealous, 'tis not ſo much the love of God that excites him to it, as the fear of Evil threatning him, or the ſence of it, which is burthenſome to him. What therefore can he do better than daily to make Confeſſion of his Sins? but from thence he is to expect, if to be judged according to his Merits, only Death and Damnation.</p>
               <p>If then Man by all his Reaſon could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſanctifie one Man only, if all the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy in the World could never make one Believer, or diſcover a Good which Death cannot rob us of; what remains then but that we believe that, thoſe who have been inſpired by God, have taught, is beſt; that we rely on the firſt and ſureſt Principles, that the Means are univerſal, which God only can reveal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49837:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <p>AS 'tis an undoubted Truth, that Man was not made by Chance, ſo 'tis as certain that he was not made in Vain; that he was not deſtin'd to everlaſting Torments, or to return to that Nothing from whence he came; and the ſame Power that gave him his firſt Being, will give him a future Well-Being. Shall not He, who by thoſe Sparks of the Divine Image remaining in him, can meaſure the Heavens ſtanding upon the Earth, be immortal? What would ſignifie elſe thoſe many Promiſes and Revelations? Who would have taken ſo much trouble to have deceived us? What would Juſtice and Piety be accounted, but vain empty Names with which the World is abuſed? and to what purpoſe all our Religion, if after this Life there was nothing to be hoped for? 'Tis true that our degenerate and ſenſual Inclinations perſwade us to follow the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way; to enjoy the Pleaſures of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, without any concern for thoſe of hereafter, to live as Beaſts, as if to dye as thoſe: But let us lay aſide all thoſe profane and inconſiderate Thoughts. The firſt Act of the Creator is a Proof of all the reſt; for He who made us out of nothing, can as well raiſe us from the dead. Will he ſuffer ſuch to eſcape unpuniſh'd who ſully and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49837:19"/>
his Holy Image? Shall the Devil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer in this Combat, or triumph over the Works of the Almighty? No, the Happineſs of man in his firſt State of Innocence, how great ſoever, was not his ultimate End; nor was it ſo compleat, but that he will be yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more happy: but 'twas neceſſary to leave him to his own Will and Counſels, as well to try him, as to oblige him to a Knowledge of himſelf, which might ſerve as a ſtep to raiſe him to that of his Creator: He would elſe, perhaps, have believed he could have ſubſiſted without the aid of any other Power, and would not have duely conſider'd, that there is but one only Being, pure, holy, and true, on whom all others depend, and without whom, we muſt either be not at all, or eternally miſerable.</p>
               <p>That men therefore may not too ſecurely reſt on the Remains of their own Strength and Vertue, God has given 'em means to try themſelves, and let 'em know, that they all equally fell with the firſt man, are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Slaves to Sin, and conſequently, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butaries to <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He has given 'em his Law, which, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as it is, ſhews 'em but their Imperfection. It's being juſt, makes 'em the more criminal, it inſtructs but to confound 'em; and ſeems ſo far from promiſing any good to 'em, that it takes away all manner of Hopes: 'tis a kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letter, an intolerable Yoke, an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49837:19"/>
of Death, ſo far from juſtifying, that it brings all under the ſame Condemnation: Yet, to ſpeak more favourably of it, 'tis a Looking-glaſs that repreſents to 'em what they were, what they are, and what they muſt be; 'tis a Flower, whoſe Fruit is the greateſt Grace can happen to 'em; 'tis a Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beau that Lights 'em in the Night, till the riſing of the Sun.</p>
               <p>As the incomprehenſible Unity which comprehends all things, is the ſovereign Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of God, ſo Union with God is the chief Perfection of Man; but we cannot come to him, unleſs firſt he draws us, or rather, unleſs he is pleas'd to come down to us. This is the great Myſtery of our Redemption, which even thoſe who receiv'd the Promiſes of it confirmed by Numbers of Signs and Miracles, ſaw at ſo great a diſtance, and through ſuch ſhadows of Darkneſs, that they could much better believe and hope for than comprehend it. Obſerving the great diſtance between Heaven and Earth, they foreſaw no way to fill up this Abyſſe, nor could they imagine how they ſhould aſcend thus high, but by <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder.</p>
               <p>Yet Reaſon does often aſſent to things even beyond it ſelf; and by this at length we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what at firſt we could not poſſibly imagine. If then Reaſon tells us, that a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium is kept between two Extreams, and yet with this Medium theſe Extreams equally
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49837:20"/>
agree, though never ſo diſtant; that 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that a Mediator be capable of the Sentiments and Affections of each Party whom he reconciles; that he makes a juſt Eſtimate of Right and Wrong between the one and the other; who can doubt but that he who is ſent us from Heaven, is endu'd with all Qualities neceſſary for him? that he partakes both of the divine and humane Nature; in a word, that he is both God and Man; and yet Man, conceiv'd after another manner than others, leſt his natural Corruption and Sins make him incompatible with the Juſtice and Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God. If he was not Man, we ſhould have no part in him, nor could his Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be imputed to us. If he was not God, he could not communicate to us his immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Vertues, his Glory and Happineſs. If he was only Man, he could not conquer Death, or have riſen from the Grave, he would have ſunk under the Pain, and have been reduc'd to nothing. And if he was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, he could not have dyed, or receiv'd from himſelf the Satisfaction which the Law he made obliges us to.</p>
               <p>He muſt then ſuffer, and yet be impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; dye, and yet immortal; deſcend into Hell and riſe again: He muſt conquer the Infernal Powers, and let us ſee, that in him truly are the Entries and Iſſues of Death. It is neceſſary, that he who will deliver others from the Curſe, does both ſuffer and over-come
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49837:20"/>
it; and that there may be ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion between the Fault and the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is neceſſary that a Perſon of infinite Worth does render a temporal and finite Suffering of infinite Value; for, doubtleſs, God rather choſe that his Son ſhould dye for the Sins of the World, than the whole World ſhould periſh. Though there be no Juſtice that allows, that one who is innocent ſuffer for the guilty, yet none forbids it, on Condition, that he voluntarily offers him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that he is not abſolutely deſtroy'd by the Puniſhment, but that it remains in his Power to lay down and take up his Life again.</p>
               <p>O wonderful Effects of Eternal Power and Wiſdom, who from one Man, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, made a Woman that caus'd us all to dye; and ſince has pleas'd, in the Fulneſs of Time, of a Woman to make a Man that will us reſtore to Life again! Thus is the Divine and Humane Nature myſteriouſly united, and without the Properties either of the one or the other, being changed.</p>
               <p>The Son of God is joyn'd in Unity of Perſon with the Son of Man; I ſay, the Son, and not the Father, becauſe we cannot have for Interceſſor that Perſon to whom he muſt intercede. He who ſends, cannot be ſent; and then as the Father does nothing of himſelf, but all things by the Son, 'tis reaſonable, that the ſecond Creation ſhould be made by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49837:21"/>
the ſame as the firſt was. Who can more effectually ſpeak than He who is the Word it ſelf? Who can better renew in us the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Image, than He who firſt form'd it? and who can better beſtow on us the right of Children, than the Poſſeſſour of it? But it is not enough that He makes Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or that that be imputed to us; but 'tis neceſſary that this Grace be conferr'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; that it be apply'd to us, which is the Office of the Spirit that equally proceeds both from the Father and the Son: 'Tis He that does both enlighten, and purifie us, that makes us underſtand, love, and believe theſe Myſteries; that makes us, as he did the Bleſſed Virgin, conceive our Saviour. He is the Bond of Love that unites us to Divinity; 'tis the true anointing by which we are made Kings, Prieſts, and Prophets: To conclude, This is He who gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as a Pledge, and aſſurance of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of a future Life, of the Reſurrection, and of Glory.</p>
               <p>This great Mediator is then come, and as he was foretold, not as a Conquerour, as a <hi>Cyrus</hi> or <hi>Alexander,</hi> but a man of ſorrows, conſecrated, by his Afflictions, the publick Victim of Mankind, whoſe Merit is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for all, but only applicable to thoſe who believe in him. He is come, not to ſhed the Blood of others, but his own; to overcome Rebellion by Obedience, Force and Power
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49837:21"/>
by Weakneſs, and Pride by Humility: and this makes him appear greater, and more Divine, as well as us to admire and adore him. Behold the ſole Object of Religion, which is not onely to ſave Man, but of him to make a God, without prejudice to the Divine Unity, or Holy Trinity. For what name can we give the Son of man, who makes one and the ſame Perſon with the Son of God? And of what Race ought we to eſteem thoſe, whom he has vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to honour with the name of Brethren? Now this Religion is eſtabliſh'd; not by Contention, or private Conſpiracy; not by the favour of Kings, or the ſuffrage of the People, not by the cunning of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, or the Eloquence of Orators; not by a multitude of men, as the <hi>Mahometan,</hi> or by numbers of Gods, as the Pagan; but by the alone publiſhing of the ſimple and naked Truth. Yet this Truth, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all manner of oppoſition, has flouriſh'd, and made it ſelf known through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World. It has ſo prevailed, that Errours of all ſorts have been confounded, all Sects diſpers'd and waſted, falſe Oracles, with Idols and their worſhippers, have fall'n before it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49837:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>AFter that which we are taught concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only way of Man's Salvation, What can we learn from all the Religions in the World? To what would <hi>Mahomet</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, if the Name of Chriſtian be ſo hateful to him, if he differs from the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Jeſus Chriſt, to which, all the Prophets do ſo ſtrongly adhere? Is it not ſtrange, that ſo many inſpired men ſhould be rais'd at different Times, and at diſtant Places, to foretell the coming of one Man alone, who was to be rejected by his own, and receiv'd by all the other Nations of the Earth? Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, after what we learn of him from the Scriptures, and thoſe Commands it lays upon us, as well as thoſe Inſtructions we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive from 'em, we have no need of being longer curious, but to ſubmit and obey. Let thoſe who make to themſelves Gods, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Services for 'em, 'tis otherwiſe with him, who is not made by our Opinion, but is the Maker of us all. His Will cannot be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd by our Conceit or vain Imaginations, but by his Word alone; this he gives us as a Light to guide us, and woe be to them who call this Light Darkneſs. The Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which it teaches us is ſo ſublime and excellent, that Man could never have found it out; and then ſo conſonant to Reaſon, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49837:22"/>
'tis impoſſible to conſider of it well, and not approve of it. It firſt repreſents Man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, informing him of his Weakneſs and Miſery, then comforts him; and no ſooner diſcovers his Diſeaſe to him, but offers him a Remedy againſt it. It contains many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations and Predictions, confirm'd, after a long Succeſſion of Time, by certain Events, whoſe end is the Salvation of the Creature, and the glorifying of the Creator. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalneſs, the End, the Stile, the Antiquity, the Strength, the Duration, and divers other Marks, which eminently appear in it, do ſo clearly prove it's Divinity, that it ſeems to be God himſelf who ſpeaks; Man therefore muſt attend and be ſilent. Has the Truth of any Hiſtory of the greateſt and moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Empires, been ſo much ſtrengthned by its Friends, as this has even by its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? What other begins with the World, continues from Age to Age, ſpeaks of things to come, as if preſent, and ends with the World it ſelf? 'Tis the way of Salvation, the Gate of Heaven; and he who endeavours to enter by any other, is a Thief. 'Tis the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of Perfection, that ſhews us of what Good or of what Ill we are capable, and teaches us to examine, to know, and reform our ſelves. 'Tis the true Paradiſe, where grows the Tree of Life, whoſe Leaves are for the Health of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49837:23"/>
To conclude, they are the Words of the Almighty, writ by him, and equally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens'd to his Servants and Friends, being nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kept or hid from any one of thoſe who belong to his Election. Whoever then knows that there are Holy Scriptures for to inſtruct men how they ought to ſerve God, and what Recompence they may hope for, and does not carefully conſult 'em, whatever Profeſſion he may make of Religion, is a Lyar, a Hypocrite, and deceives himſelf; ſince they are writ as well for the meaner ſort as the greateſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; for Women as Men; and for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as their Fathers. If there be any, who having once read 'em, though out of Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity perhaps, and are not ſo taken with 'em as to read 'em continually, 'tis a very ill Sign. Is it to deal fairly, or indeed, Is it not to declare they receive the Devils Wages, and take his part to prevent the Salvation of men when they forbid the reading of 'em to ſo many pious Souls who thirſt after the Word of Eternal Life? Let <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the Falſeneſs of their Doctrines and Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but let the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, being Truth it ſelf, be expos'd and viſible to all; let it ſhine as the Day, that ſpiritual things may be as evident to our Underſtanding, as corporeal are.</p>
               <p>But, perhaps 'twill be ſaid, What need have we of ſo much Reading and Study, ſince the Church does appoint what is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49837:23"/>
for us, and that ſuch who cannot err do guide us? But, I ſay, there can be no greater Error than to perſwade us that we cannot err; for this indeed, is boldly to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to our ſelves, a divine Property, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable to Men, unleſs to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles; and they only by the Commiſſion they had to declare the Word they receiv'd, and publiſh what was truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd to 'em. Perhaps, the Word of God is not to be underſtood without <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle:</hi> But I ſay, the Wiſe Men of the World are ſo far from this Knowledge, as their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is folly before God, which makes 'em as obſtinately and with as much Violence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Motions of the Holy Ghoſt, as one Contrary does the other. It may be urg'd again, that 'tis but a fragment, a part, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Rule, inſufficient to lead us to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I ſay, That there is no Man either ſo ſimple, or dull, who from hence is not enabled to learn more than the beſt Saint can practiſe; for there is no one ſo good, who comes not ſhort of the Perfection that is here propos'd.</p>
               <p>Methinks I hear theſe wilfully ignorant men complaining of the difficulty of a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they have never ſearch'd into; as if the knowing the ways of Salvation did not belong to 'em.</p>
               <p>They uſe to urge, out of a religious Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they are not worthy to read it. 'Tis
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49837:24"/>
true, you are not worthy of the Grace of God, but ſince he is pleas'd to beſtow it on you, who will you have to receive it for you? He is ſuſpected by you, his Word is dangerous, and to be fear'd; he has declared and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it only to enſnare your Souls, to deceive and deſtroy 'em: You pretend you know your Weakneſs, and you ſhould wreſt the ſence of it; confeſs rather your own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs, and that you will turn that into Poyſon, which others, that you know, do into Honey. You call that Word dark, the firſt of which, made Light; that ſpiritual Lamp which was given us to no other end, but to enlighten us. You underſtand not that Word which the very Rocks did, that Word which rais'd not only the Dead to Life, but ſummon'd them who were not, as if they were; that Word which commanded Nothing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Something, and that Nothing obey'd. Confeſs then, that you are leſs ſenſible than the Rocks, the Dead, or Nothing it ſelf. This is the Natural Effect of the Counſel, and thoſe Inſtructions you receiv'd from your Teachers, who, to make their own Precepts the more eſteem'd, vilifie the Scripture. Its Purity ſerves not their Ambition, and not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to accuſe it of Falſhood, charge it with Obſcurity; and becauſe they cannot poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contradict, they miſinterpret it for their own Purpoſes: and tho' it's full of Prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neither to add to, or ſubſtract any thing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49837:24"/>
from it, yet they are not content to lay hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Impoſitions on the Conſciences of men, and load them with new Humane Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which make the State of the Goſpel more intolerable than that of the Law; but their Inſolence and Boldneſs are ſo exorbitant, as to retrench the Commandments of the Law, though the Reverence due to God, who writ 'em with his own hand, ought to have ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red 'em from that Sacrilege, and have ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd 'em for ever inviolable. Theſe men ſtudy Divinity, only to quarrel the Scriptures, and paſs for learned men in 'em, without having read 'em; and before they have read 'em, being prepoſſeſſed with the Sence of the Schools, they judge 'em with Prejudice: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, 'tis very hard to take any other Impreſſion, than that which they receiv'd in their Youth; and then, with what Folly does the Devil ſeduce the minds of men, that they who proceed in ſuch a Method, ſhould be thought wiſe and knowing?</p>
               <p>There are, 'tis true; myſterious Prophecies, that were not underſtood by thoſe who deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd 'em; the Knowledge of 'em was reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for ſuch that ſhould ſee their Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment. There is no one Paſſage in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that threatens Eternal Damnation to thoſe who don't clearly interpret the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> and we may attain to Salvation, without being fully acquainted with the meaning of the Viſions of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49837:25"/>
other Prophets. I will farther add, that the Predictions, Threats, and Promiſes, the full diſcovery of which neceſſarily depends on the future, do imprint certain <hi>Ideas</hi> upon us, of terrible pains prepar'd for the Wicked, and of a glorious Reward and felicity for the Good. Thoſe things we underſtand, certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us of the truth of what we do not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; and when the Reader does meet with clear Texts, by which he cannot explain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he muſt humble himſelf, confeſs his Ignorance or Incapacity, and ſo put a ſtop to his Preſumption. However it is, there is no one but may there diſcover ſuch Commands as he ought to obey, the Belief he ought to hold, a pattern of ſuch Prayers and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings which he ought to make to God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. And this indeed is all our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have to direct us in, without perplexing our Minds with nice and intricate Queſtions, or diſturbing us and themſelves with their vain, impertinent Thoughts. But let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of belying our ſelves, in ſaying this Word is clear and eaſie, becauſe the Doctors of the Age urge the contrary, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple believe it. No, no, 'tis truly very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and obſcure; Jeſus Chriſt himſelf does teſtifie it, but eſpecially to the Learned. He gives thanks to his Father that he has hid theſe things from 'em, and reveal'd 'em to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Children. 'Tis obſcure to ſuch who are caſt away, and whoſe eyes the God of this World
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49837:25"/>
has ſhut. Let us boldly confeſs, 'tis not to be underſtood barely by Humane Reaſon, We want the aſſiſtance of a Divine Spirit, to make us have clear conceptions of ſo Divine a Word. Thoſe who have not this Spirit can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not certainly comprehend it: the Children of God only know the Voice of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and only thoſe of the Flock know that of the Shepherd. Let us acknowledge, that too great a luſtre does make it ſeem obſcure to a great part of thoſe who look on it; only the generous and legitimate Eagles can fixedly behold this Sun, but the Owls and Birds of Darkneſs become blind by its light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>'TIS not to be doubted, but that the chief Enemy of God, the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of univerſal Rebellion, the great Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the World, does, by all Methods ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, promote his own Worſhip, and then no wonder that the moſt part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions are Worldly and Diabolical. He cares not how, or by whom they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, whether introduced by Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Opinion, Abuſe, or Cuſtome, ſo they are but alike Profane and Superſtitious; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe who at firſt adored <hi>Bel</hi> or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49837:26"/>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> do afterwards worſhip the Sun, the Moon, the whole Hoſt of Heaven, or of Hell. There is no Religion ſo extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, which he does not favour; nor is there any one diſpleaſing to him, but the true. He hath firſt added Gods to Gods, carry'd their Idols to the Holy place, and then hath found out wayes of oppoſing the Scripture by Scripture, and by untrue Interpretations on it, created falſe Beliefs. He hath ſerved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the Light, only to dazle, and of Truth, to diſguiſe falſhood, the better to put off his Impoſtures. He has his Learned men to teach and diſpute, his Profeſſors of Religion to give Examples of living well; his Prieſts, his Prophets, Martyrs and Confeſſors. And yet men are not ſenſible by what Spirit they are led, ſo obdurate are they, and given up to Satan; they are ſo fully poſſeſs'd with, and infatuated by him, that they ſcarce think that he is. They are ſo profane and preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, have ſo mighty an Opinion of their own Natural Reaſon, that they pretend to reform the Works of their Maker, and to judge of the Word of God, as if barely Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane; They content not themſelves with what they learn from Divinity, without the aid of Philoſophy, and confound both the one and the other; and thus, inſenſibly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the Profeſſion of Chriſtians, become as Heathens. They employ themſelves in the ſearch of nice and curious Queſtions, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49837:26"/>
not regarding what is clear and evident, take a pride in raiſing Doubts and Scruples; and in a collection of Contradictions, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Difficulties, pervert themſelves and others from the knowledge of the Truth. They take, when they pleaſe, figurative Expreſſions literally; they make the worſt Interpretations on thoſe things that are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and doubtful; and when they meet with Words of a double Senſe, they be ſure take that which ſuits beſt with their Intereſt and Deſigns. They puzzle each other with ſpecious Reaſons, and their Judgment is ſo weak as to allow, that two Contradictories may be maintain'd by equal Proofs. One would believe they learn, that they may be more ignorant, and that they ſtudy to be Scepticks; and by theſe means, they make Knowledge of leſs Value than Ignorance it ſelf.</p>
               <p>In Effect, if Humane Knowledge was grounded on any Certainty, thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo perfectly to underſtand the Art of reaſoning well, would be all of the ſame Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: but if their Opinions are ſo very diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and divided, and yet that there is but one Truth; in what can they be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding? in a certain crabbed, knotty artificial Divinity only, full of Metaphyſical Terms, which neither the Prophets, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles judg'd neceſſary to Salvation, or rather, have not at all known; and of which, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49837:27"/>
to their Example, 'tis much better to be ignorant than knowing.</p>
               <p>In Humane Inventions, in <hi>Chimaera's</hi> and odd Pictures, and indeed, in all things capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of producing Errors, and of deſtroying Reaſon by its own ſubtilty, you meet with ſome who are always vainly prating, eternal Diſputants, that employ their whole ſtudy in contradicting others, and who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd more for a falſe Syllogiſm, than for the Peace of the Church, or the Happineſs of the World. They never engage in any Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, but with a reſolution not to yield in the leaſt for the love of the Truth, but only to endeavour either to ſeduce their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by all manner of perſwaſions and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or at leaſt, to ſupplant 'em by Artificial Stratagems. They fear nothing ſo much as granting one Point, leſt then they ſhould be obliged to allow all. If any of 'em does in the leaſt yield, he loſes all his Credit with his Party; and if ſincere but in one act, 'twill be look'd on by 'em as an unpardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fault. They are alwayes armed with the fallacious Arguments of the Schools, and Proofs grounded on certain Maxims which they lay down, and oblige them to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as Principles of unqueſtionable Truth, which muſt admit of no Doubt, or endure any Examination; and on theſe depend the infallible conſequence of what they believe, or what they endeavour to perſwade us
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49837:27"/>
to: For, though their Impoſtures are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, yet they ſo diſguiſe 'em as to make 'em plauſible, that they may keep the People, by their pious Cheats, in their impious Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>They know how to take the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Enemy, they are well skill'd in ſhifting the moſt formal Aſſertions, they ſubtilly refine the very ſubſtance of the Matter, and the ſtate of the Queſtion; they have their Sophiſtical Diſtinctions, their ſet Comments, their Evaſions and Defeats; and thus every one in their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, as in War, aims only at Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. Execrable Souls! who regard more the defence of their Honour and Intereſt, than their Religion it ſelf, and who look after what they are to object, or anſwer, rather than what they ought to believe; who value not their want of Faith, provided they appear not to be void of Reaſon. Why ſhould we hope from theſe men for a candid and faithful Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the moſt hidden things, who only endeavour to render more obſcure thoſe which are clear and evident; and who ſo change the Ordinances of God, that 'tis eaſie to diſcover it; for, with the aſſiſtance even of common ſence, our Eyes alone may be juſt Judges of it? But we are not to expect other fruits from their Animoſity or Obdurateneſs, who are only free and ſociable with thoſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49837:28"/>
who ſuffer themſelves to be inſtructed, or wholly govern'd by 'em: For they are not capable of knowing more, having, as they preſume, learn't all they can, and propoſing to themſelves only the teaching of others, are pleas'd to be rather eſteem'd the Maſters of Error, than the Diſciples of Truth.</p>
               <p>But 'twill be asked me, if in a Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſo great weight as this, I can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, without Preſumption, that my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on herein is infallible, or at leaſt, more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten'd than that of the Learned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. I anſwer, that I profeſs to embrace no other than what is eſtabliſh'd on the clear Evidence of Scripture, intelligible by the meaneſt of men, and which it has pleas'd God to reveal to the humble, and hide from the proud. No other than that by which I am taught, that no one ought to preſume beyond what is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. That 'tis abſolutely forbid either to add, or take from it; that thoſe who promote God's Honour and Service, barely by humane Doctrines, do it in vain; and by their Traditions, make the Law of no effect. No other than that which preſſes me to avoid profane Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vain and impertinent Diſputes, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Contradictions, of a Knowledge, falſly ſo called, which 'tis difficult to purſue, without erring from the Faith, and becoming even impious. Beſides, I anſwer, that theſe Demands cannot be juſtly propos'd to thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49837:28"/>
who ſerve themſelves only of their Senſe and Reaſon, to know the Voice of their Lord and Father, to receive his Commands, and obey him; who preſume not boldly to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their own idle Conceits with his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and who expound the Scripture but by it ſelf. 'Tis from the unbounded Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and ſublime Viſions of theſe Angelical, Seraphick, enlighten'd Doctors, ariſe ſo many extravagant Opinions; and not from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent reading of ordinary men, who in the Words of eternal Life, ſeek after nothing but ſuch Light as may direct 'em in the ways of Repentance and Salvation. There are none eſteem'd the Authors of Hereſies, but thoſe who preſume they are able to defend 'em; who by the ſame Spirit of Pride and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence they propos'd 'em, maintain them. Theſe are Errors then, which the Learned can only pretend to, and Follies, which the Wiſe can only commit; the Vanity of knowing what others know not, the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of having firſt diſcover'd ſome new Invention, the giving a Name to ſome Sect, and being it's Head; the Terrors of Poverty, a thirſt after Honour and Riches; a deſire to pleaſe the Great men of the World, to merit their Favours, to flatter their Paſſions, to carry on their Intereſt, for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their own, are thoſe Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which contain the ſecret Articles, and chief Myſteries of their Faith. They willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49837:29"/>
abandon whatever concerns the Intereſt of their Souls for the advantage of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; they deſire that Religion ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Fortune, and Conſcience to Neceſſity. Error is no ſooner broach'd, than there are thoſe found who receive, and promote it; not out of Devotion, but from a Deſign of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome new Party in a Quiet Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thence to create trouble and confuſion. <hi>Europe</hi> is ſo divided into Sects, and torn in pieces by the violence of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Factions, that hereupon the Atheiſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, the <hi>Mahometans</hi> are confirmed in their Errours, the <hi>Jews</hi> ſcandalized, and all equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harden'd. This does not happen from Queſtions ſometimes concerning the Elect, and at others of the Reprobate, but from the inconſiderateneſs of thoſe who enquire after Reaſons thereof, when ſo great an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle as St. <hi>Paul</hi> found none, but the good Will and Pleaſure of God. I confeſs, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſufficiently wonder at thoſe, who ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſlight thoſe things which God is pleas'd to make known to us, ſo raſhly to ſearch after ſuch, which, for ſome time, he thinks fit to hide from us; without being too indiſcreet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſumptuous, without not only an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, but dangerous Curioſity. I will not diſturb the Publick Quiet, by raiſing freſh Doubts concerning the two Natures, the two Wills, or the Subſtance of Jeſus Chriſt, without too great a love of my ſelf;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49837:29"/>
I will not pretend to be the Comforter, with <hi>Montanus,</hi> nor the Saviour of Men, with <hi>Menander;</hi> I will live as a Believer, with the Faithful; not ſcandalizing my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, either by a too particular Opinion of my own ſufficiency, or by a contempt of that of others.</p>
               <p>So long as the Weakneſs of Men ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce in the Church no other Scruples but what are made concerning Meats, or ſuch like; ſo long as no other Ornaments are uſed but flat Pictures, that they provoke not the Jealouſie of God by emboſs'd Images; ſo long as they uſe only ſome ſuperfluous Ceremonies, which in the judgment of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, are ſometimes indifferent, and at others neceſſary, although that Errour which ſeems at firſt ſight but ſmall, is, for the moſt part, a degree to a greater; ſo long as the ſtate of the Church, though not ſo pure as might be wiſh'd for, yet is at leaſt tolerable, I will not forſake its Communion; but I will with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw my ſelf from all thoſe Aſſemblies where I ſhall be forc'd to conform to the External Acts of Superſtition or Idolatry, and to yield a Religious Worſhip, not only to Saints, and to Angels, who are fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with us, but Wood and Stone; where the Sacraments are but partially admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and where the Commandments of God are deſtroy'd by thoſe of men. And I ſhall not believe, that there can be any
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49837:30"/>
Schiſm, where there is ſo juſt an occaſion to ſeparate; and indeed, where 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do otherwiſe. For what Senſe can thoſe words bear, which oblige the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to forſake the Camp, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 13. or <hi>Babylon, Rev.</hi> 18. 4. and not only by their Minds, but their Bodies too, ſince as well the one as the other are conſecrated to the Glory of their Creator? And when we ſee <hi>the Abomination of Deſolation ſet up in the Holy place, Dan.</hi> 9. 27. ought we not to <hi>flye to the Mountains, Mat.</hi> 24. 15, 16. And if Antichriſt be once plac'd in the Church of God, ſhall we obey him, and call his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands thoſe of the Church? I will go out then from this Confuſion, and conform my ſelf to the Order and Diſcipline of the true Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, though in ſecret, in the midſt of her Enemies, retired; tho' I follow her to the Wilderneſs, and ſearch her in the clefts of the Rocks and Caverns; tho' ſhe appears not glorious but by Perſecution, and amidſt her ſufferings, ſhe ſhines with no Scarlet, but that of the Blood of Martyrs; whether the Storm be over, or her Tears wiped off, that her Voice may be heard, and her Face ſeen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:49837:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>OBſerving the univerſal Diviſion of ſo many Sects, each of which, had it's Teacher and Head, and ſome their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, I believed it highly neceſſary, to make our Applications to God by Prayer, to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves, and ſeriouſly conſult, not the uncertain Imaginations of men, but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Rules which God himſelf hath taught us; I was the more ſollicitous for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of theſe things, becauſe God, by his Word, has fore-warned us, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many Antichriſts ſhall ariſe in the Church, and ſome one above the reſt, but alſo, that from the time of the Apoſtles, the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> was ſet up, and was conſequently to be advanc'd, notwithſtanding the Blindneſs of thoſe who would not ſee it, and who ſearch for Pretences for their voluntary Ignorance: I look'd therefore on thoſe Religions as er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, which were not purely Evangelical and Divine, which are mix'd with the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, and lay all their ſtreſs on Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions too ſublime, and not to be reſolved; the Controverſie whereof is too nice and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. I had a very ill Opinion of thoſe which are introduc'd by Tyranny, or the Sword, which are ſo ill-grounded, that their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors dare not communicate 'em to others; and to that end, keep the People under a ſottiſh
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49837:31"/>
and brutal Ignorance. I had no kindneſs for thoſe whoſe Intereſt is ſecular, and whoſe Kingdom is of this World, whatever name of a Church they may take to themſelves, becauſe they invert the Order of Jeſus Chriſt, and preſumptuouſly transform that into a time of Glory which he hath ordained for the Patience of Saints.</p>
               <p>Moreover, if we are to credit Univerſal Experience, whatever is ſubject to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of men does decay, and become as changeable and inconſtant, earlier or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as they themſelves. Children continue not willingly in the Belief of their Fathers, at leaſt, of their Grand-fathers; Faith is not hereditary, as the Title of an Houſe or an Eſtate. They have only remaining for the moſt part the external Profeſſion, which, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up either from their Birth or Cuſtom, they eaſily forſake what their perverſe Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours forbid 'em to love, or know; and if they have been initiated in good Principles, they end in bad ones. Thus the Purity of the Goſpel, in whatever Town or Province it has been received, has ſcarce proceeded to the third Generation; and the Apoſtles themſelves lived only in thoſe Churches they founded, Errour inſenſibly creeping into the place of Truth. God already threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them to extinguiſh their-Light, or to transfer it, letting 'em ſee that Faith was not a particular Priviledge to one Place, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49837:31"/>
or People, and that the Church being Catholick, could not be ſubjected to the Power of one King, or the Government of one Prieſt. It is in vain Men pretend to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle a durable State, or find a laſting Sovereign good in this Life; they cannot long endure even Proſperity it ſelf, and the alone way to ruine 'em, is to grant 'em even their own Deſires. If our firſt Parents, placed in Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence amidſt the Fruit and Flowers of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Garden, could not withſtand the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſions of the Evil Spirit, though he took on him only the form of a Serpent, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd 'em but an Apple to tempt 'em; how then ſhall they who are Sinners by Nature, reſiſt him when he appears as an Angel of Light, and offers them all the Advantages they can poſſibly deſire. 'Tis certain, that the Devil for the moſt part does ſeduce men by a Paradiſe of Pleaſures, to caſt 'em into the bottomleſs Abyſs of Hell; and 'tis by a Hell of Pains and Afflictions, that God does uſually try men, to exalt 'em to the Glory of Paradiſe. Riches are of ſo great Diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to their Poſſeſſors, that they keep 'em, as a weighty Burthen, from aſcending to Heaven. They are ſo incoherent with the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, that he who had the Command of all, and could have employ'd 'em without Abuſe, voluntarily makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf poor, to procure us eternal Salvation, and to make us rich by his Poverty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49837:32"/>
In effect, what Hiſtory aſſerts is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by all good men, that the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of Emperours, and the vaſt Gifts of Lords and Ladies, have been the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and fatal Poyſon that could have been ſpread in the Church: for, from hence Piety began to grow cold, and to yield to the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Age; and all Chriſtian Vertues were ſoon ſtifled by Luxury and Abundance. Theſe Benefactors who are ſo highly magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, do ſufficiently prove, that they were unacquainted with the Will of Jeſus Chriſt, and with the Calling of his Miniſters, ſince they beſtow on 'em ſuch mighty temporal Riches, as to make 'em Sharers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this World. Wealth on a ſudden encreaſing ſo much, made thoſe who were true Believers plainly foreſee, that none but the ambitious and covetous; none but ill men would be advanc'd to Preferment in the Church, and that it would be brought to the unhappy Extremity of being govern'd only by it's Enemies.</p>
               <p>Since then, I know not by what Permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heaven Corruption has been ſo rife, that the Eccleſiaſticks are become worſe than Seculars. They have receiv'd their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from men, which they ought to have had alone from God, in ſo religious a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; and if they have been concern'd in ſpiritual Affairs, it has been rather to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand than ſerve; to raiſe themſelves to great
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49837:32"/>
Honours, and to make themſelves Biſhops over the reſt of Biſhops. They have imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him who not ſatisfy'd with the Joys of his Fellow-Angels, boldly aſpired to the utmoſt height of Pride, ſaying, in his Heart, <hi>I will raiſe my Throne above the Stars, and ſhall be made like to the Almighty.</hi> Inſtead of a due Obſervation of that Worſhip and Service God himſelf has appointed, they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd it's Simplicity, affecting Pomp and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very in their Devotions, (and as they ſay themſelves) ſanctifying the Ceremonies of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> by introducing of 'em into the Church. Not being able to endure the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Doctrine, without altering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſing of it into a thouſand Shapes, they have, to this purpoſe, made choice of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers after their own faſhion, who raiſing nice and ſcrupulous Queſtions, have underſtood 'em as little as their Hearers: and whatever Colour of Senſe they may bear, being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd in elegant and florid Words, they both ſeem equally ſatisfy'd. We have ſeen, that poor Worms, juſt riſen from the Duſt, and ready to return thither again, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolently taken upon them the Title of Gods, and commanded the very Angels as their Guards, and have diſpos'd of Heaven and Hell at their Pleaſure, as of their Eſtates. But what likelyhood is there, that thoſe who are rais'd only by Corruptions, by Bribery, by Threats, Promiſes, or private Bargains,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49837:33"/>
ſhould be the infallible Diſpenſers of God's Will, and Judges of Men's Faith? What Patience would not be tyred to ſee thoſe who are alone guided by the Spirit of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, who make the Church an Houſe of Trade and Den of Thieves, tranſported to ſuch heights of Impiety, as to make the Holy Ghoſt an Accomplice of all their Crimes? Their Pretences of having Power in Heaven makes 'em ſeem to affect leſs the Good of the Earth, that we may believe, that the Divine Authority and theirs are equal. But as they are Lyons in Cruelty, ſo are they Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeches for Covetouſneſs, being always find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out new Methods of laying numberleſs Impoſitions on the People. For, to paſs by their ſeveral Excommunications, Injunctions, transferring of Cauſes, and Exactions, under pretence of War againſt the Enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, there is no end of their firſt Fruits, Bulls, Indulgences, Canons, Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, Pardons for Faults, and Penances, and ſuperabundant Satisfactions. All theſe Inventions make Sins venial ſo far as they are vendible; for they ſet to ſale, their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Sacrifices, and proſtitute even Heaven and God himſelf; ſo that he that offers moſt has the Bargain. Horrid Inventions, that transform <hi>Simon Peter</hi> into <hi>Simon Magus!</hi> who make (as much as in their Power) Jeſus Chriſt a Tyrant, and his Apoſtles Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Huckſters. What Divinity! That thoſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49837:33"/>
who are but able to pay for it, ſhall, in a Moment, be deliver'd from the Torments of Hell, at leaſt, from thoſe of Purgatory, tho' the Sins they have committed are never ſo enormous, whilſt others remain there thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Years, unleſs perchance, Poverty ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther voluntary or forc'd, or Faſtings, even to the murdering of themſelves, or ſome other ſort of Severities of Nakedneſs or whipping do redeem 'em! But beſides this ſpiritual Merchandize, and expoſing things ſacred to Sale, by what divine Inſpiration do they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Subjects of their Oaths of Fidelity, and diſpenſe with their Allegiance to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Princes, whom they endeavour rather to terrifie than reform; and that dreadful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition which renders 'em deaf to the juſt Remonſtrances of thoſe who breath after Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation only, is it an Imitation of the Meekneſs and Clemency of Jeſus Chriſt, or of the barbarous Cruelty of <hi>Herod,</hi> who put to Death ſo many Innocents, leſt he ſhould miſs of him who was Innocence it ſelf?</p>
               <p>O God! How long wilt thou ſuffer the Children of Pride to reign, who make Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but a Maſque, and uſe thy Name only to render the People willingly tributary? How long wilt thou endure that horrible Scandal theſe men give to the Gentiles, who have yet ſome ſhadow of Reſpect for the Law thou thy ſelf haſt pronounced! and ſeeing the Objects of thy Jealouſie, carved Images
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49837:34"/>
in the Churches, and the Feſtivals with which they are honour'd, the religious Offices paid to 'em, believe this is by the Command of thy Chriſt, and that Chriſtians do worſhip as many Men as the Heathens did Gods? When wilt thou by the Breath of thy Mouth deſtroy thoſe, who with as much. Inſolence as Hypocriſie, abuſe the People by their Impoſtures, which even the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts</hi> diſcover, and from thence believe Religion a Trick, ſince it's proved only by falſe and counterfeit Miracles? Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, we muſt have Recourſe to thy Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Power; for, we endeavour but in vain to convince 'em, having ſo extraordinary an Opinion of themſelves, pretending to a Knowledge from Heaven it ſelf, that they believe their Senſe is far beyond that of other men; that their Thoughts are the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Dictates of Reaſon; and that whatever Impreſſions they receive, is from the mouth of Truth it ſelf. If the <hi>Heathens</hi> did with that Violence reſiſt the Goſpel, and the Knowledge of the true God offer'd to 'em, thoſe who had no other Gods, but ſuch as Men made; what Oppoſition is to be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from thoſe who ſhrowd themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Authority of God himſelf? who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves poſſeſs'd of all Right, both humane and divine; and that to the end of the World, all Power is given 'em both in Heaven and Earth; and, who under the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49837:34"/>
empty Title of a Church, make their Errors ſeem fair and plauſible, and thus, too unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd paſs their Deceits upon the World; Princes, who at firſt might have prevented theſe Abuſes, have, by I don't know what irreligious Prudence, ſuffer'd them; whether from want of a Knowledge of 'em, or from ſome weighty Cares of State, found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged to diſſemble that Knowledge, or that they were conſtrain'd to yield to the Appointment of Heaven, and could not, but in vain, oppoſe the fulfilling of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies: Prophecies, which having long ſince repreſented to us things as we now ſee 'em, leave in-excuſable ſo many learned men whom Fear or Hope has made ſilent, and who, by their unfaithful ſilence, have ſtrengthned what by a juſt Contradiction they might have render'd weak and invalid; or, who rather indeed have with too great Ingenuity defended Error, which they ought to have buried under an eternal Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>THERE is no greater Tyrant in the World, or that makes himſelf more obey'd, than Cuſtom, eſpecially in Matters of Religion; and that which makes it the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49837:35"/>
more abſolute, is, the Obligations it layes on mens Conſciences, which for fear of erring, are oblig'd to purſue thoſe Rules it at firſt preſcribed: This makes it plain to us, that notwithſtanding the vain preſumption of men, and the good Opinion they have of their own Parts, they are yet ſo naturally weak and infirm, that it ſeems to us that their Soul came not from Heaven, but is purely Senſual, and that all the Perfection which they have attained to, is only an Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of what they have learn'd. They lay ſo great ſtreſs upon their Birth, Education, or Chance it ſelf, that that which firſt takes with 'em, does ſo ſtrongly engage 'em, that they are made incapable of believing any thing, but that of which they were firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded. Upon this account I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd, as much as poſſible, to diſpoſſeſs my ſelf of thoſe impreſſions were made on me in my Youth, to look on 'em as altogether foreign, that the Truth might be the ſole Object of my Faith, and that Cuſtom might not tyrannically prevail over my Reaſon. Then I have always thought, that he ought not to be truly valued as Man, who was by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſs'd by the courſe of the World, who was not in ſome ſort infinitely above the Advice that is commonly given him; who was ſo weak and mean-ſpirited, as to abandon his own Judgment, and ſuffer himſelf to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlav'd by Popular Error. But men, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49837:35"/>
for the moſt part, of ſuch things only to which they have been us'd; and judging according to their cuſtomary Practice, have contracted ſo ill an habit, that to remedy it is extreamly difficult, the very faculties of the Mind being ſeized, which ſhould be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to deliver 'em from it; they have certain Notions ſo deeply imprinted on 'em, that they become natural; and paſs for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelf: they know nothing elſe, they underſtand no other Language, and without changing their very Nature, they cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Belief.</p>
               <p>They are not ſenſible, that inſtead of maintaining the Truth they defend only the firſt Opinion they have receiv'd, without examining whether it be as true as pleaſing to 'em; whether grounded on Prejudice, on ſpecious Pretences, probable Gueſſes, or wordly Conſiderations. They conſider not, that all Sects whatever, claim the ſame Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that all Hereſies have ſome who take their part, and with equal Paſſion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote 'em; have their learned Patrons, who think they ought not to yield the one to the other, either in Opinion or Knowledge. They reflect not how ſtrangely they are tranſported with a fond Love of themſelves, that perſuades 'em they mightily differ from their own kind; that they have a much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Conception of things than others; that they are enlightened by ſome Divine Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49837:36"/>
whilſt others have ſcarce Humane Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Then they proceed, Nothing is ſo true, or to be ſo eaſily comprehended, as what they believe. The proof of it is clear, and it's Demonſtration infallible; He that perceives not this, knows nothing Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is conſtantly on their ſide, but Error and Obſtinacy on that of their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: What unaccuſtom'd madneſs and blind Rage, or what Pride keeps 'em from ſeeing, that even thoſe whom they wonder at, look on them with Amazement; and that they are ridiculous to thoſe they laugh at; and that they only ſeem to pity thoſe, who have a real pity and compaſſion on them? Ought they not, obſerving the great Uncertainty of things, and the frailty of mens Parts, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to univerſal Principles, and firmly adhere to the Commands of the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Law-giver, who expreſsly forbids us to turn either to the right or to the left?</p>
               <p>But they are ſo far prepoſſeſs'd with what the World preſents 'em; the Concerns of this Life have ſo blinded their Judgment, that they take no Care to inform themſelves better, or do they conſider, that neither Time, or Country, or any thing whatever, can proſcribe againſt the Truth; beſides this, they are captivated with the Belief of their Parents, their Examples at home, with the multitude and Antiquity it ſelf, which we cannot but attribute to Error, which has ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49837:36"/>
inſenſibly crept in amongſt us, and has been advanc'd, from Time to Time, to the height of Power, that it's Enemies, in oppoſing of it, have been utterly foyl'd, or at leaſt, very much baffl'd. 'Tis very difficult, without doubt, to condemn our Country or our Prince; to ſpeak againſt our Anceſtors, our neareſt Friends or Relations; nay, even againſt thoſe who have taught us: but the Buſineſs is, we muſt ſtrive to diſingage our ſelves from the Falſhood of mens vain Imaginations, to juſtifie Truth againſt the Teſtimony of it's many Enemies; to repair the Decays of an almoſt-ſpent Life; to ſeek after our chief Good and Happineſs; to give our Aſſents to the Words of him that ſays, <hi>Thoſe who love Father or Mother, or any thing elſe better than him, are not worthy of him.</hi> But for all this, they perſiſt in their Reſolutions of following the Example of thoſe worthy men whoſe Authority they urge, not conſidering, that even the <hi>Turks</hi> can at leaſt ſay thus much for themſelves, and the Heathens more. But, they chooſe to ſtick to theſe falſe Principles, rather than to give themſelves the Pains of examining into the beſt Doctrine can be propoſed to 'em. Then they are, as it were, liſted and enſlav'd to live and dye, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Tyrannical Power of certain Guides, who tell 'em they cannot err, that the Spirit of God does neceſſarily aſſiſt in their Aſſemblies and Determinations; that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49837:37"/>
their Power is abſolute; and beſides all this, can reconcile Religion with the Advantages of the World: Oft thus they very eaſily ſuffer themſelves to be perſuaded, it being moſt agreeable to their Inclinations, and for the accompliſhment of their Deſigns. They are pleas'd to hear others ſlander'd, and hug themſelves to ſee thoſe convicted of Error, who talk to 'em of Truth: She is ſuſpected by 'em, they dare ſcarce look on her, leſt being conquer'd by her Beauty, they find themſelves obliged to court her, or to ſuffer ſome juſt Diſpleaſures on her Account, which they are unwilling to ſubmit to. The Truth of it is, they are wilfully ignorant of thoſe Principles they will not put in Practice, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a certain Satisfaction and Quiet in their Ignorance, that Law, though never ſo juſt, which reſtrains their Liberty, is uneaſie to 'em. It is enough, that Afflictions being a neceſſary part of the Goſpel-Diſpenſation, to deter thoſe of this World from it's Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They rather yield to the violent Stream that hurries 'em on, than ſtrive againſt it; they had rather be lull'd into a ſoft Sleep, attended by agreeable Dreams, than hear the troubleſome Voice of thoſe who waken 'em only to diſturb 'em. O Brutiſh Stupidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty! O Apparent Hardneſs! Muſt Vice and Error, becauſe grown common, looſe their Name, and be call'd Vertue and Wiſdom? Muſt Cuſtom be ſo prevalent, as to hinder
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49837:37"/>
men from being reaſonable. But, 'tis not to be doubted, but that thoſe whom the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſtiles Drunk, are ſo great Strangers to their own Senſes, ſo deprav'd in their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, as to take that for true which is falſe, and that they ſee not indeed what they ſee. And 'tis not to be queſtion'd, but that they reſemble thoſe who had ſo long us'd themſelves to the eating of Poyſon, that at length it was even Meat and Nouriſhment to 'em.</p>
               <p>In the mean while, they have plac'd all ſort of Religion in humane Traditions and Superſtition; they have not conſulted either with Senſe or Reaſon; and I don't know from whence it is, that the greateſt part of Men, the moſt exquiſitely curious in other things, make no Search at all after that which is moſt neceſſary. Their Knowledge of God is, as that of the <hi>Barbarians,</hi> obſcure, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and inſignificant; and had they been born amongſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> they would have believ'd as they do, becauſe they have but one Faith, called Acquired, depending on Tradition, that never ſaved any one. This is that of the Wicked as well as theirs; nay, that of the Devils themſelves, who, as theſe, own a God, and that he is Almighty, that he created the World, and ſent his Son; who believe the great Myſtery of his Birth, of his Life, and of his Death, and who yet muſt not pretend to have a ſhare in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49837:38"/>
or Glory. To obſerve the inconſiderate Zeal of a People, who when they pray, are ignorant of what they ſay, is a thing, claims both our Pitty and Horror too; who ſatisfie themſelves with bare Shews, and are led away by ſuch Preachers, who rather thirſt after the Blood of their Neighbours, than deſire their Salvation. A People abus'd with Vanities, imagining, God is better pleas'd in one place than another, and who ſearches amongſt Strangers for what he may find equally amongſt his own. An ignorant and unwiſe People, who ſee not, that under the Goſpel they raiſe (without thinking of it) <hi>Judaiſm</hi> again, againſt what is ſaid in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>That the time is come, that thoſe who will worſhip God truly, muſt do it in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> And how do either Places or Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages ſerve in order to this? How do thoſe Acts of Devotions contribute to it, which are looked upon only from their Quantity and not Quality, which are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended either from their Faith or Piety, but by certain Tasks they impoſe on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and by ſome odd Numbers in which they believe great Vertue, and which they vainly affect, as the <hi>Magicians</hi> did of old? Superſtitious Devotions, full of dark and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Doubts, as if they were afraid to know the Truth, and that the very Light was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to 'em; who apprehend nothing of the True Religion, but what is ſaid of it by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49837:38"/>
their Enemies, and therefore, hate and ſpeak reproachfully of it, and always repreſent it after the moſt dreadful manner they can imagine. It cannot, certainly, be difficult to perſwade thoſe to what we will, whom we have once brought under a blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; to which, they yield with as much Eaſe and poorneſs of Spirit, as if they ſaid, we will be ſtupid, we will be ſenceleſs. For, if if they once ſay that they'll follow the Church, they contradict themſelves, and confeſs they embrace what they know: but, what more than an ordinary Knowledge is requir'd to diſcern betwixt what is true and what is falſe? But, why muſt they be blindly obedient, whom God has endu'd with Reaſon, and given his Precepts to 'em with this expreſs Command, <hi>That Fathers inſtruct their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in 'em, and that all ſearch the Scriptures, the alone means to direct us to the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi> But how can they inform others, who are themſelves ſo ignorant; who, as a juſt Puniſhment on 'em, for adoring Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, are ſo beſotted, as to ask their Adviſe and Counſel; this is to conſult even Stones and Marble.</p>
               <p>Ye blind, perceive ye not, that ye become inſenſible, by paying a Veneration to things that are ſo? Underſtand ye not, that even Reaſon tells you, that you are beneath what you worſhip, and yet your depraved Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations have made you leſs valuable than
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49837:39"/>
the works of your own hands? Be not thus childiſh, but leave theſe Babies to Children; they are ridiculous, in a full grown and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Age. You are not leſs blameable than Atheiſts themſelves, for you, as they, render the Deity inſignificant, and of no Uſe, making it material, and repreſenting him who is only Spirit, by a piece of Wood or Stone, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he hath ſo often, in his Jealouſie, ſaid, <hi>To what will you liken Me?</hi> You audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly make him who made you, and moſt ingratefully endeavour to ridicule him, by giving Eyes to him which ſee not, Ears that hear not, Hands that work not, and Feet that are not able to walk. 'Tis poſſible you may pretend, that your good Intentions are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for your Ignorance; you take ſuch mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as are preſcrib'd to you; and in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you do, you believe you ſerve God, tho' you don't only perſecute, but murder his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Hypocrites, know that under the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of good Intentions, infinite Abuſes creep into the World, for unleſs they are grounded on holy Writ, they are ſinful. Thus the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were puniſh'd for their want of conſideration, in worſhipping the golden Calf, whilſt they deſign'd the celebrating a Solemn Feaſt to the Eternal. Thus alſo <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> provok'd him to Anger, and kindled that Fire which conſum'd 'em, when they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only to offer him Perfumes. Thus <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> was ſuddenly ſlain for having laid his hand
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49837:39"/>
on the Ark, when falling, tho' he intended to have kept it up. If good Intentions would ſerve, the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, Enemies of Jeſus Chriſt, were not guilty; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this teſtimony of 'em, that they had the Zeal of God; then alſo would many wicked Sayings become juſtifiable; and the moſt barbarous Maſſacres wou'd be plac'd amongſt good Works, all ſorts of Religion would be ſafe, and almoſt all men ſaved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>'TIS to no purpoſe therefore to alledge our good Intentions in the Exerciſe of a Religion already furniſh'd with ſufficient Directions and infallible Rules, as alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd by an abſolute Obedience to 'em. There is no need of other Advice, or farther Inſtructions, where we are in no danger, and cannot act but with certainty; where even our great Maſters in the Profeſſion are no farther authoriz'd than to ſee the Orders of the Church carefully obſerv'd; and thus the Church cannot err. So that thoſe who abuſe themſelves and others with theſe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial Excuſes, are to be look'd on as Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, who have never ſeriouſly thought on thoſe things that are Heavenly, but make it their buſineſs only to procure the Advantages of this World. I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd 'em under all ſorts of conditions, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49837:40"/>
whether it be, that the Scripture has foretold it, or that Experience has proved it. I have obſerv'd, that even our great ones have ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom any Tincture of true Piety, ſuffering themſelves to be byaſs'd by Faction, rather than Reaſon, taking no Meaſures, but what are ſerviceable to their Intereſt. They make Religion only as a Cloak to their Ambitious Deſigns; and many of 'em enter into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, and lay dangerous Plots againſt their lawful Sovereign, and the Gevernment, under Catholick Pretences. They inſtill a certain Courage and falſe Generoſity, into 'em, even in their Infancy: They rarely diſcourſe to 'em of the Knowledge of God; and beſides a Sermon ſometimes, which they hear with Impatience, they look upon their Converſation who talk to 'em of Religion, or a future State, as uncourtly and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. They are not deſirous to make any farther Search than their Knowledge already reaches; or, if ſome of 'em pretend to more Light, they forge to themſelves ſome bare Probabilities, to perſwade 'em, that things really are as their Paſſions ſuggeſt 'em to 'em. To contradict 'em would be inſolent; for, being in Power, and poſſeſs'd of Fortunes, they think they are of good Sence too; they back their Opinions with Authority, and make indiſputable Decrees. They cannot bear with that Company which favours not that Love they have of themſelves, or that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49837:40"/>
verſation which does not flatter their Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and is agreeable to their Sence and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. They are altogether vain, both in their Diſcourſe and Thoughts; they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be abuſed with the out-ſide and Appearance of things, being ſo pleas'd with empty Shadows, that they will not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of thoſe things that are moſt ſolid and ſubſtantial, if convey'd to 'em by weak In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. They would never have received the Law from the mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> becauſe of his Imperfection of Speech. Truth muſt be repreſented to them, with Ornament and Splendor, that is, with the Artifices of Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: and, without the Gayety of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Rhetorick, we cannot perſwade 'em to any thing, though ſent by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. If he ſend his own Meſſengers, ſhould he call 'em out from the common people, being either Shepherds or Fiſher-men, they will judge of 'em as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, whom they look'd on, as contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſorry Wretches; 'twas well, if they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtoned, maſſacred, baniſh'd or impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd 'em.</p>
               <p>There is a Wiſdom in the World made up of Show, of Grimaces, a refin'd Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, by which, men deceive themſelves and others too; 'tis this makes their Life but as a continual Maſcarade or Comedy, in which, every one repreſents another Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon than his own, affecting nothing more
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49837:41"/>
than to appear what really he is not. This incurable Madneſs, which goes under the Name of humane Prudence, does ſo diſorder their Underſtandings, and fills 'em with ſuch idle chimerical Notions, that it incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citates 'em to comprehend any Divine Truth. They employ themſelves only in ſeeking after thoſe things that are periſhing, not conſidering, that they heap up Goods for thoſe that will riotouſly waſte 'em; and are covetous, only to the making others, either luxurious or prodigal. What Fathers! who either that they are too indulgent to, or that they utterly forſake their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſeem equally to conſult their Ruine; who, whilſt they are afraid of the Vanity of ſome, diſinherit others of their right of Succeſſion; and, before they know what either Concupiſcence or Continency mean, under pretence of devoting 'em to God's Service, baſely ſacrifice 'em to their own Covetouſneſs. What Prudence! which makes the free minds of Men Slaves to their Bodies; who are expert only in flying from their chief Good, ingenious to their own Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and ſubtle to deceive themſelves! 'Twas this caus'd our firſt Parents to loſe that happy State of Paradiſe; and which, inviting men to fancy to themſelves a thouſand ways of living, hath fill'd the Earth with Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Idolatries, Sects, Hereſies, and impious Religions. By this, have the Saints been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49837:41"/>
our Saviour crucify'd, it having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to promote and defend too many Antichriſts, whoſe Reign muſt be in this World. This it is alſo, that continually oppoſes the holy Spirit, and with Inſolence, dares diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with his ſacred Word, either by wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sence, or retrenching it's terms when it cannot ſo diſguiſe 'em, as to make 'em contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to it ſelf. This is it which accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates all to Intereſt, and which their Service being in an untelligible Tongue, from whence the People are kept in Ignorance, their Prayers directed to the Creature inſtead of the Creator: Images bore on mens Shoulders, and ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd by Songs, with more ſuch like Actions, or worſe, pretends to make all theſe paſs for ſlight Inconveniences, or things indifferent.</p>
               <p>Of all ſorts of Hypocrites, thoſe are the moſt dangerous, who make Piety their Pretence; for, there are none who can ſo eaſily put tricks upon us, as ſuch who make profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; they having the Reputation of decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no one. Some appear to us ſoft and mild, others ſevere and ſtately; and both ways they alike endeavour to recommend their Virtues to us. If their appearing Sweetneſs betrays us, their Haughtineſs contemns us, and the great value they ſet on themſelves, ſuffers 'em to have very little for their Neighbours.</p>
               <p>They have the art to appear for ſome time, what their Profeſſ on or their Habits ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige 'em to be. But, this forced Goodneſs
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49837:42"/>
this ſtudyed Compliance remains no longer than till they are either thwarted in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt or Opinions. They ſeem mild and gentle, but cann't long diſſemble it; for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the leaſt provoked, they ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Lyons and Tygers, which were hid under a Humane Shape. Yet, their Anger, if we may believe 'em, is never rais'd but by Reaſon, and their very Crimes are more juſtifiable, than the beſt Actions of other men. If we look on 'em as Saints, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves ſo, and lay claim to it, as a true Reward of their falſe Devotion. This ſhadow of Holineſs, or rather, this glittering Zeal, has ſo often amazed me, that I have conſider'd, that each Nation had it's devout religious Men, and that the auſtere Life of ours, was not to be compar'd with that of the <hi>Cynick,</hi> the <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> the <hi>Hierophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> or the <hi>Gymnoſophiſts;</hi> and with this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, that thoſe miſerable <hi>Pagans</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd the Devils, as they commanded 'em; but theſe adore the true God after ſuch a Manner as he would not be.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Whence is it Men embrace the Principles of Religion, unleſs, from a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inclination, which is common to <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> and <hi>Infidels;</hi> or, from Ambition, to let the World ſee, Government cannot be ſupported but by their Juſtice and Probity? There are ſcarce any do good for the Love of it, each one has his by End, and thoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49837:42"/>
who act not according to their Duty, for fear of Puniſhment, are engag'd to it by hopes of Honour or Riches. Many have Cunning and Patience enough to conceal their bad Deſigns, till they have obtain'd their deſir'd Ends; but, having rais'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the higheſt Pitch they can, and ſtanding in need of no farther Aſſiſtance for their Advancement, diſcover 'em. To this purpoſe, they uſe all Artifices imaginable; they ſpeak the Language of Saints, they write Books, they look grave and demure, they declare many Truths; which frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provokes me to ſay, Who is it that hath put the Word of God in the Mouths of theſe Men, and who makes us even now find <hi>Saul</hi> amongſt the Prophets? I have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively heard their Sermons, which are furniſh'd with common Places, with deep and ſerious Meditations; but, they are ſo tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally paſſionate, that they rather become the Theatre than the Pulpit, and are fill'd with all the rhetorical Flowers that Art can ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply 'em with, either to move or pleaſe. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever good Inſtructions may be interlarded in their Diſcourſes, they ſtill cloſely adhere to their ill Principles; for, having no other aim, but the gaining of ſome Preferment to exchange that, and ſo riſe from Dignity to Dignity, they preach Jeſus Chriſt only with Emulation; they bear him witneſs, but as thoſe evil Spirits who confeſs'd that he was
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49837:43"/>
the Son of God, and going out of one Body, deſir'd leave to enter into another. 'Twould be a matter of little weight, if men diſguis'd themſelves only before men, even to the diſſembling of their Diſſimulation, if they made not an apparent and publick Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Hypocriſie before God himſelf. 'Tis this I call that external, out-ſide Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhlp, that painted Devotion by which they amuſe the People with fantaſtical Geſtures, and confus'd Noiſes they underſtand not.</p>
               <p>Yet, we ſee with what Heat and Eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs they defend that which they know not, and which they never will, being pleas'd with an airy Good, rather than with the true ſubſtantial Religion; for, that ſeems but cold and inſipid to 'em in compariſon of the palpable myſteries of Superſtition. Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Superſtition! purſued with ſo much Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or rather Fury, by ſo many weak Men and Women, called religious, who are like thoſe who were never at Quiet till they had made a diſturbance between thoſe two holy Apoſtles <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> They make to themſelves a God of very difficult Acceſs, who is never to be ſatisfy'd, and with whom they have never done; hence proceed all thoſe raſh Vows, their Pilgrimages, their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Prayers, and eternal Repetitions. They frequent the Churches more than their Houſes, where they go only to torment their Families, which are never pleaſing to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49837:43"/>
'em, unleſs, in Imitation of 'em they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with their avaritious Abſtinencies. Under Pretence of an extraordinary Piety, they introduce themſelves into Courts, near ſome devout Perſons, and into the greateſt and richeſt Families; where ſome careſs 'em, others ſuffer 'em, but more are troubled with 'em, complain of 'em, rid themſelves of 'em, and think nothing ſo uneaſie in the World; and thoſe of the beſt Judgment, ordinarily, give 'em the worſt Character. They find they are ignorant, fooliſh, time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, diſtruſtful, and full of idle Scruples, being, for little or no Reaſon, ſometimes tranſported with Admiration, and then ſeiz'd with Horror, they are provok'd, torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, amaz'd, only at ſomething that happens beyond their Capacity of underſtanding. Any thing proves what they have a mind to believe; a few cunning Tricks, or a falſe Apparition, paſs with them for Miracles. They are perſwaded to any thing that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual or ſtrange. Counterfeit Jewels are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued by 'em as great Rarities. They often, upon the bare Credit of ſome Cheat, pay as great Reſpect to ſomething that has been brought from a neighbouring Mountain or River, as if it had come from that of <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> or thoſe of <hi>Jordan,</hi> or the more celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Holy Places of <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> I believe, by this time Mount <hi>Calvary</hi> is made plain, at leaſt, is but common Earth and Duſt, all
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49837:44"/>
the Sand and pretty Stones being carryed away, as holy Reliques, to adorn the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Chappels of numbers of devout Virgins, who would believe, they ſhould give but a bad Proof of their good Education, did they not out-do their Mothers themſelves in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
               <p>Theſe Abuſes are own'd by many, which they forbear not to condemn, and yet pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices; ſo that their Actions belye their Words. For, if they are confin'd by any Weakneſs or Infirmity, and would yet be accounted Sons of the Church; Why don't they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to it's Neceſſities, to the Relief of the Poor, and it's Paſtors? Or, if their Zeal is not made remarkable, Why don't they, at leaſt, ſo act, that their Idolatry be not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent? But, if you preſs this Argument home upon 'em, you touch 'em to the Quick, you diſcover the Poyſon within 'em, and ſo far provoke 'em, that they'll not ſuffer you to ſay more; and thus do they diſcover their Hypocriſie. 'Tis not, ſay they, a hundred Years, ſince you were not at all; you are Schiſmaticks; Why did you forſake the Church? But, beſotted as they are, they ſhould add to this, You will not worſhip what is elevated on the Altar, or believe, that God can be made of a little Morſel of Bread: You will not proſtrate your ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the likeneſs of any thing that is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in Earth? and you are ſcandaliz'd,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49837:44"/>
that the People pay ſuch a ſubmiſſive Reſpect to Images and Reliques, with Songs of Praiſe and Devotion. You preſume ſo far, as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to receive the Sacrament in both kinds, as Jeſus Chriſt has inſtituted; and will not be contented with that part only the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows you: You will underſtand the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Prayers you make to God, and all the religious Service you are obliged to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to him. In a word, you will not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Authority of the Learned, after the Example of Princes and Governours, or be enſlaved either by Tradition or Cuſtom. Certainly, they believe Religion does princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſiſt in the Succeſſion of Perſons, and not in the Doctrine of the Goſpel. I can only ſay of 'em, that they own the Truth but by bare Humane Reaſon, that they are zealous neither for one Party or other, but cloſe with that which is moſt to their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, not conſidering, that the Scripture does condemn the Luke-warm, as well as Murderers and Adulterers. I am obliged here, to confeſs my own Weakneſs in accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing theirs, and to acknowledge, that I ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times look on 'em with Pity, at others, with Anger, and then with Indifference; but, I cannot think on ſuch who have forſaken the Faith, without Horror, as being the worſt of men, the lively Images of the firſt and chief Apoſtate. Theſe men betray their very Brethren, ſell their Religion, are a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49837:45"/>
Scandal to the whole World, making it more their Buſineſs to enrich than to ſave themſelves.</p>
               <p>Give 'em the Purſe, and they'll continue with you, as <hi>Judas,</hi> who foreſaw not, as theſe, that in ſelling his Maſter he bought his own Deſpair. Having never had any real Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations to the gain of Knowledge, they have always neglected the procuring it, whilſt they have made an outward Profeſſion of the true Religion; but having alter'd their Belief, they become mighty Diſputants, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Defence of their Change. To this purpoſe, they ſerve themſelves of all the Reaſons that can be thought of, though in their Conſciences they know they have none, but the weakneſs of their Judgment, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Depravity of their Minds, or the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty they have to reconcile their Ambition and Covetouſneſs with the Diſgrace and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of Jeſus Chriſt. Then, the Promiſes and Favours of great men, have irreſiſtable Charms, with which, theſe men of merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Tempers, eaſily comply; whilſt thoſe who us'd to command, now court 'em, their very Maſters careſs and flatter 'em. In a word, the greateſt part of Mankind ſeem born to Slavery; to which, though never ſo full of Hardſhip, if bound to it by golden Chains, they ſubmit, nay, prefer it before the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty. They are ready even to adore thoſe by whom they enrich themſelves, or
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49837:45"/>
where they meet with Honour and Reſpect; and, as the Heathens, own no other Gods but their Benefactors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>AMongſt ſo many bewitch'd or crazed Perſons, the wilfully blind, and Slaves of the World, I have ſought for ſome, in whom I might confeſs to have found ſuch a Purity of Mind, and ſuch marks of their Election, that I might have joyn'd with 'em in the Communion of the Spirit, and by that Bond of Perfection, which makes 'em inſeparable from their Creator, and their Neighbour. For, what Satisfaction or Comfort could I find with the men of the Age, before whom we muſt never, it being indecent (from whence I know not) to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Religion; they either talk not at all of Divine things, or if they do, 'tis after a Humane way? What Pleaſure could I have in their Friendſhip, who heartily differed from me in that which ought to be the chief end of all our Deſires and our Hopes? I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to know the Children of Heaven from thoſe of the Earth; and the meeting one of the Faithful would have been as an Angel to me. But, amongſt ſuch Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men, I could not meet with one,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49837:46"/>
though I earneſtly labour'd after it, being without doubt, leſs diſcerning than <hi>Elijah,</hi> who ſaw not one in all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> where yet there were many.</p>
               <p>I happen'd in an Age, in which, the men of it did even already degenerate from the firſt Simplicity and late Reformation; in which, thoſe who ſtyled themſelves of the Reform'd Religion, follow'd their very ſteps who have deſtroy'd the moſt flouriſhing Churches. For, they uſed the ſame liberty in their Words and Actions, the ſame ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Vanity in their Cloaths, the ſame lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xurious way of living, which ſcandaliz'd the Emperour <hi>Julian,</hi> and confirm'd him in his Apoſtacy. <hi>Matth. 24. 12. Iniquity did ſo abound, that the love of many waxed cold.</hi> And to judge of 'em by their outward Behaviour, thoſe who were falſe Chriſtians, could not be diſtinguiſh'd from the true.</p>
               <p>I thought no where ſo proper to find thoſe I ſought for, as in the moſt lawful Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; but I could not diſcover the Church, even in the Church, that being frequented by certain Perſons, whoſe higheſt Devotion conſiſts in their Looks; who never think the Sermon too long, or their Meetings too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; who would look upon Religion as too cold, did it not in ſome Acts imitate even Superſtition. It is indeed too much fill'd with thoſe who come only for Company; 'tis their Education or Chance, that draws
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49837:46"/>
'em thither, rather than any hearty deſire of improving themſelves in the knowledge of the Truth. Hither they come, only to ſee the World, from whence, the World, in ſome ſort, ought to be baniſh'd; where they behave themſelves with ſo little Reſpect, that 'twould be Injuſtice to call 'em Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, ſince there is no manner of Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance either of their Zeal or Devotion.</p>
               <p>Their only Aim is to be ſeen in the moſt known and publick Places, inſtead of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God Thanks that he is pleas'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit 'em to be in the Company of Saints; amongſt whom, it ought to be of ſufficient Satisfaction to 'em, without pretending to other Advantages, that they have room enough only to kneel. There are ſome, who make the day of reſt a day of Labour, and perform the moſt neceſſary and juſt Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as burthenſom and uneaſie Tasks. There are others ſo deprav'd, that they hear Sermons, only to find fault with 'em, to wreſt their Senſe, or ſcoffingly, to repeat 'em to the Enemies of the Reformation. Many have loſt the very Sence of ſuch Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are plain, pure, eaſie, and full of Reaſon; Truth does not at all affect 'em, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs agreeably pronounc'd by a loud and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Tongue, unleſs beautify'd with all the Gayety and Flowers of Rhetorick. They deſpiſe what is intelligible and clear, and judge that unworthy of 'em which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49837:47"/>
People are able to underſtand. They are not to be ſatisfy'd, unleſs we undertake to criticize on ſome profound myſterious Point, ſubtilly to treat of ſome intricate Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, the reſolving of which belongs to God alone, having reſerved the Knowledge of it to himſelf. They have forgot, that he who hath choſen the weak things of this World to confound the things that are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 27. As he was meek and humble, ſo will he that our Knowledge be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate or preſumptuous; that he has put his Word in the Mouths of ſuch weak ones who cannot yet declare it ſo imperfectly, but that thoſe who have a Love for it, muſt own it, and diſtinguiſh it from the dazling appearance of Falſhood. They have forgot that the ſubtilty of Language, and cunning Arts of Speech, are uſed only to harden thoſe to whom he hath ſo frequently offer'd his Grace, which they have rejected, to maintain Error with Obſtinacy, which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with them for ſtrength of Argument, and which indeed may be called the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and Virtue of the Reprobate. The truly Faithful need no Eloquence to perſwade 'em, that is introduc'd into the Church when Faith decays; and whenever Art is us'd to move the People, 'tis an apparent Argument of their obdurate Tempers. Yet, our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers find themſelves obliged, that they may pleaſe their curious Hearers, to become more
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49837:47"/>
refin'd and lofty, to quit the Simplicity of the Apoſtles, ſometimes for the ſubtilty of Philoſophers, or at others, for the ſublime Style of Orators. Theſe things are now no more cenſur'd than the manners of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the People; and many ill Cuſtoms are ſo far eſtabliſh'd in ſeveral Churches, that there are very few who either have the Courage, or Strength to remove 'em. The holy men of this Age have trouble enough to ſtrive againſt the Age it ſelf, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, in the Perſon of the Great and Powerful, does inſenſibly procure a Reſpect to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>I have met with a Reformation only in Doctrine; and I have not doubted, but that there were ſome Believers where the Word of Truth was preached: but, 'twas as hard for me to diſcover 'em, as 'tis for the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to diſcern the Actions of the Juſt, or for the Good, the Infirmities of the Wicked. There are found but few, who are always careful to render their Works ſo conſonant to the Precepts of the Goſpel, as not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be drawn off by Promiſes and Hopes of another kind. Beſides, God calls ſome of every Sex, of each Age, and of all Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; even thoſe who perſecute him, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called; and, when he pleaſes, his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Enemies are made his faithfulleſt Friends. Nay, by I know not what ſort of Decree, whoſe Cauſes are incomprehenſible, he, in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49837:48"/>
an Inſtant, changes thoſe whoſe Lives are debauch'd and vitious, and prefers 'em even before ſuch, whoſe Manners ſeem to have been perfectly regular, and who boaſt, that they have fulfilled the Law. 'Tis certain, that the moſt virtuous fall too often, whether it be from ſome extraordinary Terror, or ſome ſudden Aſſault of <hi>Satan,</hi> or from a Tryal by God himſelf, who does ſometimes expoſe 'em to their own Weakneſs, that they may not forget themſelves, and that they impute not to their own Virtue, what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally an Effect of Divine Grace. The Gift of God has always the ſtrongeſt Influence upon 'em; for, notwithſtanding thoſe Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies they ſometimes allow themſelves in, or thoſe Errors that prevail upon 'em, it fares with 'em as with the prodigal Son, for ſooner or later, they neceſſarily return to their Father. However it is with 'em, they make not themſelves known by any affected Looks, or peculiar Faſhion in their Cloaths; they deſire to appear as other men, not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularizing themſelves by any odd fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Geſtures; their Actions are not at all hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, their Devotion ſerves not as a Snare for their Covetouſneſs, or their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility as a Mask to their Ambition. 'Tis by ſpiritual Signs they are made remarkable; if the Body does partake of theſe, they are Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets in Phyſiognomy, the knowledge of which, is reſerved to the Author of Nature
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49837:48"/>
alone. When the Holy Spirit has once made an Impreſſion on 'em, there remain certain Marks upon 'em, which make 'em ſhine in the Eyes of the Almighty, as the Stars of the Night, which yet have no Light but what the Sun lends 'em. He alone, who has made the Hearts of men, and can change 'em, does know 'em, and make 'em known to whom he pleaſes; but, there are many appear Believers to us, who are not ſo, being capable only of a temporary Faith. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, if we may paſs our Judgments on Men, I believe that their Converſation does ſufficiently diſcover their Affections: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve alſo, that thoſe who truly love God, do infinitely rejoyce in the Contemplation of his Works, but more eſpecially, in the Meditation of his Word. They conſtantly read it, not out of bare Curioſity, or to find Fault with it, not from a vain deſire after Knowledge, or mercenarily to inſtruct others in it, but to inform themſelves of the Truth, to ſeek after Comfort, to ſtrengthen their Faith, and to confirm their Hopes. They have it always, either in their Mouths or Thoughts; and the greateſt Trouble they have, is, that they cannot effectually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it to thoſe who deſpiſe it, who look on it as a Snare to entrap 'em; who fear it as the ſinging of <hi>Syrens;</hi> for, their profligate Tempers render 'em incompatible with it's Purity. The Spirit of Diſcretion is an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49837:49"/>
ſo rarely met with, that only the true Elect know how to chooſe, and the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpiritual how to try all things, and keep to that which is good. 1 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 5. 21. They are not concern'd to ſee ſo many falſe Prophets inſolently take upon 'em the Name of God, and vainly boaſt to be the Diſpenſers of his Word, which they uſe only to their own baſe Ends, and which they expound, as the Devil did, when he preſum'd to tempt the Son of God himſelf, and, as he daily does, thoſe who follow him.</p>
               <p>Moreover, they intermeddle not in the Buſineſs or Intrigues of this World, but their contempt of 'em makes themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſable; upon this account, they appear mean and deſpicable, they are hated, perſecuted, as if their manner of Living, as well as their Belief, did accuſe that of others. They don't willingly ſide with any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, unleſs the Service of God, or the Good of their Country engages 'em to it. And if they aim at any publick Employment; they will not under-hand make their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for it; much leſs, raiſe their Eſtates to the Prejudice of the Faith or Charity. The common Talk amongſt men of getting Riches, of making their Fortunes, of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fine Houſes, is not their ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: we may with Reaſon ſay, their Ambition is much higher than that of others, ſince no worldly Greatneſs can confine
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49837:49"/>
it. They know very well the right Uſe of things, what Advantages men poſſeſs'd of Honours and great Offices, may with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and neceſſarily claim; but thoſe are ignorant for whom they take pains, who are alwayes heaping up Riches, projecting mighty Deſigns, and erecting ſuch vaſt, prodigious Buildings, that their whole Life is not long enough to finiſh 'em. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no one ought to be called either Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious or Reaſonable, but he who in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt labours after the attainment of his ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Good and Happineſs; and 'tis with pity they look on thoſe who buſie themſelves ſo perpetually about the things of the Earth, as if they pretended not in the leaſt to any part in Heaven. 'Tis with trembling and ſorrow they obſerve the confidence of thoſe who ſtick at nothing whereby they may gratifie their Appetite and Senſes; to whom the ſteps of Goodneſs ſeem but as Degrees to Evil; and who become Great and Powerful, but that they may commit all ſorts of Crimes unpuniſh'd, and tyrannize òver their Fellow Creatures. They abſent themſelves, as much as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, from the Converſation of bad men; and becauſe they are leſs given to Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, they are look'd on as leſs agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. 'Tis painful to them to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant to thoſe that are diſpleaſing to them, nor can they approve of Error and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49837:50"/>
Vanity; they cannot admire what God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns, or ſhew any Signs of Joy in their Faces, for that which their Hearts are ſad.</p>
               <p>Whatever Trouble or Diſſatisfaction they may meet with in this uneaſie Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whatever Hatred, or Averſion they have for all theſe things, their Severity is yet leſs than their Charity. They don't, under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of renouncing the World, ſpend all they have, nor do they advance their own Fortunes by the Ruine of any one. They know they ſhould be worſe than Infidels, did they not take Care of their Families, and that 'tis God's Command, That thoſe who work not, ought not to eat, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 10. Therefore, as the day of Reſt is kept Holy by 'em, ſo thoſe of working are employ'd in honeſt Labour. But they are ſo far from believing that they have no other end in this World, but the doing their own Buſineſs in it, that they frequently cry out with their Maſter, <hi>Here I am, O God, to do thy Will.</hi> And, though they live, or rather languiſh, (as out of their Element) being alone amidſt the Multitude, and Strangers even amongſt their Brethren; although their Integrity and purity of Life, is look'd on as Folly, and their Strength as Weakneſs, yet they are not concern'd, that they ſuffer for doing well, and value not their Reputation, if they can but preſerve their Conſcience. They know
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49837:50"/>
very well, that if they pleas'd Men, they ſhould not be true Servants of God; that 'tis impoſſible to believe in him, and yet paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately to purſue the Glory of this World, which certainly becomes bitter to 'em, when they begin to have a juſt Sence of the Sweetneſs of Jeſus Chriſt. They are ſatisfy'd that this Life is but a Paſſage, a place of Tryal, or rather, a Field of Combat, where thoſe that fight not, muſt not expect either Honour or Reward.</p>
               <p>'Tis extreamly difficult, on this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to reconcile the Knowledge of ſo many great Doctors, with their Obdurateneſs; I cann't imagine how they can think of the Goſpel, and yet reflect not on their own Conſciences. I am amaz'd, that ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations as they have, don't oblige 'em to own, and to ſay, <q>We are out of the way certainly, and the Profeſſion we make is abſolutely contrary to that of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt and his Diſciples. 'Tis ſaid, That ſuch who will live righteouſly ſhall ſuffer Perſecution; How then do we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer? The Princes and People are of our ſide, we enjoy the Pleaſures and Delights of the Earth, our Lot is always on a fair Ground. And if this makes not the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of this World, what is it that can do it? Shall we reckon the Vows of Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Faſtings and the Rigors ſome of our Party ſuffer? But, they are ſo far
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49837:51"/>
from being blam'd, hated, or perſecuted for theſe things, that they are rather ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd and receive Rewards for 'em. Beſides, theſe voluntary Afflictions are of Humane Invention, and of the nature of thoſe, concerning which, the Scripture ſays, <hi>Who hath requir'd this at your Hands?</hi>
                  </q> I wonder, that the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of the Age have no Conſideration of theſe things; ſince Sufferings are ſo nearly link'd to the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity, that I know not whether we can ſay, that thoſe who have not been under ſome Perſecution have yet commenc'd Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. For, if in any Province or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the Bleſſing of Heaven, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, favourably countenances the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Zeal of ſome one Age, ſuffers Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to flouriſh, and poſſeſs the Gate of it's Enemies, <hi>Gen.</hi> chap. 22. verſ. 17. and chap. 24. verſ. 60. in a little time, Error and Inſolence, the common Attendants of Proſperity, the Practiſes of <hi>Satan</hi> and his Emiſſaries, change and corrupt it, make it emulate the Religions of the World, and deſpiſe it's own original Simplicity. Shall the Servants be greater than their Maſter, ſhall they have the benefit of the Joys he has procur'd for 'em, and partake of his Glory, without bearing a part in his Torments and Patience? No, No, 'tis ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that they find their Pleaſures amidſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49837:51"/>
Grief and Sorrows, as the Roſe amongſt the Thorns; and that it fares with them as with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who became greater by his Baniſhment; and as with <hi>Job,</hi> who grew young by his Calamities. They ought to eſteem it a ſingular Favour, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did, that is given them not only to believe in Chriſt, but to ſuffer for his ſake. <hi>Philip. chap. 1. verſ.</hi> 29. and to think that they ſuffer very little, in compariſon of that Reward they hope for. Hope and Charity are the inſeparable Companions of Faith, all three together made a true Believer, and theſe three are infallible Marks of one. I don't mean that Faith which is obſcure, blind, weak, and wavering; that is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Birth, Opinion, Cuſtom, and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that is always doubting, and is eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcandaliz'd, that does not mortifie the Affections, that makes us not forſake the World, or our Selves, and which faints under Perſecutions. I don't mean that Faith which follows Jeſus Chriſt for Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and only Advantage, and of all his Miracles, conſiders that chiefly which mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied the Bread. But, I ſpeak of that which is manifeſt, certain, and conſtant, that proceeds from the Power of the Holy Ghoſt, from the Words of Eternal Life, from Prayer and Humility, which is not acquired but revealed, that enters not into the Heart of thoſe who believe after a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49837:52"/>
humane way. I ſpeak of that Faith which removes from us the Cares of this Life; that raviſhes us with the Admiration of Divine Graces; that infinitely ſurpaſſes the Diſcourſe of Men; that obliges us to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him who has beſtowed it on us, with Sighs and Groans that cannot be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49837:52"/>
            <head>A TREATISE Concerning the <hi>E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CHARIST.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF Religion was only grounded upon the Opinion of men; if they might ſerve God according to their own Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not his Commands; every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion would be a good one, and our Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions alone would be ſufficient to recommend each different Invention to us. The World, which for the moſt part is affected with things preſent, would be pleas'd with ſuch variety of Worſhip; one part of it would not be accus'd of Hereſie, or any other look'd on as guilty of Superſtition. But 'tis not enough to own a God, or pay any ſort of Homage to him, the great bus'neſs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is, to ſave men from that Eternal Death which they have merited; but their Minds are ſo clouded with darkneſs, and ſo involv'd in Sin, that they cannot find either a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt it, or the way to Salvation, or
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49837:53"/>
the Paths that lead to Supreme Happineſs. What likelihood is there, that the Children of Rebellion, who are under the Curſe and Anger of God, ſhould have yet ſtrength enough to recover their Fall, or ſufficient Light to direct 'em out of that profound and dark Abyſs into which they caſt themſelves. If they cannot comprehend Divine Truth, and that this Faith muſt be derived from ſome other Spirit than their own, why ſhould they pretend to the making of Laws, and ſo abſolutely to determine of Univerſal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. They ought to receive Inſtructions from an Underſtanding much more perfect than their own; for indeed they are ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to preſcribe or command on this occaſion, that they are utterly diſabled even to obey. I cannot imagine how men can be ſo preſumptuous, and yet ſo weak and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. They are ſure become inſenſible of their Infirmities, they are ignorant of their want of Knowledge, and flatter themſelves that their Light is ſo very clear, that their Blindneſs cannot be diſcover'd. The ſame Inſolence that at firſt deſtroy'd 'em, does continue to do ſo even to the end; they have violated the moſt holy things, and, if we may ſo ſay, have laid their hands on the Ark, againſt the ſtricteſt Prohibitions. Is there any thing more Sacred in Religion, than the Sacrament of the Euchariſt? And ought not that to be for ever preſerv'd inviolable, ſince
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:49837:53"/>
inſtituted by him who was Wiſdom it ſelf? Yet what part of it is not alter'd, corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or brought to nothing at all by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church? What remains then, in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of what is now called the Maſs, of that which was heretofore called the Supper of the Lord? 'Tis a memorial our Saviour was pleas'd to leave of himſelf, to excite men, not only by Words, but by viſible Signs, to a remembrance of that which they never ought to forget. What Signs were ſo eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible? To what Elements could he have better compared himſelf, than to thoſe which are moſt neceſſary to the preſervation of our Lives? He who is that Bread which came from Heaven, for our Spiritual food, and that we might eternally live with him? What was more proper for him to do, than to take Bread, break it, and give it us, ſince his Body was to be broke for our Sins, and He to be deliver'd up to Death, that he might procure Life for us? What could He more ſignificantly ſay, than <hi>Take and Eat,</hi> ſince we cannot live unleſs joyn'd with him, as the Subſtance of the Bread which we eat every day is incorporated with our bodies, ſo that it becomes the ſame with us, and of two Subſtances but one. The ſame conſiderations that invite us to Eat, will to Drink alſo, unleſs one could do the Office of the other, as 'tis done in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49837:54"/>
Cup, being a ſign of the ſeparation of the Blood from the Body, is inſeparable from the Sacrament, even becauſe the Blood was ſeparated from the Body; for, in the double Action, the breaking of the Body, and the effuſion of the Blood, ought to be equally repreſented. It is not enough then at this Feaſt to <hi>eat,</hi> we muſt <hi>drink</hi> alſo, as 'tis cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary at all others in the World; for he who invites us to it, does command us to do ſo, being pleaſed to ſuit himſelf to our Methods of living, and who would have us bear a part in his Sorrows, only that we may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of his Joyes; He being the Beginning and the End of all things, the true Source of thoſe living Waters, whoſe Streams ſo refreſh the Trees of Paradiſe, that by thoſe they grow, flouriſh, and become eternally fruitful. I have not here undertaken to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine each particular part of the Maſs, or to compare it with this firſt Inſtitution, or to ſearch after any conformity to it, where in truth there is none: The Inſtitutions of men are here ſo intermix'd with thoſe of God, or indeed, have rather ſo quite alter'd 'em, that we can diſcover nothing but the pomp and ſtatelineſs of the myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: I will venture only to urge ſome things on the very words of our Saviour, which are the innocent Original of thoſe Controverſies, Seditions, Maſſacres, and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that happen amongſt Chriſtians, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49837:54"/>
which make the reaſon of our Communion become that of our Diſſention. 'Tis extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly difficult to add any thing to the thoughts of ſo many admirable Perſons, who have ſaid all that can be on this Subject, and who ſeem to have forgot nothing but Brevity; but I, having no other End, than the endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make my ſelf underſtood by the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid and wilfully deaf, 'twould be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſerve my ſelf of others Reaſons, if ſo be I can make my own perſwaſive.</p>
            <p>'Tis a manner of ſpeaking uſual amongſt all Nations, the ſtyle of all Languages, to give to a thouſand things the name of what they only put us in mind of, and to which they bear ſome reſemblance: This alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends even to Perſons: as we ſay, This is the King, when there is only his Seal or Picture; and, not abſurdly, we often name God, when there is only his ſhadow, or Image. This is a Figure ſo very common, that 'tis frequently made uſe of, even by thoſe that underſtand not one Figure in Rhetorick. This manner of Speech ſeems to be particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly made uſe of in Sacraments, not only as a great Propriety, but that 'tis inevitably neceſſary. Yet the Superſtitious, or rather thoſe whoſe Intereſt it is, have made it their buſineſs to take it literally; and 'tis inſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to hear 'em impertinently repeating, He hath ſaid it, He hath ſaid it. 'Tis true, that He hath ſaid, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49837:55"/>
adds to it, <hi>which is broken for you;</hi> and ſhews the neceſſary relation between the breaking of the one and the other: For, he took Bread, not to eat it himſelf alone, but to give it thoſe who were with him; He gave it not as a Sign of his Glorious Body, but as that of his Body which was to be broken for us. From hence 'tis apparent, that the Breaking and the Communion are ſo firmly joyned to this Action, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them 'tis not indeed a Sacrament. Let thoſe, who ſo frequently urge, that He hath ſaid it, teach us, after what manner He gave his Body to his Diſciples, during his Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, before his Reſurrection and Glory; as alſo before his Paſſion and Death. Is it not in breaking Bread for 'em himſelf (who was in ſome ſort broken before he ſuffer'd) and that by his own hands, and not by thoſe of his Enemies, ſince the Sacrament preceded the Sacrifice? Is it not according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of all Sacraments, that he ſpake of it, in giving it a Name expreſſive of the Effect, and in ſaying, that 'tis not only what he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, but that which he offers to thoſe who deſire to receive it? Who perceives not, that our Corporal eating does aſſiſt at the ſame time, and is a means to excite our <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls to a <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piritual one, which is abſolutely dependent on Faith? 'Tis certain, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have been afraid, after the Bleſſing, to give the Bread the name of Bread, leſt it
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49837:55"/>
ſhould be taken for ordinary Bread. But, St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it Bread four times at leaſt, for fear, that as by the <hi>Capernaites,</hi> or <hi>Romans,</hi> it ſhould be taken for Fleſh: he ſaid alſo, the Cup is the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt, for fear it ſhould be believ'd the Blood it ſelf. We cannot, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, approach theſe Sacred Signs with too great Reverence, ſince by their means, the things they ſignifie are convey'd to us, or at leaſt, ſo offer'd, that 'tis but deſiring 'em, and we may receive 'em. Faith ſerves as a Mouth to us, and our Souls, in ſome ſort, eat and drink the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, as our Bodies eat and drink the Bread and Wine which repreſent 'em. Thus the Fathers, to ſtir up a Peoples Devotion, and engage 'em to the profound Reſpect of Holy Things, uſed certain ways of ſpeaking, which were not to have been believed, had they not been figurative. Their mighty Zeal, which perſwaded 'em they could never ſay too much, left 'em no room to imagine that their Metaphors, Metonymies and Hyperboles, would one day paſs for Articles of Faith. They could never have thought, that from the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of their Rhetorick, would have grown ſuch a monſtrous Doctrine, or, that from the Weakneſs or Malice of men their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and devout Meditations would have been turn'd into Chimerical Notions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49837:56"/>
But, having endeavour'd to improve each others Expreſſions, they have unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily contributed, without thinking of it, to a Myſtery they as yet knew not, and have by their Arguments, helped to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en it's Abuſe. Their Evidence is every day cited to this purpoſe, the Tranſports of their Thoughts, and their extraordinary heights of Speech, are urged as undoubted Teſtimonies of the ſimple Truth. Though the ſame Writings of theſe Fathers are ſo expounded, that we may ſay of them as of the Holy Scriptures, That thoſe things which are clear and manifeſt remove the Scruples raiſed by ſuch which are difficult and obſcure; yet the great Doctors of the Age, whatever Reaſons have been ſhewn 'em to the contrary, forbear not to impoſe on the Credulity of the People; who, as the higheſt Peice of Devotion, daily worſhip a bit of Bread, and in this are ſo far prevail'd with by Cuſtom, that they are even ready to maſſacre thoſe who will not believe it. Add to the Errors of Speech, the long Converſation the Primitive Chriſtians held with the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, of whom they have not only borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Temples, Altars, and Images, but alſo, Habits, Geſtures, Numbers and Myſteries; you'll find, that after their Example, they have omitted nothing that may render their Religion pompous, and ſuitable to the Grandeur of the World, that they could
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49837:56"/>
not ſtoop to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, preferring rather the Appearance of things, than the real Truth.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who have read but a very little, muſt confeſs, that they ſcarce ſee any thing in their Churches, which they have not bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the ſuperſtitious <hi>Gentiles:</hi> And, not to ſpeak of any thing but what relates to our Subject of Diſcourſe, they worſhipp'd no Images but what muſt be conſecrated; being perſwaded, the Deities they repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed were fixed to 'em, by the power of their magical Operations. Thoſe Chriſtians who have not been ſatisfy'd with the Terms of Bleſſing, and giving of Thanks, have been ſo pleas'd with that of Conſecration, that in time they believed a Virtue and Efficacy in it? hence proceeded the Obſervation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny myſterious Ceremonies, an Affectation of certain Words often repeated, beſides a Preſumption of adding others to thoſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt's, that they might not be wanting either in their Numbers or Virtue. Hence aroſe the Name of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſo ill underſtood, and ſo ill made uſe of, that without the Explication they give of it, 'twould not be, in the leaſt, ſignificative of what they deſign it. This is a Doctrine, which as much as 'tis poſſible, deſtroys the Humanity of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and which frames to it ſelf a God in which, no reaſonable Creature can believe. This is the Source from whence flow ſuch
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49837:57"/>
Streams of Contradictions, and unallowable Conſequences, that they both ſcandalize and diſcourage the greateſt part of Men, they obſtruct the Converſion of the Infidel, and confirm the Atheiſt in his Unbelief. 'Tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a horrible Abuſe of thoſe Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> to place a Power in 'em, in theſe lattertimes, of chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bread of the Euchariſt into the incorruptible Body of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to be receiv'd in by our corruptible ones, without any Need, or our finding any extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Effect or Advantage by it. The Text is much more expreſs, that ſays, <hi>The Word was made Fleſh;</hi> yet no one believes, that by <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the Divine Nature was changed into the Humane: So from the Sacramental way of ſpeaking, that ſays, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> no one ought to infer, that the Subſtance of the Bread is converted into the Subſtance of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt. What Virtue, what efficacious Uſe has not been allowed to Baptiſm, both by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and the Fathers? By it, we put on Jeſus Chriſt, and partake not only of his Death and Burial, but his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo. By it, we are in an Inſtant made new Creatures; we paſs from Sin to Juſtification, and aſcend from Earth to Heaven. However Holy and Celeſtial the Euchariſt is, what more abundant Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can it beſtow on us, than the Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49837:57"/>
of theſe ſame Priviledges, the Operations of the ſame Spirit, the firſt Fruits of the ſame Transfiguration and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Yet, for this only, the Learned of the Times have ſought out many Inventions that exceed the Capacity of Men, and ſubvert all Orders, and the very Principles of the True Doctrine. From their hollow brain is produced an idle vain thing, that is void of all Subſtance, a real Apparition, which preſents it ſelf only to the Eyes, but deceives all the other Sences, that offers Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to our Minds, and impoſes on our Underſtanding and. Reaſon. A Body that has neither Extent or Quantity; an indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Point that comprehends the whole; Blood that contains the Body in which it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; at the ſame time ſolid, and yet to be drank. What is really Corporeal, they annihilate, and make a Body of that which is truly ſpiritual. They utterly ſpoil the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament by taking the Subſtance from it; they deſtroy the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, by robbing him of all the Proprieties of a Body, only attributing to him thoſe of a Spirit. 'Tis not then to receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, unleſs we have what it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits, <hi>viz.</hi> A ſubſtantial Sign: To be denyed, that is, to be deprived of what is ſignify'd; ſince in this Sacramental Communion, the one goes not without the other. But, either let 'em tell us
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49837:58"/>
what is it's Subſtance, what it's Elements, what it's Figure, what it's Relation, or let 'em confeſs that 'tis not neceſſary to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him in Figure, who is preſent in Perſon, or corporally to receive in the Hoſt, the Sign and the thing ſignify'd together. In effect, 'tis incoherent to be ſacramentally preſent, and yet really ſo: The Sign is not what it ſignifies, or the Picture what it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents; the Union of theſe things is made by Relation, not Subſtance.</p>
            <p>The matter in Queſtion is concerning a Spiritual Nouriſhment, repreſented to us by a Corporeal one, without which, the other cannot be: For, what Relation is there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Sacrament made up of Accidents, an appearance only of Bread, and the real Body of Jeſus Chriſt, broken, by which, we are nouriſh'd to Life eternal? What ſubſiſts not, cannot be the Repreſentation of a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and to repreſent a Body by what has no Body, is to repreſent a Being by no Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Every thing by Nothing, and if I may ſo ſay, the Truth by Falſhood. Hereupon, they make Expoſitions ſo very obſcure, and Diſtinctions ſo intricate and confus'd, that they cannot poſſibly make others underſtand that of which they themſelves are ignorant; and you cannot diſturb 'em more, than to put 'em on making plain even their own Explications. It has always been believ'd, That the Mind did better apprehend things,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49837:58"/>
than they could be expreſs'd by any Words: but theſe men imagine they expreſs what our Thoughts cannot conceive: And when they have ſaid all they can, they have Recourſe to the Omnipotence of God, without taking the leaſt notice of his Will. If we are to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve 'em in this, God is not Omnipotent, unleſs he can deſtroy thoſe very Laws which he made to be eternally inviolable; unleſs he can contradict himſelf, and belye the Truth. He is not omnipotent, unleſs he can make a Humane Body to take up no place at all; or at leaſt, that the Whole be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under a Point or Atome. He is not Omnipotent, unleſs he can make the Colour and Taſte of Bread to ſubſiſt without the Bread it ſelf; that is to ſay, That <hi>Accidents</hi> are not <hi>Accidents,</hi> which, they pretend, is every day done by him, in favour of theſe Gentlemen, by a Miracle, which no one can evidence, having never perceived any thing of it; or rather, by a Myſtery that ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes all ſorts of Miracles, kept hid and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered only to be a Refuge for Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Ignorance. Who can patiently hear theſe Doctors, and not ſlight 'em? It is not enough that God is incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they do all they can to make him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believed. They ſhelter themſelves under a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, falſly ſo called, that conſiſts in critical Queſtions and difficult Anſwers, made inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant by their own Subtlety, that affect
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49837:59"/>
the Ears with Sound and Noiſe, but not at all the Underſtanding. They own a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they emphatically pronounce; and which, to ſpeak properly, ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, unleſs taken in the ſence of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Churches, who believe, that our Communion cannot be but Spiritual ſo long as it is Sacramental. By ſuch like extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant and vain Expreſſions, they take off all the Difficulties can be urged to 'em, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain their Hearers with airy and idle Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, by which, they take Pleaſure to deceive themſelves. They ſay, there muſt be a Sacrifice in the Church, againſt that place of Scripture, <hi>There is no more Offering for Sin, after that which has been once made for all. Heb. 10. v.</hi> 10. 18. They will have their pretended propitiatory Sacrifice, and that of the Croſs, to be but the ſame thing. Beſides, they will have the Bread of the Euchariſt changed into the Glorious Body of Jeſus Chriſt; and I know not how they allow to the ſame Subject, Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Glory: we muſt receive him whole, in remembrance that he was broke; and living in Memory of his Death; and tho' at their deſire, he comes every day to 'em, both in his Humane and Divine Nature, yet we muſt not forbear doing theſe things till he come. This is called Conſecration, that is, taking away the Subſtance of the Bread, and only reſerving it's Accidents, therewith to cover the Body of Jeſus Chriſt. This is called ſacrificing him, in
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49837:59"/>
Remembrance of himſelf, for the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Living and the Dead. This is called eating him corporeally, altho' the Fleſh profits not at all. And altho all theſe things are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by contradicting themſelves, yet that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be dry'd ſource of Miracles, <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> reconciles 'em all, in defence of a Temporal right that uſurps the Name of Spiritual. However it is, the <hi>Sacrament</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be referr'd but to the time of the Sacrifice; and 'tis not to celebrate the memory of that, by ſuppoſing any other Body than that which was broken. 'Tis not that Blood which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd in the Veins of the Body we are to drink, but that which was ſhed, which, though worthy of having been receiv'd in the Veſſels of Election, yet fell on the Earth, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, cannot be drank, but ſpiritually. The Sign cannot contain more than the thing it ſignifies; and we take it really, tho' after the manner that the Spirit and Faith make things real. If it be true, that the Bread contains the Body whole and entire, what does the Wine add to it? What ſignifies the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of two Signs? 'Twas in vain the Lord commanded they ſhould be taken ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, if one contains the other by a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence of this Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Twou'd be no great matter if it only produc'd ſuperfluous things, if it did not ſuch monſtrouſly ſtrange ones, that we dare ſcarce mention 'em, being ſo
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49837:60"/>
very offenſive to thoſe who maintain 'em, that they have not the Courage to hear 'em. To what end had the Son of God, ſupping with his Apoſtles, eat his own Fleſh and drank his own Blood? Was his Body glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before glorified, or elſe, Had he two Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies at the ſame time, the one paſſible, and the other impaſſible? What neceſſity in theſe latter days, more than in former, oblig'd him to exhibit himſelf as Corporeal Food, to be expos'd, as we may urge to theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, to be eaten by the moſt abject Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Earth? But, let us paſs by in ſilence theſe many Inconveniences which they themſelves infer from this ſo ill-grounded Doctrine; and to palliate 'em are oblig'd to have Recourſe to Rules, and Canons, which were they not Superſtitious, we would call Ridiculous. Let us only add, that if the Body of Jeſus Chriſt be inclos'd in the Sacrament, we may eat it without believing in him: Thus Infidels obtain more than they require.</p>
            <p>They eat of Celeſtial Food they have not asked for; nay, their very Contempt of it does not hinder 'em from it, ſince they cannot receive the Sacrament without eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: but they are ſo far from eating it, that Believers themſelves do it not as 'tis underſtood by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> They receive not with the Sacrament, the Divine Eſſence, but the Virtue and Eſſicacy of the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49837:60"/>
Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt: and, ſince the Wicked cannot partake of his Graces, it follows, that thoſe Graces are not joyn'd to it by Conſecration. 'Tis not the Words pronounc'd, but believed, that make Jeſus Chriſt communicated in the Sacrament. 'Twould be ſtrange, if he muſt be unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily eaten by his very Enemies, and that he who is Holineſs it ſelf ſhould every day enter into their defiled bodies, only to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 'em more guilty, and that he might have more Reaſon to condemn and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh 'em. On the contrary, 'tis the Devil that would enter into 'em, as he did <hi>Judas,</hi> when our Lord gave him the <hi>Sop.</hi> How is it poſſible, theſe two Gueſts ſo irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, can agree together? It is not credible, that being fill'd with the moſt ſovereign Good, we ſhould only have a ſenſe of Evil from it; we receive our Saviour, that we may be ſaved, the Wicked take only the conſecrated Signs; and becauſe ſuch, they commit Sacriledge, and render themſelves guilty of Treaſon againſt the Divine Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, becauſe they have no regard to the Inſtitution of <hi>Our Lord,</hi> contemn his Offers in it, and deny it's Vertue.</p>
            <p>They publickly take his Enemies part, they again ſpit in his Face, they crown him with Thorns, they ſtrike and crucifie him: 'Tis thus they eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup unworthily; 'tis thus they eat
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49837:61"/>
their own Condemnation, not diſcerning the Body of Jeſus Chriſt. For, the Symboles, Seals, and Pledges of his Love, are account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, by thoſe who believe in him, it being Faith alone, which makes the Signs inſeparable from the thing ſignified. 'Tis heavenly Food, given to no one for his Condemnation, but only for his Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for Life, and not for Death; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the Accidents of Bread, or in the Bread it ſelf, but in the Heart of thoſe who receive it. Thus the Bread ceaſes not to be Bread, but to be common Bread; it loſes not it's Subſtance, but acquires Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which changes not it's Nature, but adds Grace to Nature, for the ſake of thoſe that believe. The Myſtery of the Incarnation unites us to the Body of our Saviour; Faith, with which he inſpires us by his Word, unites us to his Spirit, which double Union is confirm'd to us by the Communion of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. But, as our Union with Jeſus Chriſt, cannot be perfect in this World, by reaſon of our Sins, and Death, which is a Conſequence of 'em; ſo, though we take the Symboles he gives us corporally, yet 'tis nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſſible, or neceſſary for us to take what they ſignifie, but ſpiritually: For, if we take his Body, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> imagines it does, our Infirmities could not bear his Glory, the ſtronger would overcome the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, we ſhou'd doubtleſs periſh, or his Vertue
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49837:61"/>
would even then blot out all our ſins, we ſhould in an inſtant be transform'd, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come incorruptible and glorious, we ſhould be aſſured never to ſee Death. But we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not of one of all theſe but by the comfort the Spirit gives us, but by Faith, by which we rely on his Promiſes, and but by that Hope we have of a Life to come. Thus to eat the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is to hear his Word, is to believe in him; to behold him on the Croſs, loaded with our Sins; to be truly ſenſible of his Wounds and Sorrows, and to confeſs, that by the Satisfaction of the Son, whoſe Merit is infinite, we ſatisfie the Father whom we have infinitely offended. 'Tis to be inflam'd with the love of him who has ſo very much loved us; and to aſſure him, (as we do all thoſe we love) that he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in our Thoughts, that he fully poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes our Hearts; that he is the Soul of our Souls; and, to uſe his own terms, that <hi>He dwells in us, and we in him.</hi> In fine, To eat the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, is to have a freſh and lively ſenſe of thoſe Favours he has beſtow'd on us, and to think that we are not only his Servants and Friends, but his Brethren, his own blood, bone of his bones, fleſh of his fleſh, and that we are part of that Church whom he has honour'd ſo far as to make his Eternal Spouſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:49837:62"/>
Behold what is the Meat, and the Drink which are not given to all ſorts of Perſons, which ſatisfie, and quench the Thirſt of thoſe only, who hunger and thirſt after Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But the Men of this World have not truly reliſh'd the Simplicity of this Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they would heighten the Luſtre of this double Sacrament, and do all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Example, or rather, in Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Superſtitions of the World. The Name of Religion, of a Church, and even of God himſelf, who ſerv'd 'em but as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to make themſelves more honourable, to procure with more Eaſe, earthly Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages and Preferments. Beſides this, I have often thought what lawful and neceſſary uſe they could make of this <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> 'tis what they themſelves could ſcarce tell, if ſo be they would conſider the common cauſe of Salvation, as well that of the <hi>Jews</hi> as of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Theſe prodigious Errors are the true Cauſes of all that Miſchief which happens in the World; and Mankind will be ſo long infeſted with Judgments, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition continues to corrupt Religion. But the Divine Oracles give us Reaſon to hope, that the days of Sorrow will be ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd, and that God will confound the Wicked by the Breath of his Mouth. The Time will come, that Children ſhall abhor, and deteſt the Belief of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49837:62"/>
and will ſay, <q>Is it poſſible that our Predeceſſors have been ſo ſilly and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, or ſo extreamly harden'd by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, or ſo very careleſs in ſearch of the Truth, to have believ'd things altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incredible!</q> What Spirit of Pride, what high Preſumption, has poſſeſs'd theſe Councils, who have imagin'd, they could appoint better Orders for Divine Service, than the Providence of God himſelf had done, by the Mouth of his own <hi>Son?</hi> I will then conclude with the Wiſe Man, or at leaſt, with his Tranſlator, who makes him ſpeak after this manner; <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes</hi> chap. 3. verſ. 18. <hi>I ſaid in my Heart, concerning the Eſtate of the Sons of Men, that God might manifeſt them, and that they might ſee, that they themſelves are Beaſts.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:49837:63"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE In which the Author gives his Reaſons why he Prefers the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before the <hi>Roman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU have been ſo kind, Generous <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtander,</hi> not only to ſuffer, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to give you a ſhort Account of the Reaſons that invite me to ſeparate from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to cloſe with that of the Reform'd. 'Tis with all my heart I deſire to obey you, yet not without an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion that my Obedience may not ſuit with that Reſpect I owe you. I fear my Belief may in ſome ſort appear injurious to yours, and that when I confeſs, with the greateſt ſincerity imaginable, my neareſt Thoughts to you, they may be ſo diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as not to be ſuffer'd by you. You ſhall have no reaſon to accuſe me of wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Senſe of the Scripture, or interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it according to my own Fancy; for I will not quote many Paſſages out of it. You ſhall have no reaſon to miſtruſt my Arguments, as being nice or ſubtil, not deſigning to meddle with any Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, for I'll leave that to the Schools and Books, believing nothing can be ſaid more
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49837:63"/>
concerning it. I will ſerve my ſelf of no Rhetorical Colours or Artificial Eloquence, intending to make my Diſcourſe as plain and ingenious as my Thoughts are; I will entertain you only with thoſe things your Eyes ſee, and your Ears hear every day, but Cuſtom hinders you from having a due conſideration of 'em.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I muſt needs ſay, that nothing is ſo amazing to me, as to obſerve the Name of God every day in the mouthes of thoſe who know him not, nor indeed will they at all make it their buſineſs to do it. They diſcourſe of him according to their own Imaginations, and inveſt him with Qualities barely Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and ſo become guilty of the ſame fault with Pagans and Idolaters, who made to themſelves Gods according to the vain Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of their own Thoughts. Some take their Religion by chance, and ſtand up in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence only of what was firſt imprinted on 'em: Others, ſuſceptible of all ſorts of Opinions, follow that only which is the moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for 'em. Whoſoever, to this purpoſe, will act only as his Natural Reaſon dictates to him, or believe but what Men like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf perſwade him to, will be capable of purſuing all Religions, one after the other, and by conſequence will really have none at all. If men were to receive no inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions but only from Men, they would find it extremely difficult to make a true
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49837:64"/>
choice of what might yield ſolid Quiet, and Eaſe to their Minds. Each Sect has its Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Logicians, who all believe their own reaſonings grounded on Reaſon it ſelf. They neither want Natural or Artificial Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, which they pervert, and ſo raiſe from it numbers of odd <hi>Chimaera's,</hi> called by them un-erring, invincible Arguments, which ſwell 'em with Pride and Vanity, and make 'em love rather to appear reaſonable, than really to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Truth, in their mouths, ſeems to put on all manner of ſhapes, or to ſpeak more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, Bare Probability paſſes with them for Truth; and in this multitude of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, he who does not cloſely adhere to ſome Principles, knows not which to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace. Every one is not able to diſcern falſe Teachers by their Doctrine. For it being now both ſubtile and obſcure too, we may call it a Learned Ignorance, that raiſes more Difficulties than it can reſolve, and does rather multiply Doubts than clear 'em. But however, ſince the great Point in Queſtion is the Service of God, to live well, and to attain to Salvation; it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that thoſe who furniſh us with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, give us Examples too. 'Tis neceſſary that ſuch who are our Guides, lead the way. 'Tis thus they may procure the name of true Paſtors; and 'tis the moſt certain means, by which we are taught by Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49837:64"/>
himſelf to diſtinguiſh and know 'em. 'Tis true, that if Men were to be judged only by their Works, there would be found but very few who were not extremely guilty. But without doubt Religion is much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, ſince thoſe of the Church are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come worſe than Lay-men, ſince their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and debauch'd lives render 'em in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable to honeſt men, make 'em abus'd by their own People, and deſerve to be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all the World.</p>
            <p>I have not much wonder'd at the different Opinions of Pagans, and their Philoſophy; but I muſt confeſs, the Diviſion amongſt <hi>Jews, Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Turks,,</hi> has ſeem'd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange to me, who ought all to be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who had nothing more to wiſh for, when once they had learn'd there was a Divine Word. Above all, I could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, without horror and pity, ſo many different Parties amongſt Chriſtians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and amongſt thoſe, I am oblig'd to ſay, I found that the <hi>Worſt,</hi> which would peremptorily force us to believe, is the <hi>Beſt.</hi> 'Tis that Party which ſeems to have made a collection of all the Errors in the World, and from hence only has merited the name of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi> 'Tis that which is rich only by borrowing, not being able to bear with the pure ſimplicity, not to ſay the Poverty of the Goſpel. 'Tis that which has not been contented to have the name of a Church
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49837:65"/>
common to others, but would, for it ſelf alone, ſet up a Title of Sovereignty, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending no Spiritual things can be diſpos'd of but by its Order; and thus by a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption as ridiculous as inſolent, calls it ſelf the Abſolute Judge of the whole World. But 'tis that alſo which is eaſily known, however we obſerve it, either by its Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or Followers, its Statelineſs or Poverty. We need no great Learning or Subtilty on this Account, ſo many Controverſies are uſeleſs, ſince it ſufficiently makes it ſelf ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent; it at firſt ſight ſhews it ſelf to any one who will take the leaſt notice of it, its Works do plainly enough manifeſt its Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. But if we will yet make a farther diſcovery of it, we need but read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and compare the matter of 'em with the Practices of this Spiritual Head and its Party. It may be you'l ask me, what I find ſo ſtrange in it? I anſwer, that I meet with what does really aſtoniſh me, and what in my Opinion, ſhould others too, as well as my ſelf. I obſerve in it, I know not what, that does both grieve and fright me, that fills me with compaſſion, and ſtrikes a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour upon me, which I ordinarily expreſs by Sighs and Groans. I obſerve I know not what Political Order, that ſubſiſts by Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick, and the Sale of Spiritual things, that uſes the Name of God, to make the Laws of Men more regarded, and to oblige the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49837:65"/>
People willingly to pay ſuch Impoſitions as are laid on 'em. Doubtleſs, there is no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch has fairer Pretences to make himſelf obey'd, and his Monarchy Univerſal. But this Scarlet, this Purple, theſe Crowns, do rather belong to Emperours, and Terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Princes, than to the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, who has aſſured us, that his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this World, <hi>John</hi> 18. 36. Which is a certain Argument, that under the name of Spiritual, this Temporal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is but a Tyrannical Uſurpation, much more grounded on the Predictions of the Revelations, than the Precepts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. 'Tis an Empire, whoſe Princes are as ſo many Slaves to Ambition and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, whoſe Votes are to be bought, and who, in the Election of a Head, that has no Power but what he attributes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, do bear a part even with Kings; who are ſcared without reaſon by his imaginary Thunder. What likelihood is there that the Truth of God, or rather God himſelf, can be found amongſt ſo much corruption and Bribery, which fills the Conclave? That Holineſs cannot be fix'd in its Throne but by the mercenary ſuffrages of theſe Men; That <hi>St. Peter</hi> cannot preſerve his Chair ſafe, but by ſecret and unjuſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances? What likelihood that men led by Intereſt, which doubtleſs is the greateſt God they own, and men whoſe manners
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49837:66"/>
are ſo impure and depraved, can any long time agree with the purity of the Goſpel? And by what Vices could they more juſtly fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Reprobate ſenſe? 'Tis really a very ſtrange thing to me, that the Doctors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church imagine themſelves, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an ill-grounded Preſumption, to be the moſt reaſonable of all men; and perceive not that they may err as well as thoſe who cry'd out, <hi>The Temple, the Temple, Jer.</hi> 7. 4. as they do now <hi>the Church, the Church.</hi> If it be ſo that it cannot err, why could not <hi>St. Peter,</hi> from whom it receives this great Privilege, beſtow it on that of <hi>Antioch?</hi> What could his Death contribute more to it than his Life? What ſignifie Places which have not had any particular Promiſes, or Seats which are not more ancient than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? In what have the Errors of <hi>Aſia</hi> out-done thoſe of <hi>Europe?</hi> What Holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles have ever fore-told that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of the Univerſe? What an unhappineſs has it been to other Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that they have not been able to continue even one Age without their Impurities, when the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> alone has been for fifteen free from Error? If ſhe muſt perſevere in the Faith, even to the end, what did <hi>St. Paul</hi> think when he plac'd her amongſt the wild Branches grafted on the Olive tree, and conſequently more liable to be cut off than its own natural ones; and why would
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49837:66"/>
he pronounce a threatning upon her, which was never likely to come to paſs? Thoſe certainly who have deſign'd to build her up, have ruin'd her, and thoſe who have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd, have deſtroy'd her. 'Tis extremely hard to make a juſt agreement between the love of the things of the Earth, and thoſe of Heaven? Or can Faith, Piety, or Virtue, ſubſiſt long amidſt Luxury and Abundance? Corruption generally begins with our Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which, when once ſo perverted as to arrive to their height, they have no manner of Reſpect for thoſe things that are Sacred; nothing then ſo Holy or Religious, which they turn not into Profaneneſs. 'Tis then men cannot away with the pure Doctrine; 'tis then they make Doctors after their own faſhion; that thoſe are inveſted with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity who leaſt deſerve it, and who inſolent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly violate the Divine Commands. 'Tis then their Preachers become fearful and coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, holding many things as indifferent, which are indeed very pernicious; and thus at length they allow, what at firſt 'twas un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to 'em even to connive at.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion has been too long conſiſtent with the Power of the World; the Princes and Nobility, the Magiſtrates and People ſide with it, and have, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages ſupported its Authority. This is a ſign of its not being the true Church, ſince that frequently needs Tryals of Affliction,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49837:67"/>
and whoſe greateſt Enemy is the World it ſelf. I muſt confeſs, that ſometimes the Preaching of the Goſpel does convert whole Towns and Provinces, nay, even Kingdoms; but they continue not long without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance; the Jealouſie of their Neighbours, the Treachery of their own People and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſet on foot by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and, what is worſt of all, their abuſe of Gods bleſſings, and their proſperous Condition, which is generally attended by a corruption of Manners, do in a little time create to 'em Croſſes and Diſquiets. Their Tranquillity and Peace would be extraordinary and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, if it laſted one Age; but this Terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrial reſting-place is not appointed for their Happineſs. How long has the Reign of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt been that of this World? how long have the Nobles, the Learned, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſubmitted to the Juriſdiction of the Church? How long has it been that true Chriſtians have not been perſecuted? How long ſince Servants are become greater than their Maſters? And by what new Goſpel have they made even <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Earth Tributary? No, no, there is no Society of men (let 'em be what they will) can have the name of a Church by any Temporal Eſtate, but by the alone Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Embracing and of teaching the incorrupted Doctrine and the Truth. Thus the Doctors of the Age, with an inſufferable
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49837:67"/>
Confidence, brag that they have not in the leaſt alter'd, either the Commandments of the Law, or the Articles of Faith, but that they have cloſely adhered to the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of 'em. But is it not to break the Law which God pronounc'd with his own Mouth, and writ with his own Hand, ſometimes to accuſe it, of being inſufficient, and then of ſuperfluity, and to retrench ſuch words from it, as they like not, when they deliver it to the people? Is it not to violate the Faith, to apply themſelves to any other Mediators than Jeſus Chriſt, and to ſubvert that Order he has appointed both for a Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and that of Sacraments? Thoſe who have but an indifferent knowledge of the Pagan Religion, muſt own that three parts of what they ſee practis'd in the Celebration of the Maſs; as to their Habits, their Geſtures or Ceremonies; were the invention of, and eſtabliſhed by <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> King of the <hi>Romans.</hi> Yet no one has ſo much as thought of making him paſs for a Prophet, or a Meſſenger ſent by God ſeven hundred years before the coming of Jeſus Chriſt, to declare what ſort of Worſhip and Religion that of the Chriſtians ſhould be. But hereupon to ſatisfie you, they give you fine words, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you, that theſe Ceremonies of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens by introducing of 'em into the Church are ſanctify'd. By the ſame reaſon thoſe things that were borrow'd by the <hi>Jews</hi> of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49837:68"/>
Idolatrous Nations, and which they brought into the Temple, ſhould have been ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd even by the Temple. But neither Prieſts, or Prophets ever imagined they could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe the jealouſie and anger of the Eternal, by a ſpecious excuſe ſo well devis'd. 'Tis unſeaſonable to uſe the flowers of Rhetorick, and to entertain thoſe with glittering colours, and appearances who only ſearch after, and ſtand in need of the Truth. 'Tis in vain to endeavour to pleaſe the eyes of thoſe whoſe Hearts are grieved for their ſins, who trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the voice of the Law-giver, and who believe the Divine Inſtitutions ſo very Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, that thoſe are looked on by 'em as guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sacriledge, who dare be ſo bold as to intermix Humane Inventions with 'em. I own that I cannot go into their Churches with a ſatisfy'd Conſcience, without a great diſquiet to my mind. For I ſee nothing on every ſide but the Pomp of <hi>Paganiſme</hi> ſhining forth, but ſuch things as are diſpleaſing to the Eternal, and which provoke his Jealouſie. I only ſee Altars and Chappels, each of which has its Patron, and are admirably beautify'd, in emulation one of the other, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of Ladies, and ſuperſtitious Trophies. How! you'l ſay, is not Jeſus Chriſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here? Yes doubtleſs, his name muſt be made uſe of to gain a Reputation to what is ſaid, and fairly to put off the reſt of their Inventions. But conſider a little, and you'l
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49837:68"/>
find that Leaven mix'd with it, of which we ought to beware; that dreadful poyſon, and that Character of Paganiſme. You'l per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Style that has little of that of the Scripture in it, but very much of the Schools and prophane Authors, and their chief Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity generally ſet out with Allegories, and ſome Meditations of the Fathers. You'l meet with a certain Miſcellany of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places, ſome ingenious pieces of Wit that pleaſe the Ears, and whoſe end for the moſt is not ſo much for the Preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and edifying of the People, but for the praiſe of the Preacher. It is palpable, that the Spirit of God does not inſpire 'em with theſe things, however good they may be in appearance, ſince they ſeem to be ſaid or done only to procure applauſe to the Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of men. I know there are ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt 'em who deſire to be accounted more ſincere than the reſt, by publickly profeſſing that they only Preach Jeſus Chriſt Crucify'd: But preſently they belye themſelves, and give demonſtrations of their being not leſs Superſtitious than thoſe they teach, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting with 'em open Acts of Idolatry. I could never like theſe Famous Preachers or Writers, who ſometimes find fault with the Jeſuits, and then with thoſe of other Orders, who ſeem to endeavour to make a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſome Points of Doctrine. Theſe are thoſe refin'd Hypocrites, who ſtrike at ſome
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:49837:69"/>
head of this Hydra, but never go to the Belly. If there were no Cardinals Caps, or rich Biſhopricks to be hoped for, they would not much care to be, or indeed ſeem better than others. For after all this do they not pray to Saints? Don't they obſerve their Feaſts? don't they fall down before Images? don't they go every day to Maſs? This is the fulneſs and complication of all errors, the ſource of all evil. This is that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sacrament, which ſince its firſt inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has extreamly chang'd its nature, and which was not ordain'd to be expos'd as a ſight only. This is that inviſible Miracle, that incredible ſign, without Elements, in which there is nothing that can be broken, nothing that can nouriſh, nor any thing which has the leaſt conformity with, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the things it ſignifies. This is, if we'l believe thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that true Supper, at which Chriſt made a propitiatory Sacrifice before he was Sacrific'd; at which his Body became Spiritual before he was glorify'd. What aery fancy! what ſtrange Doctrine, that would perſwade us that the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, which, except ſin, is altogether like ours, is whole on the Table, and whole under the accidents of the ſmalleſt piece of bread that can be imagin'd; that 'tis cover'd under a Point or Atome? Is not this to belye, and utterly deſtroy the Humanity of the Son of God? Is not
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:49837:69"/>
this to place Death in the room of Life, and to make our Adoration of no effect at all, inſtead of bringing us to a ſerious Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the Being of Beings, and of him who is really Man, as he is truly God.</p>
            <p>This imaginary <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is ſo full of Contradictions, that it renders the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ridiculous than the moſt ignorant of men. It has Conſequencies not to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd without Horror, and which thoſe who defend, cannot hear of, without Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Fury. What willfull Ignorance, what blind Paſſion, what Curſe, what Obſtinacy, does hinder the Exerciſe of their Minds? Open your Eyes ye ſtupid ones, uſe that Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding which is left you, and conſider that the ſame Communion, and the ſame Faith ſerves the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and that whatever Priviledge one has had above the other, they are chiefly diſtinguiſh'd by Time: The one believ'd in him who was to come, and the other, in him who was come: The former had no need of <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> and the latter judge it not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. The Prieſts, who are believ'd to make every day this miraculous Change, and by that, receive within 'em the Holy of Holies, ſhould be extraordinary ſanctify'd Men; and yet their Lives are ſo corrupt and vitious, that their Names, for a long Time, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come infamous even to a Proverb. I could never approve of their Maſſes, their Mattins,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49837:70"/>
their Veſpers, or indeed, of their Prayers, which are made in a Tongue the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not; a true Sign of their Slavery, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyranny.</p>
            <p>I liked not thoſe Traditions which are loaded with ſo much Heatheniſh Superſtition, that Purgatory, thoſe pretended Satisfactions, their Singing, their Feaſts, their Fraternities, their Proceſſions or Pilgrimages, their preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on their good Works and Merits. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their manner of proving theſe things by the Scripture, there is nothing in the World but may be proved by it alſo. They forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deduce 'em from ſome Paſſages, in which, neither the Prophets or Apoſtles would have been under figurative or obſcure Expreſſions, had they been neceſſary to the Chriſtian Worſhip. They have boldly ſet up Saints in the place of Gods, and their Canonizations of Men inſtead of that of God's, without conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it's Conſequence. In the mean while, the World groans under Multitudes of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Orders, which they every day inſtitute, ſometimes under one Name, and ſometimes another. They care not though they ruine Houſes, and whole Families, if they can but advance their own Intereſt, and leave enough to eſtabliſh themſelves under Retreats of Idleneſs. Children, by their Perſwaſion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey even their Fathers, and under Colour of devoting themſelves to God, and to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Prayer, they give themſelves up to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49837:70"/>
the imaginary Devotion of certain hollow Brains, and to the unprofitable Actions of a vain and ridiculous Obedience. And 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly apparent, that the more theſe things encreaſe, the more does the Anger and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Heaven afflict the Earth. I cann't imagine, how the Auſterity of ſome, agrees with the Licentiouſneſs of others; for, 'tis often obſerv'd in the World, that there are ſeveral bear the Name of <hi>Monks,</hi> who are far from being ſuch. They cunningly whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle themſelves into Houſes where they can get any Advantage, and holding the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men captive, enſlave the Men by their Means. Some are profeſs'd Litigious men, and yield not in this to their very Abbots; others are ſollicitous, and make whom they pleaſe to gain or looſe the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I could never endure thoſe <hi>Pagan</hi> Imitations, their Shaved Heads, which look as if bald. They ſeemed to me, to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomething away from the Shape and Beauty of Men, which God had given 'em; they were ſo far, in my Opinion, from bearing the Character of Holineſs, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing looked more deform'd and ugly. I have always been rather diſpleas'd with, and indeed deteſted, than admir'd their Hoods, their Cowls, their naſty Habits, and naked Feet. God having created Man after his own Image, endued him with the moſt perfect form of all Creatures; yet they have made
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:49837:71"/>
it more frightful than that of the moſt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous or wildeſt Beaſts.</p>
            <p>Since Jeſus Chriſt is come, Figures and Signs are needleſs, unleſs ſuch which he has appointed. 'Tis not bare Feet, or bald Heads, but Mouths to publiſh the Goſpel, that we want. I abhorr'd likewiſe to ſee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral go about cheating the World, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be poſſeſs'd by ſome Spirit that taught 'em to ſhow cunning Tricks, as not long ſince, thoſe of <hi>Loadun</hi> and <hi>Louvriers,</hi> of which People have been undeceiv'd, I would ſay to their Shame, if they had not wholly loſt it.</p>
            <p>I have not eaſily given Credit to their Miracles, whoſe Doctrine I could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. 'Tis the laſt Refuge <hi>Satan</hi> has, when he has loſt his Cauſe, to endeavour to dazle us with falſe Lights, and fright us with Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions. The Adventures of Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and People, are repreſented by our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediens; but the Religious, pretending to be poſſeſs'd, play the part of Devils, and act the Comedies of Hell. I have thought, that if their Doctors are extravagantly learn'd the People are brutiſhly ignorant; and that it pleaſes God, that his Children ſhould be moderately wiſe, that is, ſupply'd with ſuch a Wiſdom that ſuits not only with the Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Philoſophers, but with that of Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards and Fiſhermen; not ſuch who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Brutes and Sots, who knew no farther
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49837:71"/>
than the Animal Life, who take Pains only to eat and drink, and ſo dye as they have lived.</p>
            <p>I have obſerv'd that thoſe devout Souls which are ſo mightily eſteem'd, are zealous without Knowledge, ſuperſtitiouſly Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, have not a true filial, but ſervile Fear of God, which inſtead of eaſing, does with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Intermiſſion torment 'em; and at length, having made both Body and Mind uneaſie, does equally deſtroy 'em. They pray much leſs to the Creator than to the Creatures; they contemplate Jeſus Chriſt, the Virgin, and Saints in pieces of Wood and Stone, which are ſo far from being like 'em, that they do 'em great Wrong; and whatever they may tell us, when they proſtrate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before Images, ſince the Body cannot at all act without the Motion of the Soul; their Minds, without doubt, are fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 'em, as well as their Eyes. 'Tis true, many of 'em are taught to ſay, that they do not adore in 'em what we apparently ſee 'em do: They diſtinguiſh Adoration, and pleaſe themſelves to give different Names to things which they alike practiſe. They are become ſo ſubtle, that they belye not only our Sences and Reaſon, but their own too, being almoſt perſwaded, that they do not that which is done by 'em even with ſo much Heat and Fervency, and in the ſight of the whole World. The People who underſtand
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49837:72"/>
not theſe Sophiſtical Diſtinctions, do proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and allow themſelves in the commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Pure Idolatry: There are ſome pleas'd to keep 'em in this Error, no one takes the leaſt Pains to undeceive 'em.</p>
            <p>In fine, I have found that the greateſt part of 'em relye on their Birth; the firſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions they have receiv'd, from ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular City or Place, on Cuſtom or Intereſt. That they ſatisfie themſelves with the out-ſide of things, with Colours, Sounds, and other Vanities, which make 'em contemn the Simplicity of the Goſpel; for, Men not being able naturally to comprehend what is of the Spirit of God, will embrace no Religion, unleſs pompous, or will admit of the Government of Jeſus Chriſt, if not Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral. Nothing engages them to Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Devotion, but what makes a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Show. Nothing prevails with them ſo much as Muſick, Painting, Images, Gold, Azure, Purple, Scarlet, and external Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. In theſe, the Ladies every day em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy themſelves; and not being able longer to charm the men of the World, by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity become religious. Their great Care is to beautifie Churches and Altars, and rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to adorn the very Marbles; whilſt the Poor are naked, and groan under their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, not having wherewithal to defend 'em from the extream Rigour of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Shall I venture to ſay, that I obſerve
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49837:72"/>
nothing in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that bears the leaſt mark of true Chriſtianity; no, not their very Funerals, which ſhould at leaſt terminate all their Vanities? The Rich then, if we may believe them, may purchaſe their very Salvation; but the Poor, even after their Death, beg for the Payment of their Burial.</p>
            <p>'Twas now but neceſſary that God ſhould raiſe a ſort of men to reform thoſe who were arriv'd to the higheſt pitch of wickedneſs, or that to this purpoſe he ſhould ſend even Angels themſelves. Yet they have blaſted their Reputations, they have render'd their very names odious, whoſe deſign was only to keep 'em from the Pit of Perdition, and direct 'em in the ways of Salvation, who of their own heads have made no Inventions, who have aimed at no Benefice or Intereſt, but that of Reformation, and the Service of God. Theſe are the Meſſengers whoſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions needs no new Miracles, for they Preach no new Doctrine. They adhere to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, to Univerſals, to the foundations of the Truth, which grows not old, or decays, and yet is valued for its Antiquity. Their Sermons are ſuch, that there is no one who is reaſonable, but muſt own their coherence with the Scriptures, which they perſwade their People to read with care and diligence, ſaying, <q>Obſerve, if we deceive you, truſt not to us, or believe not our Doctrine, if
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49837:73"/>
you find it not confirm'd to you by that of the Prophets and Apoſtles.</q> Whilſt thoſe on the contrary, of the <hi>Roman</hi> perſwaſion, cry, after the manner of the Heathens, <hi>from hence, from hence, ye prophane,</hi> and do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways rather terrifie than afford comfort, their profeſſion being in every thing dark, and myſterious, nay, it ſets it ſelf out with the name of Myſtery. But I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that Religion a bad one, which deals with us with that frankneſs, which takes off the Veil of Superſtition, which diſperſes the darkneſs of Ignorance, and gives fuch light, underſtanding and conſolation to its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, as that of the Reform'd does. Yet theſe are the unpardonable crimes that excite the calumnie of ſo many enemies, who are both their Accuſers, and Judges, unjuſt and inconſiderate Judges, who continually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt 'em this ſhort ſentence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd into 'em by truly infernal Furies; <hi>you are damn'd, you are damn'd.</hi> Inhumane and Diabolical ſaying! which againſt the Prohibition of our Saviour himſelf, raſhly judges anothers Servants; and thoſe who are not under their juriſdiction. Theſe are the ſtrongeſt arguments, the ſofteſt remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, and the moſt charitable words they put into the mouths of their people, who bark and rail at their Brethren, inſtead of gently diſcovering their Errour to 'em, or hearing their Juſtification. How great is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49837:73"/>
the injuſtice of Men! And how do moſt of 'em deſerve that Condemnation they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce againſt their Neighbours. Such as theſe upbraid me with my Religion, who are unacquainted with their own, and know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of mine but from its Enemies. They condemn me upon the bare report of my Adverſaries; without hearing either my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate or my ſelf. But pray tell me, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Ladies, who are they for whom you have ſo great an Averſion? to whom do you talk with that Sharpneſs and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? Are they not thoſe who ground all their Religion on the Holy Scripture, who read, meditate on, love, and admire it, who learn it by heart, and who are ſo far from accuſing it of inſufficiency, that in that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone they find the Words of Eternal Life, ſufficient for their perfect Inſtruction and Comfort? Are they not thoſe whoſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity recalls you to that firſt Eſtate in which you were? When no Images were yet ſet up in your Churches, when you own'd no other Purgatory than the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, when going to Maſs, or taking the Cup from the People, was not ſo much as talked of, but meeting together for the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Bread, which was not elevated to make it ador'd? They certainly have not the Spirit of God, who hate ſuch as love his Word, and only covet to impart to you that Light, and thoſe Joyes they receive from it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:49837:74"/>
It muſt be acknowledg'd, theſe are ſtrange Hereticks, and are mightily in the wrong, to ſtick to Principles, not to preſume beyond what is written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6. and not to turn to the right hand, or to the left, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23. 6. They are to blame, not to conſent to the adding of other Commands to the Law, or other Articles to the Faith which is preſcrib'd 'em. In a word, they do very ill, that they mix not profane things with Holy. Indeed, I conſent with all my Soul to their Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; let what name they pleaſe be given 'em, I had much rather be one of thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, than one of the Catholicks of the Age. For, in effect, who are they whoſe Doctrine we ought ſo very much fear? Is it that of Kings and Princes, who are chiefly intruſted with the care of Secular things? Is it that of Magiſtrates, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide Differences between men? Is it that of the People, who are employ'd in Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Arts, or in Trading? Nothing leſs: 'Tis that of the Great Doctors of the Church, and whoſe Leaven ought to be ſuſpected by us, as that of the Phariſees. They are thoſe who do what they pleaſe, by the Priviledge and Authority of that Character they bear; who, under the name of Doctors, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, preach Errour effectually, and who, the more they are fill'd with Frenzy and Enthuſiaſm, the more would they perſwade us they are inlighten'd. They are thoſe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49837:74"/>
who have ſuch an extraordinary Opinion of their own Strength, that they brag that they are not only able to fulfill, but to ſurpaſs the Law. And though that obliges us to <hi>love God with all our Hearts, and our Neighbours as our ſelves,</hi> it is not ſufficient to bear teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Faith, or to magnifie their Works. To this muſt be added Councils which it comprehends not, and which tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port men beyond that perfect Love which it obliges us to. Several Traditions muſt be obſerv'd, which, tho' inſtituted by Pagans and Infidels, are become Sacred, ſince ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Church, and called Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical. To conclude, Many amongſt 'em do ſo abound in doing Good Works, that they have ſome to ſpare to impart to thoſe who do none at all; and in order too to their obtaining Eternal Life.</p>
            <p>It is not to be wonder'd at, that the Evil Spirit has prevail'd on men to forbid the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Holy Scripture; for 'tis impoſſible that thoſe impreſſions it makes on pious minds, which are ſeriouſly induſtrious in the ſearch of Salvation, can conſiſt with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Religion of the Times. It has often recover'd me from a Lethargy, into which I was inſenſibly plunged by the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the World. By it I have learn'd to know both my Beginning and my End. It has infus'd into me both a Love and Fear of my Creator: it has made me fear his
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49837:75"/>
Judgments, adore his Goodneſs, and lay claim to his Mercy. It has caus'd me to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſuch various, and ſo many proofs of his Providence, that I had no room left to doubt of it. I never read it, but I became better'd by it, yet not with that Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as I could have wiſh'd. Therefore I thought 'twas neceſſary for me to begin it often, and never to leave it off. I met with ſo many Truths in it, from one end to the other, that I have not follow'd their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who only ſeek after Contradictions in it, who will not diſtinguiſh Times, or conſider the different reſpects why things have been ſaid. It is not dangerous to ſuch, who have good deſires, it ought not to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted by 'em; it does inlighten 'em, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct 'em, and ſhews 'em the way that leads to Eternal Life. It is impoſſible that He who ſuſpends his Judgment, who is not ſway'd by Paſſion, Cuſtome, or Prejudice, who is only govern'd by Reaſon, and ſeeks after the Truth, ſhould not find it by this way; and thus to ſearch after it, comes from the Spirit of God. What ſhall I ſay more? He muſt not expect to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, who does not love this Word above all things; and who does not evidence the love he has for it, by frequent read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. For many will ſay with their Mouths, they love that which indeed they do not. They in vain pretend to excuſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49837:75"/>
themſelves, upon the Credit of their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in ſaying, that 'tis not intelligible by all, that every one expounds it to his own Advantage. If they are to be believ'd, God ſpake to his Children only to deceive 'em, and not to be underſtood by 'em. Thus there is no way left either to read or know any thing. Every paſſage hath its diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Senſe, whereupon we muſt refer our ſelves to our Maſters. Even thoſe which ſeem moſt Evident, are moſt obſcure, and oftentimes ſignifie the contrary of what they ſeem to ſignifie. As for Example; when 'tis ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any likeneſs, Exod.</hi> 20. verſ. 4. this ſignifies, we muſt fill our Churches with Images: when 'tis ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Neighbour, Exod.</hi> 24. 16. by this is meant, thoſe are to be called Hereticks, who embrace no other Religion but what is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by the Word of God. Then when 'tis ſaid, ſpeaking of the Communion, <hi>As often as you ſhall eat of this Bread. 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 26. The Sence of this is, That you ſhall eat no Bread. And when 'tis ſaid, <hi>Tarry one for another.</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 33. The meaning of this is, That Maſſes ſhall be ſaid without Communicants. And thus of the reſt. They render the Scripture intricate and difficult only, that they may be conſulted as <hi>Oracles,</hi> and their Authority abſolutely depended on.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:49837:76"/>
If Philoſophy was ſo neceſſary for men to diſcharge their Duty to God, the mean and ordinary people of the World could never know any thing of it, againſt that place of Scripture, which ſays, <hi>That he hath hid theſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed 'em unto Babes. Matth.</hi> 11. 25. It is not to be hoped, that a well eſtabliſh'd Coufe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, can either clear or diſſipate this Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſince moſt men deſign only the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the firſt Opinion they have receiv'd, or ſetting a Value and Reputation on their Profeſſion. Diſputes indeed are dangerous, for thoſe who manage 'em ordinarily grow paſſionate and ſharp, or ambitious of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt; at leaſt, of not being overcome. I have never obſerv'd thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to deal with Sincerity; their Religion has ſo little of Religion in it, that it ſcarce ever ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers 'em to act in any thing, without conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Humane Intereſt, or without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtudied all manner of Tricks and Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: <hi>As the Children of this World are in their Generation wiſer than the Children of light.</hi> Luke 16. 8. They are aſſured of the Victory before the Combat. They are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they ſhall be countenan'd by thoſe who preſide, and be applauded by the Voice of the Multitude. They are aſſur'd of him on whoſe Account the Diſpute is made, and to have the better by any way whatever, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs that of Reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:49837:76"/>
Otherwiſe, they amuſe the Standers by, and loſe the time in repeating long Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and will always ſpeak thrice as much at leaſt, as their Adverſaries. They will not diſpute with equal Strength or Arms; they will be both Party and Judges, and pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Sovereign Juriſdiction over all things that belong to Religion; will not be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined but by themſelves; they will admit of no Advice, or allow any Councils but what are made up of men all obliged to the ſame Intereſt. They will reſolve nothing but after their own Way, their own Policy, their own Cuſtoms, or Prejudices, which confirm their Errors, inſtead of removing of 'em. But, if they were well aſſur'd that Truth was of their ſide, it being certainly the ſtrongeſt, tho' the leaſt known; yet ought they to be ſo chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to us, as to ſay, <hi>Aſſemble the learned'ſt of your Men together, and we, on our parts, will do the ſame; We'll receive your Reaſons in Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſigned with your hands, and we'll return you ours, with the ſame Freedom.</hi> But theſe Hypocrites, theſe ſelf-intereſſed Men, of ſeared Conſciences, will not run the Riſque of ruining, at once, both their Religion and their Fortunes. 'Tis not their deſign to draw men to their Party by the Power of Truth; they know no way to do it, but by Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by Liberty, and fair Promiſes. They make it their buſineſs to find out, amongſt thoſe of the Reform'd Religion, and eſpecially the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49837:77"/>
Paſtors, a <hi>Judas,</hi> who may be prevailed on to ſell himſelf, to betray their Maſter and Brethren. But, to what purpoſe theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, or theſe Compulſions? To what end, this Diſpute, or rather, this inſufferable Wrangling? Is it not only to prove to us, that thoſe who proſtrate themſelves before Images are not Idolaters? Is it not to perſwade us to go every day before the Altar, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the going forward and backward, the Geſtures, the myſterious Ornaments of a Prieſt that turns his Back upon us, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the People to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> to ſeveral repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Words and murmuring Noiſe of a Tongue, which for the moſt part, they underſtand not. 'Tis for this they make ſo much Diſorder in the World; 'tis for this they promiſe, they threaten, and perſecute the Saints even to over-come 'em, as far as 'tis poſſible for 'em, and make the very Stars fall from Heaven. 'Tis this which does afflict us, and this which does often amaze us. 'Tis this would make us ſink under our Fear and Sorrows: but on this account, the Holy Trinity comes to our Aſſiſtance, the Holy Ghoſt does comfort, and withal aſſure us, <hi>That the Son ſhall not loſe one of thoſe whom the Father has given him. Joh.</hi> 17. 12. and 18. 9. Moreover, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Truth, are ſo gloriouſly trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant over their Enemies, that they find themſelves caught in thoſe Snares they laid for others.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:49837:77"/>
Whoever ſhall attentively read the Books of Controverſie, ſo refin'd as they are at this Time, will perceive, that thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Religion do apparently ſurpaſs all others; and that there are only ſuch who are contentious, ſtupid, or harden'd, and given up even to a reprobate Senſe, that receive not from 'em as full Satisfaction as Reaſon it ſelf can offer.</p>
            <p>To conclude, <hi>Ariſtander,</hi> I am forc'd to tell you, that I find not ſo much as one remaining Spark of the pure Goſpel, any ſhadow of true Chriſtianity, in all this <hi>Roman</hi> Hierarchy. 'Tis a Body labouring under an irrecoverable Leproſie; an Hydropick Body, puffed up with it's ill Humours. 'Tis ſick of a Lethargy that ſleeps the Sleep of Death, from which, no Voice is ſtrong or loud enough to awaken it. On the contrary, I am fully ſatisfy'd with the Profeſſion of the Reformed Churches, which inſtruct me in the Divine Commands, without any Mixture of Humane Inventions. I find there preached, the pure and plain Truth of a <hi>Jeſus Chriſt crucified; 1 Cor. 2. 2. who brings healing under his Wings, Mal. 4. 2. who makes the Deaf to hear, and the Blind to ſee;</hi> and in a Word, even <hi>the Dead to riſe again, Matt.</hi> 11. 5. to enjoy the for-ever-bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Life of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, who lives and reigns eternally.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:49837:78"/>
            <head>A LETTER to a Lord at Court, who would have perſwaded him to turn <hi>Catholick.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce the Care you are pleas'd to have of me in all my Concerns, extends it ſelf even to the Salvation of my Soul, I humbly beg your Lordſhips leave to give you my Opinion on this Subject; and 'twould be an extreme Pleaſure to me, was it not contrary to yours. 'Tis not without Aſtoniſhment that I have obſerv'd in the World ſo many different Religions, which are all maintain'd by their Patrons, with an equal Poſitiveneſs, one believing he has as much Reaſon on his ſide as the other. But 'twas yet greater Amazement to me, to ſee that God does ſo manifeſtly make himſelf known to men that will not liſten to him, and who are ſo obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, not to meditate either on what they hear or read, and perceive not what they even ſee. I can hardly look on thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Contempt, or Indignation, who have no Religion but from their Education, or Chance, on whom Cuſtom is abundantly more prevalent than Reaſon it ſelf. They lazily adhere to what they firſt meet with, and, betraying themſelves, dread nothing more than to know the Truth, for fear of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49837:78"/>
being oblig'd to embrace it. I believ'd then, my Lord, that to preſerve our ſelves from theſe Errors, 'twas highly neceſſary to have recourſe to Principles; and therefore I dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſearch'd the Scriptures, which are ſaid, and with reaſon, to be <hi>Divinely inſpir'd, 2 Tim.</hi> 3. 16. and in which are found <hi>the Words of Eternal life, John</hi> 6. 68. From hence I firſt learn'd, that God would be acknowledg'd the ſole Author, as well as the only Object of Religion; and that he is ſo jealous of his Commandments, that whoever preſumes to add to, or retrench from 'em, is guilty of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege. Theſe Holy Oracles, by ſo many evident Proofs, confirm the Faith of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and the Truth of Chriſtianity, that 'tis impoſſible for any one, unleſs ſtupid, or hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Wickedneſs, to doubt of 'em. The beſt things that have been ſaid by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers are here urg'd, with more Power and Efficacy; There is nothing wanting in 'em, either for regulating our Manners, or the Worſhip of God, or the Comfort of our Souls. But in theſe we find not any of thoſe new words, which 'twas neceſſary to invent to expreſs their new Doctrines. Theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with what is ſufficient to know of our Sovereign Good, and what they declare not, was not neceſſary to be ſaid. We muſt not imagine that they are to be interpreted as we pleaſe. They are ſufficiently explain'd by themſelves, to be underſtood by thoſe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49837:79"/>
who ſincerely deſire it, and perfectly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form 'em of what true Chriſtians ought not to be ignorant of. If the Myſteries in 'em are obſcure, the Precepts are clear, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Darkneſs of the one, or the Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the other, allow men to contribute any thing to 'em, but their Obedience. I read 'em then, <hi>My Lord,</hi> not out of bare Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, with deſign to contradict 'em, or that I may be look'd on as more learned by it; but that I may enjoy the Comforts of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life, and acquaint my ſelf with thoſe of a future. I diſpute not of Grace, but ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ask it. I dive not into the Secret of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination, but I look after, and endeavour all poſſible ways to find my ſelf concern'd in it. I don't believe that God is obliged to give me an Account of what he is pleas'd to do from his Juſtice or his Mercy. All theſe nice Queſtions belong to the Great Doctors of the Age, who allow themſelves this Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; who ſo much abound in their own Senſe, and who are ſo full of Pride and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, that they will not humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves even at the Voice of the Almighty; to which, would they yield that reſpect and Submiſſion as they ought, was of it ſelf alone, ſufficient to reconcile all the Differences of the World.</p>
            <p>The Impreſſions which the Word of God makes on thoſe who read it with Care and Attention, do enlighten 'em to diſtinguiſh
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49837:79"/>
between the true Religion and the falſe, and to reject all thoſe Traditions which are not coherent with its Doctrine, or confirm'd by its Authority. Who doubts but that the Primitive Chriſtians, the more calmly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce themſelves in the World, have been forc'd to allow of many things, which have been made uſe of as degrees to Superſtition, and which at length have been eſtabliſh'd as inviolable Laws? Men have been always vain in their imaginations; have <hi>ſought out many inventions, Eccl.</hi> 7. 29. and I know not by what <hi>Science, falſly ſo called, 1 Tim.</hi> 6. 20. have fram'd to themſelves ſome fantaſtick Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's and Notions, which they have plac'd in the room of Truth. They can't reliſh the wholeſome Doctrine, they deſire ſomething to pleaſe the eye, they entertain themſelves with colours, and ſounds, or with ſome my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious Appearances, the ſubject of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and Amazement. The plainneſs of the Goſpel ſuits well with their temper; they are ſo far from following the ſteps of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, to <hi>go forth from the Camp bearing his Reproach, Heb.</hi> 13. 13. that they will admit of no Religion, but what is glorious and ſplendid, and conſequently of none but what <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s conformable to the Kingdom of this World. They have their Religious men, and what is worſe, Women too, who look askew on thoſe <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat believe not as they do, and who on the credit of ſome Impoſtor, or on the teſtimony
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49837:80"/>
of one Party alone, condemn the other to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit all his Happineſs. They often put me in mind of thoſe honourable Women who did ſo perſecute thoſe two Apoſtles, St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and were never at eaſe till they had forc'd 'em out of <hi>Antioch.</hi> Obſerve then, How not only vain and uſeleſs Devotion is, but pernicious too, when it is not inſpir'd by the Spirit of Diſcretion, or the Knowledge of the Truth. Many of 'em impoſe on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Laws which God never inſtituted, and are as thoſe concerning which 'tis ſaid, <hi>Who hath required this at your hands? Iſa.</hi> 1. 12. From hence have the People been corrupted, become Superſtitious, and from Superſtition proceeded to Idolatry. 'Tis from hence ſo many Judgments remain yet amongſt us, from hence is God's Anger kindled againſt men; from hence are they provok'd one againſt another; and to compleat their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 'tis from hence they rather harden their hearts than ſtrive to reform 'em.</p>
            <p>For my part, my Lord, I joyn with thoſe who conſtantly adhere to the Scriptures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who turn not from 'em either to the right hand, or to the left, who exhort us to the reading of 'em, and who deſire their Sermons may be try'd by this Touch-ſtone. When we ſee 'em deal thus fairly, I cannot doubt but that their Calling is lawful, and that they make a part of the Univerſal Church. But I beware, as much as 'tis poſſible for me, of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49837:80"/>
the Leaven of the Phariſees of the Age, who would have the Ordinances of men be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to thoſe of Divine Inſtitution, whoſe Religion is but a Pretence to make 'em the more eaſily procure what their Ambition or Avarice prompt 'em to. I confeſs I can't but wonder that they reflect not on thoſe words of Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>But in vain do they worſhip me, teaching for Doctrines the Commandements of men, Matth.</hi> 15. 9. and that they believe not that many, even when they deſign to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, diſpleaſe him. Who are theſe men? Not Kings, Nobles, or Magiſtrates, that are intruſted with the management of Temporal things; it muſt be thoſe then who are charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the government of Spiritual ones, who abuſing the credulity of the People, and the name of God himſelf, make themſelves obey'd even as God. I am amaz'd that what he ſays in another place ſo expreſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Wiſe and Learned men of the World, does not terrifie 'em, and oblige 'em to quit their own Doctrine. But they think ſo arrogantly of themſelves, that they look on thoſe with pity, not to ſay rage, who dare contradict 'em, or in the leaſt doubt of their Infallibility. Yet, as a juſt puniſhment on 'em, they are ſo blinded, as to be ignorant of, and ſuffer others to be ſo too, what it has pleas'd God <hi>to reveal unto Babes, Matth.</hi> 11. 25. to the confounding of the greateſt part of the <hi>Mighty,</hi> of the <hi>Noble,</hi> and the Learned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:49837:81"/>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 26. All ſorts of Reaſon teaches us, that he ſpake only to be underſtood, that he caus'd his Word to be written that it might be read, and hid it not but from thoſe who are loſt. If he condemns a wilful and brutiſh Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, he diſapproves of a haughty and vain Knowledge, the Spring from whence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe ſo many Diſputes, which do infinitely more hurt than good, and which maintain not ſo much the Truth, as the firſt received Opinion. He believes, He follows Chriſt who perſecutes him; He believes himſelf of the number of the Faithful, whoſe whole Faith conſiſts but in an indiſcreet Zeal, in the ſtrength of Errour, and in being poſitive and obdurate. The men of the Age acquaint not themſelves with this Truth, or if they do, 'tis from thoſe of their own party, who confirm 'em in their belief, and neither the one or the other allow of any Religion which agrees not with their Conveniencies. If any of 'em have a ſenſe of their Diſeaſe, it is agreeable to 'em, they take ſuch pleaſure in it, that they'l not endeavour after any cure. But to conclude all, I will maintain, that men have no ſurer ſign of their Election, than their love of the Word of God; and that thoſe ſhall not be ſaved who have not loved it more than Honour, Riches, and the moſt amiable things in the World.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:49837:81"/>
            <head>A LETTER to an Officer of the Crown that often diſcours'd to him of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN Your Lordſhip does me the Honour to diſcourſe to me of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, my Reſpect will not give me leave to anſwer you, but only to liſten to you: yet, if I am longer ſilent, I fear you may judge me inſenſible of what I have the moſt lively Senſe. 'Tis this makes me take the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of entertaining Your Lordſhip with a few Lines concerning my Belief, and not without wonder, that others are not of the ſame Opinion with me. As ſoon as my Senſe and Reaſon began to be ſerviceable to me, I with great Care and Diligence ſearch'd the Holy Scriptures; and I have no other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion but what I learn'd from thence. I never believed that ſome dark and abſtruſe Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were contrary to others that were clear and evident; and I have found moſt of 'em ſufficiently plain, fully to inform me of what I ought to believe. I never thought that God would ſpeak to his Children only to deceive 'em, or not to be underſtood by 'em. Thoſe who have good Inclinations, never read the Scriptures but they profit by 'em. If thoſe whom Curioſity (it may be) has invited once to read 'em, don't continually perſevere in
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49837:82"/>
doing ſo, 'tis a ſhrewd Sign, they have had no Operation on 'em. 'Tis not the meek or humble, the plain men of the World, or even the ignorant, that promote Hereſies; thoſe who do this, and then maintain 'em, muſt be both malicious and learned too. 'Twas no diſheartening to me to ſee the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Goſpel bear a certain Character that made the World deſpiſe 'em, and they the World. They are dejected, as if out of their Element, and did but out of Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance participate of others Joys. Above all, in the Exerciſe of their Religion, they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor all manner of Superſtition, and believe that 'tis an Abuſe and a high Crime, to mix the Inventions of men with the Ordinances of God. If our good Intentions were capable of making our Vows and Offerings equally acceptable, all Religions would be good ones: But, the <hi>Jealouſie of the Eternal, Exod.</hi> 20. 5. will not ſuffer us to profane holy Things, or ſanctifie profane ones; or, to ſpeak yet more fully, to conſecrate Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. Let the moſt rational men read and read again the Scriptures, and let 'em frame a Religion according to the Rules they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, <hi>without preſuming beyond what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, 1 Cor.</hi> 4 6. and I am confident, they cannot make any other than that which I profeſs, and, by the Grace of God, will do the ſame all my Life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:49837:82"/>
            <head>A LETTER to <hi>Monſieur de la Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiere,</hi> who begged his Opinion in Writing, upon the Books of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie he had made.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Don't pretend to anſwer in one Letter, ſo many Books which your Revolt has oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd you to write in Oppoſition to that Religion you have forſaken, and in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that you have cloſed with. I muſt only ſay, I could never, with all the Senſe and Reaſon Heaven has been pleas'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow on me, reconcile what I ſee in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to what I read in the Holy Scriptures. I have ever conſulted both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I have read the Writings both of the one and the other, that I might the better know 'em by their Words and their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But, I find that your Doctors ſerve themſelves of too much Art and Cunning, to be believ'd; their Divinity is ſo refin'd, that they undo themſelves by their own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty. They mix with it I know not what Leaven, of which our Saviour bids us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and which indeed has not the taſte of true Bread, or the heavenly <hi>Manna.</hi> Thoſe of the Reform'd Religion, on the contrary, act with greater Sincerity, adhere to the Rule of the Scriptures, which do more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:49837:83"/>
our Underſtandings, and give great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Tranquillity to our Minds.</p>
            <p>Let who pleaſe imagine he has clearer Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations than I have, ſuch as I have, I find in their Doctrine as full Satisfaction as a reaſonable Soul can wiſh for in the Search of the Truth. Why then all this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie? If we have never ſo little Knowledge of the Will of God, or how jealous he is of his Commandments, we cannot ſee the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> without condemning it. We are extreamly in the Wrong, to call thoſe Chriſtians, who have no ſign of true Chriſtianity, who ſpeak not in the ſtyle of Jeſus Chriſt or the Goſpel, to whom the Words of Eternal Life are ſtrange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth. If we miſtake any one Word in their Hearing, 'tis enough to make us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd Hereticks; they look a skew on us, and 'tis very likely, we ſhall paſs for Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers even in our own Country. Inſtead of this, they diſcourſe only of the Prayer-book of our Lady, and the Office of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, of their praying by Beads, of their devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves to St. <hi>Francis,</hi> or St. <hi>Roch;</hi> and thoſe defective Inſtructions ſhew that thoſe who inſtruct them thus muſt needs be very bad Maſters. What, Sir, would you have me go, and whither would you have me go? Can I look on thoſe People without Pitty, who know not what they ſay when they either pray or ſing? But, above all,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49837:83"/>
Can I ſee ſo many poor miſerable Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who have never done, and who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God is only pleas'd with Numbers and Repetitions? Can I, without Horror, take Notice of their Beads and Altars, dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to any other than the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, where the Creature is placed in the Room of the Creator? Can I ſee on the high Altar that which is called the Bleſſed Sacrament, an ineffectual Object, an inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Sign, Bread which is neither broke, given, or receiv'd by any one; that repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents neither the breaking of the Body, or the ſhedding of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, and which is nothing leſs than the Sacrament? Would you have me go every day to obſerve ſacrificing Prieſts that cannot tell you them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what they ſacrifice, and of the Supper of the Lord, make a Show only? Sometimes, they ſpeak with a loud Voice, and yet not to be underſtood; and ſometimes ſo foftly, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce ſuch Myſterious and Sacred Words, that 'tis not permitted to thoſe who are by, tho' never ſo devout, to hear what is ſaid, leſt they prophane it. They turn to the right hand and to the left, in Imitation of what the Heathens called <hi>Vertigines,</hi> and from whence, they expect to procure ſome efficacious and admirable Vertue. This is the higheſt pitch of Superſtition; They elevate what they hold in their hands, to make it adored; to which, they attribute the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:49837:84"/>
Names of God, of the Hoſt, of the Body of our Lord, and of the Sacrament; and all theſe, if we may believe them, are conſiſtent together, without any Contradiction. Sure theſe Men muſt be of a very eaſie Belief, to imagine, that that which they make with their own hands, and which they conſecrate, ſhould be made the God who made them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then not conſidering that the Supper ought to be a common Meal, and therefore muſt have Company at it, or without having Conſideration of that Paſſage, which ſays, <hi>Stay one for another,</hi> the Prieſt, for the moſt part, eats alone, and ſometimes, gives it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſome particular Perſon; which, from Abuſe and Cuſtom, they forbear not to call the Communion. What is yet worſe, the taking away of the Cup; which cannot, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Account, more at one time than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be juſtified, and that evident Reaſon of it's Concomitancy, tacitly accuſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of not having well thought what he did, do correct, or rather violate his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and ſo add Sacriledge to Blaſphemy. Moreover, thoſe who have but an ordinary Tincture of Humane Learning, very well know from what Invention, from what Source have flow'd their Holy Waters, ſome fix'd, others running, or carryed about. Their Enſignes, their lighted Tapers at Noon-day, their Images of Saints, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid Gods. To conclude, all their
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49837:84"/>
Feaſts, their Proceſſions, their ſhorn crown'd Heads, their pontifical Ornaments, their pompous Ceremonies, that make the Croſs of Jeſus Chriſt of no effect, do ſufficiently of themſelves prove, that they preſerve no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Plainneſs or Simplicity of the Goſpel. The principal Heads of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (in this truly Univerſal) have been afraid to omit any one ſingle Act of the Religions of this World, as if God needed to borrow even from his Enemies, new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, or other Methods to procure greater Honour to himſelf. Thus Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm is not quite aboliſh'd, and we may ſay, that there are yet ſuch Remains of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Idolatry, that the Heathens even now do triumph, in ſome Meaſure, over the Chriſtians. Here we find nothing pure or compleat, nothing that bears any Marks of the firſt Inſtitution, every thing is chang'd and corrupted; and, to uſe their own terms, there ſeems to have been in all things, a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Tranſubſtantiation. But, what would become of the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity, that was ſet on Work from the time of St.</hi> Paul. 2 <hi>Theſſ<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 7. and by what would Believers know it, if it had not the Marks of Infidels? All theſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations have come to paſs for the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Kingdom, or rather that King, who advances himſelf above all others, and who only uſe the Name of God to authorize his own Laws againſt thoſe of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:49837:85"/>
'Tis with the Head of this Church as with the Church he governs; 'tis but warily obſerving him, and we may be undeceiv'd. He is elected only by political Intrigues and Briberies, and his Government is but a Trade; for, under it Sins are taxed, and Pardons to be ſold. He ſets himſelf up as the abſolute Judge of Divine, as well as Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, of the Living as the Dead, and diſpoſes even as he pleaſes, of our very Souls, ſending ſome to Hell, and others to Paradiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He beſtows on ſome Eccleſiaſticks in great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, Titles of Vanity and Pride, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizes only ſuch who defend his Tyranny and Uſurpation. What a Succeſſor is this of St. <hi>Peter?</hi> How does he imitate Jeſus Chriſt? What a Vicar is he, to ſubvert all the Orders of his Lord, and who turns his Poverty, his Humility, and Sufferings, into Riches, Pomp; and Pleaſures? Yet, he has the Multitude on his ſide, the Arm of Fleſh; and for a Time, he is even impower'd to contend againſt the Saints and overcome 'em. Theſe are Ills ſcarce to be remedy'd, becauſe eſteem'd Vertues, and in which, many find all the Conveniences ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable. With theſe, are Hypocrites, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and Covetous, pleas'd, and all ſuch who are byaſs'd by Intereſt. Theſe are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the timerous, the weak, the brutiſh, the ſtupid, and to all thoſe who are harden'd by Cuſtom. The Antiquity of theſe Errors is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make 'em valu'd as Sacred Laws, in the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49837:85"/>
Opinion of the Vulgar. Even many of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by ſuiting themſelves too much to the preſent time, and not fore-ſeeing what might come to paſs, have confirm'd 'em by conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at 'em. To cite their Teſtimony on this Account, is not to defend our own Cauſe, but accuſe theirs, 'tis to have Recourſe to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for want of Reaſon. They themſelves ow<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> that they are not infallible, and in this matter, that their beſt Thoughts are very imperfect, if not altogether conſonant to the Scripture. The Doctrine of the true Church is purely Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal &amp; Divine, and not to be authoriz'd by that which is not ſo. Theſe famous Preachers, which you deſire ſo much I ſhould hear, are Acceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to all theſe Abuſes, and deal very unfairly, unleſs they undeceive the People. There is no Religion but may be eloquently diſcours<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>; nay, there are thoſe which preach up Mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y admirably well, but we may ſay of Eloquence, as of Beauty, that 'tis a gift of Heaven, beſtow'd as well on the Wicked as the Good. The Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the greateſt part of 'em is indeed to ſet forth themſelves, and to procure ſome ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Preferments which now exceed the Secular. Is it to preach Jeſus Chriſt, to conceal the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>oſt important and chief part of his Commands? They freely enlarge themſelves in diſcourſing on the Precepts of the <hi>Second Table,</hi> but fear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than ſaying the leaſt that can be on the <hi>Firſt,</hi> which does alone ſanctifie all our Devotion, and without which, 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God. Inſtead of exhorting their
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:49837:86"/>
Hearers to read the Scriptures, they do all that lies in their Power to make 'em miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſometimes accuſing 'em of being imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and at others, of Obſcurity. As if God, the ſole Author of Religion, had command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us to do our Duties but by halfs, and had ſpake to us that he might not be underſtood. Sure, Sir, thoſe who talk at this Rate, do but deride their Hearers, and have not a mind to be believed. For my part, I am ſo much perſwaded, that what is evident and clear in the Word of God, is ſufficient fully to inform me in the Methods of Salvation, that I boldly declare, if I cannot attain it by theſe, I will not endeavour after it. In a few Words, I adhere with all my Heart to the Creed, I am obedient, as far as 'tis poſſible for me, to the Ten Commandments, I pray as our Saviour himſelf has taught me, and receive the Sacraments of Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper after that manner which he himſelf has inſtituted 'em. This being the Summary, not only of the Law but of Faith alſo, a Collection of the very Life of the Scriptures, to be of this Belief, and to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves with thoſe who make the ſame Profeſſion, is indeed to be in the Church.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:49837:86"/>
            <head>A LETTER to a Lady who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to prevail on him to go hear ſome of the Famous Preachers of the <hi>Roman Church.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOU have often preſs'd me, <hi>Stephanie,</hi> to go hear the moſt excellent, at leaſt ſuch who are moſt eſteem'd amongſt your Preachers: And you now oblige me to tell you what I wiſh I could paſs by in ſilence. But your abſolute commands are laid on me to give you my judgment of 'em, and I ſhall then have done it, when I have aſſur'd you only that I find in 'em what has been fore-told of 'em, That their Diſcourſes would be florid and ſublime; That they would pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh great and wonderful Things. But I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that this would not ſatisfie you, and that it was neceſſary for me to deliver my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion yet more fully, altho' abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to yours. I muſt freely confeſs to you, that I never go into your Churches without doing violence to my ſelf, or indeed being out of my Element: For, ſince I cannot joyn with 'em in their Religious Exerciſes, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be there without giving or receiving ſome ſort of Scandal. Firſt, I conſider the Place, and the Perſons, and the ſight of each of 'em is equally offenſive to me. I obſerve thoſe who ſing, or who pray, to have little or
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49837:87"/>
no Underſtanding, and whoſe Stupidity is a juſt Puniſhment on 'em for their blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Commandments of men, and for that religious Veneration they pay to Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which are exalted where God alone ought to be worſhipped. 'Tis not at all pleaſing to me to ſee the Preacher in his Surplice or Rocket, whiter than Snow, border'd with a rich Lace, ſtarch'd, ſtiffen'd, and ſo ſet out, that he has much ado to go from one ſide of the Pulpit to the other. Theſe things, without doubt, preach already to thoſe who will underſtand. They have all their meaning and Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The very Habit of the Biſhop, is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Myſteries, and is not one of the ſhorteſt Lectures of the Schools. 'Tis, it may be, the better to repreſent the Diſgrace and Sufferings of Jeſus Chriſt, and to ſhew, that the Servant is not greater than the Maſter. When I obſerve any of 'em thus ſplendidly attired, I ſay to my ſelf, Nothing will come from him but what is like him; and I expect ſuch, and not fewer Flowers than the Poets have beſtowed on their fabulous <hi>Aurora.</hi> 'Tis true, ſome of 'em do not thus externally adorn themſelves, as not ſuiting with their courſer Ruſſets, or their Vows of Poverty, which will not allow 'em to wear ſuch gay things, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Sacred they may be. Yet, this Vow ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom reaches beyond the Garb, and the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Capuchins</hi> and <hi>Recolets,</hi> is not leſs Rhetorical than that of Biſhops and Abbots.
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49837:87"/>
However, they all begin after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by making a Sign of a Croſs, of Humane and Superſtitious Invention, which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly apply to the three Perſons of the God-head; by which, as I believe, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to draw a Bleſſing on themſelves and their Preaching. By a like Abuſe, they name their Text in <hi>Latin,</hi> the Repetition of which, many of 'em affect in the ſeveral parts of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. And I cann't imagine, why they ſet a greater Value on the Ancient Language of Popes, than on that of Jeſus Chriſt, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, in which, things were at firſt writ or declar'd. This is but a falſe Luſtre, by which they make their Diſcourſes more florid, ſince they are preſently forc'd to pronounce it in a known Tongue, and to explain it. 'Tis but a ſtrange Noiſe with which they would ſurprize the People, and make that paſs for ſome great Myſtery, which is indeed but a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Superfluity. Then do they begin with a Preface, not leſs artificial, myſterious, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legorial than the reſt, as a Pattern of what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, which they be ſure fail not to conſecrate with an <hi>Ave-Maria.</hi> Here I find my ſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly diſturb'd; I who believe all Religious Worſhip ought to be terminated in the alone Perſons of the Trinity, and that that Honour which is due to them, ought not to be given to any one beſides. If the Bleſſed Virgin does take notice of 'em, and hear what they ſay, 'tis not to be queſtion'd, but that ſhe is highly offended
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:49837:88"/>
at 'em, and that the greateſt kindneſs they can receive from Her is this, that ſhe ſays, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Example of her Son, <hi>Pardon them, O Lord, they know not what they do, Luke 23. v.</hi> 34. and that 'tis anſwer'd. Theſe are the wilfully ignorant; who ought to know it, and who deſerve to be thus harden'd, ſince they are more careful in the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Traditions, than the Scriptures. As to the Preaching in general, both of the one and the other, tho' the Matter and Form of it may differ, yet they all agree in their firſt ill Principle, and ſet it out with the Name of a Church, which is ſo very convenient for 'em, that they can by no means quit it. Doubt not, <hi>Stephanie,</hi> but that I have with attention heard theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Preachers, who are follow'd by ſo many, who are admir'd by the Nobility, and approv'd of by the Learned themſelves. I have indeed found that they had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and eloquence, and many other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Gifts which indifferently happen to the Bad men of the World, as well as the Good. Nay, I have obſerv'd in the Faces of ſome the marks of Holineſs, whoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe was ready to have deceived me, and poſſeſs'd me with a good Opinion of their Belief, if, either a little before, or preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, I had not diſcover'd their being, as it were, poyſon'd with unhappy Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that did not at all ſavour of the Purity of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:49837:88"/>
the Goſpel. Theſe Wiſe men have put me often in mind of thoſe Fools, who after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for ſome time diſcours'd very ſeriouſly, could not forbear returning to their firſt Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Here is I know not what mixture of good and bad things, I know not what My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, of which they have ſome ſort of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, but cannot expreſs. Here are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd thoſe Tares the Devil ſowed in the Church, that Leaven of the Phariſees, the poyſon of Humane Inventions, which make us now ſay, what the Sons of the Prophets did in the time of <hi>Eliſha, There is Death in the Pot, 2 Kings 4. v.</hi> 40. They all equally betray God's Cauſe, their deſigns being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to preach up themſelves; and proceeding from a wilfull Blindneſs, to the efficacy of Errour, at length come to believe what they endeavour to make others do. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend truly to preach Jeſus Chriſt crucify'd, that it may be ſaid they preach him, that his Name may be made uſe of to their praiſe, and ſet a greater Reputation on their Sermons. But they plainly demonſtrate they do not abſolutely believe in Him, ſince af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this they fail not to preach up a St. <hi>Fraen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> a St. <hi>Dominic,</hi> to whom they attribute as much Power, and as many Miracles, as to Jeſus Chriſt himſelf. The higheſt Points of their Divinity are grounded more on <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> than St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and theſe mighty Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Chriſtian Faith have no greater
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:49837:89"/>
Maſters than Pagans and Infidels: They make by their Diſcourſes the Simplicity of the Goſpel pompous, and diſguiſe all Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Sincerity, ſo that when I have well obſerv'd em, they always appear'd to me ſuch as Huckſters and Mountebanks, which corrupt the Word of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 17. But if this Compariſon ſeems too injurious to 'em, and that you deſire one more favourable and lofty; I muſt tell you that I place 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Angels, but thoſe who bear the name of Wormwood, who make the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters bitter, and deſtroy a great part of the World, I place 'em amongſt thoſe who are permitted to do Miracles, to ſhake the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Heaven, to make the Stars fall from it, to tempt, to ſeduce, to perplex, as much as 'tis poſſible for 'em, the very Elect. We have had ſo many warnings of theſe things, as if they came to paſs only to make good the Scripture that has foretold 'em. This is the true Lamp that directs us in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Satan's Character, amidſt ſo much Brightneſs they borrow to dazle us. If we do hear any thing that is pure and holy from 'em, their falſe applying of it, and thoſe ſubalternate ends they ſerve by it, does preſently make their Deſign plain; all their ſeeming Reality does not prevent our eaſie perception of the Myſtery of Iniquity. I don't mean thoſe whom you your ſelf ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove not of, whoſe Words and Actions
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:49837:89"/>
are ſo light and extravagant, that their Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs ſeems to be rather the entertaining of their Hearers with ſome pleaſant, diverting Diſcourſe, than the correcting, or inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 'em; who rather act the part of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medians, than ſeriouſly do that of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. I don't mean ſuch who ſpend their time in Converſation with the Ladies, who run from Houſe to Houſe ſo much the more eagerly, ſince what they are commanded by God, to be Husbands of one Wiſe is look'd on as a Crime by 'em, and therefore the more ſtrictly forbid by men. There are none ſet their Affections more on Secular things than theſe Church-men, nor any thoſe of this World more than they who pretend to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon it.</p>
            <p>I know very well, that Biſhops are advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be free and familiar with thoſe they have the Care of; this heretofore ſignified, that they ſhould entertain 'em kindly, viſit 'em upon Occaſion, exhort and comfort 'em. But, now the meaning of it is, That they muſt play with ſome, hunt with others, treat ſplendidly, and keep a Noble Table. In theſe things, the Revenue of ſo many rich Biſhopricks is employ'd, and ſeem to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd on many of 'em, that they may the better be enabled to live at Court, whilſt their Flocks know no one ſo little as their Paſtor. Muſt that which is the Art of all
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:49837:90"/>
Arts, the Cure of Souls, the Adminiſtration of holy Things, be now the Profeſſion of the Ambitious, the Prodigal, the Covetous, and ſuch who addict themſelves to Pleaſures. What Edification can we expect from ſuch who aim at nothing but their own Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and preach only, that by that they may riſe to theſe high Preferments they ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly covet. The paſſionate Deſire by which you ſo frequently urge me to hear theſe men, puts me in mind of that great Zeal the Wives of <hi>Solomon</hi> had for their falſe Gods, and who were never quiet till they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd on him to conſent to their Idolatry. You would have me ſubmit my Judgment to that of ſuch numbers of honeſt men, who both approve of, and follow 'em; not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, that the true Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel meet not with ſo much favour from the Princes of the People, or the Multitude. No, no, their ſincere and plain Profeſſion allows 'em not to procure ſo much the Approbation of the World; they ſtick firmly to the true Rule; they expound the Scriptures by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they intrude not on things they have not ſeen; and, as the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, deliver not what they have not receiv'd. You here ſee, <hi>Stephanie,</hi> what a too fond Opinion of your own Belief, a no leſs vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than ſuperſtitious Piety, common to the devout Zealous Women of the Times, have
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:49837:90"/>
provoked you to make me ſay. 'Tis too ſhort an Anſwer, in Compariſon of what I could have return'd, and it may be longer than what you deſir'd to have had; But, if you cannot conſent to my Opinion, be ſo kind at leaſt, to approve of my Obedience, who aſſure you that I am</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
